<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6094468</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-018-0253-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal applications of animal species by the local communities of Punjab, Pakistan</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><address><email>altaf_mughal450@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Umair</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><address><email>Umair.bot@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Abdul Rauf</given-names></name><address><email>raufabbasi5@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>Noor</given-names></name><address><email>noor@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9978-3866</contrib-id><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Arshad Mehmood</given-names></name><address><email>arshad799@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Zoology, Women University of Azad Jammu and Kashmir, Bagh, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 8293</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16821.3c</institution-id><institution>School of Agriculture and Biology, </institution><institution>Shanghai Jiao Tong University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Statistical Wing, Department of Mathematics, Women University of Azad Jammu and Kashmir, Bagh, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Fisheries and Aquaculture, Punjab, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2215 1297</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412621.2</institution-id><institution>Department of Environment Sciences, </institution><institution>COMSATS University Islamabad, </institution></institution-wrap>Abbottabad Campus, Abbottabad, Pakistan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>55</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Different species of animals are being utilized in traditional therapies by various cultures for a long time and such uses still exist in folk medicine. The present study aimed to document animal-based traditional therapies used by the local communities of Jhelum and Lahore districts of the Punjab province, Pakistan.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Field surveys were conducted in 2015&#x02013;2016 in six different sites of the study areas. Data were collected through semi-structured interviews and face to face conversation with local informants.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The ethnomedicinal uses of 57 species of animals including mammals, birds, fish, reptiles, amphibian, and invertebrates (30, 25, 25, 7, 3.5, and 3.5%, respectively) were documented. Meat, oil, brain, fats, milk, eggs, and skin were the most utilized body parts. <italic>Ovis orientalis punjabiensis</italic>, <italic>Francolinus francolinus</italic>, <italic>Sperata sarwari</italic>, <italic>Channa punctata</italic>, <italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>, <italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>, <italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic>, <italic>Labeo rohita</italic>, and <italic>Carassius auratus</italic> were reported for the first time to treat human diseases, i.e., allergy, epilepsy, fever, joint pain, and backache, to act as aphrodisiac, and to enhance memory. <italic>Streptopelia decaocto</italic> and <italic>S. tranquebarica</italic> were the most frequently utilized species with highest frequency of citation (32 for each). <italic>Columba livia</italic> depicted highest fidelity level and used value of 92.86% and 0.89, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Being agro-pastoralists, the inhabitants of Jhelum possess more traditional knowledge compared to Lahore. The present study could be important for conservation and sustainable use of animal biodiversity in this region. Additionally, detailed study on chemical profiling and bioactivities may lead to animal-based novel drug discovery.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Animal species</kwd><kwd>Traditional therapies</kwd><kwd>Local communities</kwd><kwd>Pakistan</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Different body parts of wild and domestic animals are being utilized since ancient time in the prevention and protection of human health disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and such therapeutics are termed as zootherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Zootherapy has profound history with wide geographical distribution. It has been reported that Chinese used earthworms to treat diseases nearly 4000&#x000a0;years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Over, 1500 animal species have been documented in Traditional Chinese Medicines, which are used to treat various diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Around 15&#x02013;20% of the Ayurvedic medicines is of animals&#x02019; origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and more than 500 species of invertebrates are used to cure both common and complex illnesses in India [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Petting, watching, stroking, and working with different animal species can be relaxing, can lower heart beat and stroke, and can be physically beneficial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Chemicals from animals and plant species have been a part of human culture to improve health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Certainly, animals as therapeutic agents have been contributing significantly to the prevention and treatment of health disorders across the globe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. It has been estimated that 8.7% of the essential chemicals used in protective drugs are animal based [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Because of immunological, analgesic, antibacterial, diuretic, anesthetic, and anti-rheumatic properties, insects are essential components of modern drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Chitosan, derived from exoskeleton of insects, is used as an anticoagulant, to lower cholesterol levels in the blood and to repair tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Potential anticancer drugs have been isolated from the wings and legs of Asian sulfur butterflies and Taiwanese stag beetles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Pharmaceutical industries are testing many animal species for drug discovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The best-known example is of snake venom that inhibits angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE), responsible for the conversion of angiotensin hormone from an inactive precursor, which causes narrowing the blood vessels and raises blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Similarly, a number of compounds having a defensive role such as biogenic amines, steroids, alkaloids, and peptides have been reported in the secretions of amphibians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. These chemical substances possess diverse pharmacological effects including cardiotoxic, myotoxic, and neurotoxic activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Wildlife is an important but poorly known source to treat many infectious diseases, particularly the zoonotic disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The trade in wildlife for food, medicine, and products and as pets, among other uses, involves hunting and the sale of animals of many species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Ethnomedicinal information collected form aboriginal peoples contribute significantly to recognize novel biological resources for commercial utilization, mainly in pharmaceutical industries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In addition, expansion of modern medicines is based on traditional knowledge of indigenous communities. Consequently, documentation of the traditional knowledge of indigenous people is imperative, because in the recent era modern drug development has greatly been affected due to loss of socioeconomic and cultural characteristics of local communities around the globe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Pakistan has a rich diversity of animals including 195 &#x0201c;species of mammals&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], 668 &#x0201c;species of birds&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], 195 &#x0201c;species of herptiles&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], over 1000 &#x0201c;species of marine and fresh water fishes&#x0201d;, and 5000 &#x0201c;species of insects&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. A number of these species are being utilized in traditional health care. However, ethno-medicinal uses of animal species have rarely been recorded. Furthermore, we imagine that ethnozoological knowledge of local communities residing in settled areas is threatened due to increasing population, urbanization, and industrialization, which should be documented before depletion. Therefore, the current survey aimed to assess and document ethnomedicinal uses of animal species among the local communities of two districts Jhelum and Lahore of the Punjab province, Pakistan.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Field sites</title><p id="Par9">Ethnozoological survey was conducted in 2012 and 2016 in four sub-areas of district Jhelum: Jhelum city, Burha Jungle, Rohtas fort, and Rasool barrage, and four sub-areas of district Lahore: Lahore city, Bara dari, Chung, and head Baloki (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study area</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">District Jhelum is located towards North of the river Jhelum and surrounded by district Rawalpindi in the North, Azad Kashmir from the East, Gujrat and Sargodha districts in the South, and district Chakwal from the West [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Total population of the district is 1.223 million, out of which 71% live in rural areas and the rest of 29% is urban population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Approximately, 98.5% of the population is Muslim, while among minorities Christians are in majority with 1%. Awan, Syed, Kashmiri, Ghakar, Gujjar, Mughal, Jat, and Janjua are the major ethnic groups in this area. Jhelum is a semi-mountainous area, receives 880&#x000a0;mm mean annual rain fall, and has 23.6&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C average annual temperature. The inhabitants of Jhelum are agro-pastoralists because of their origin from different parts of Azad and Jammu Kashmir (India). Inhabitants in the rural areas of Jhelum live in mud and brick houses and speak Punjabi and/or Pothohari language. Agriculture, livestock, and mining are the main sources of income. Khewra salt mine in Jhelum is the world&#x02019;s second largest salt mine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. District Jhelum is rich in animal diversity, particularly due to the Mangla dam on the Jhelum River. This wetland is an excellent habitat for bird species. Scientists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] reported 336 species of birds including 153 breeding residents, 115 winter visitors, 15 summer visitors, 39 passage visitors, and 14 occasionally recorded species. The Mangla water reservoir also provides habitat and food for a variety of fish species. The mammalian fauna of the area is mainly of Oriental origin. The main mammalian species belong to <italic>Canis</italic>, <italic>Herpestes</italic>, <italic>Lepus</italic>, <italic>Lutra</italic>, <italic>Manus</italic>, <italic>Mus</italic>, <italic>Rattus</italic>, <italic>Suncus</italic>, <italic>Sus</italic>, <italic>Viverricula</italic>, and <italic>Vulpes</italic> genera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par11">Lahore is also called as the heart of Pakistan, because it is the hub for culture in the Punjab region and Pakistan as a whole. District Lahore is located towards the North of the river Ravi and is surrounded by Kasur district in the South, district Sheikhupura in the North West, whereas in the East and North-East it is bordered by Indian Punjab [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. According to a recent survey, the total population of the district is 11.33 million. More than 40% of its inhabitants are below the age of 15 and the same percentage of the population is literate. Almost all inhabitants of this area live in an urban environment. Lahore is the second largest city in Pakistan after Karachi and 32nd largest district in the world. Around 94% of the population is Muslim comprising Sunni and Shia while 6% are minorities, i.e., Christians, Hindus, and Sikhs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Majority of the people in the district speak Punjabi, however, in different dialects, which make it a diverse speaking population area. Urdu and English languages are also spoken and understand by a large number of the population. The average annual rain fall in Lahore district is about 490&#x000a0;mm. The winter in Lahore is cooler than Jhelum with temperature ranging from 1.2 to 15&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C whereas in summer temperature rises up to 46&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Nevertheless, Lahore district has greater extension in its urban area. However, still ancient shrines, gardens, cemeteries, traditional buildings, canals, and roads are present, which are the home of many birds, amphibians, and reptiles. In previous records, more than 240 bird species have been documented in Lahore; however, this number is restricted to 85 species now, due to urbanization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Changa Manga forest near Lahore is a wildlife hotspot including wild boar, deer, jackal, nilgai, Asiatic wild cat, and Old World vultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Increasing population, urbanization, and industrialization depicted great impact on the floral and faunal diversity of Lahore district. Virgin areas of the district supporting natural flora and fauna have been devastated and replaced by buildings, roads, and industries. A greater part of the native flora has been replaced by alien plant species, which is gradually removing the fauna. Such invasion of exotic species poses risk to the biotic uniqueness of the local ecosystems and traditional knowledge of local communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In a study conducted in Nishtar and Wagah towns of Lahore, about 49 species of birds were reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In a recent survey, 3 amphibian and 15 reptilian species were reported from Kasur near Lahore [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data collection and analysis</title><p id="Par12">Before the field survey, prior consent was taken from the Department of Zoology, Women University of Azad Jammu and Kashmir, Bagh, Pakistan. In addition, we also followed the ethical guidelines of the International Society of Ethnobiology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ethnobiology.net">http://www.ethnobiology.net</ext-link>) during the study. Questionnaires and semi-structured interviews were conducted to document ethnomedicinal uses of animal species. Data were collected from 100 informants in each district including farmers, herdsmen, hunters, teachers, and traditional health practitioners (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Informants were selected based on their knowledge on medicinal uses of animal species. Mammals, birds, herptiles, and fish species were recognized using field guides &#x0201c;<italic>Mammals of Pakistan</italic>&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], &#x0201c;<italic>Birds of Pakistan</italic>&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], &#x0201c;<italic>Amphibian and Reptiles of Pakistan</italic>&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], and &#x0201c;<italic>Freshwater Fishes of Pakistan</italic>&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Data on ethnomedicinal uses and cultural values were analyzed using various indices such as frequency of citation (FC), use value (UV), relative importance (RI), fidelity level (FL), similarity index (SI), principal component analysis (PCA), and cluster analysis (CA).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ethnographic data of local informants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variables</th><th>Demographic categories</th><th>Jhelum</th><th>Lahore</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Gender</td><td>Male</td><td>100</td><td>99</td></tr><tr><td>Female</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Experience</td><td>Health practitioners</td><td>19</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>Farmer</td><td>35</td><td>45</td></tr><tr><td>Teachers</td><td>31</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>Herdsman</td><td>10</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>Hunters</td><td>5</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Age group</td><td>20&#x02013;30</td><td>5</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>31&#x02013;40</td><td>27</td><td>21</td></tr><tr><td>41&#x02013;50</td><td>36</td><td>34</td></tr><tr><td>51&#x02013;60</td><td>26</td><td>21</td></tr><tr><td>Above 60</td><td>11</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Education</td><td>Post-graduate</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Graduate</td><td>12</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>SSC</td><td>20</td><td>23</td></tr><tr><td>Primary</td><td>34</td><td>45</td></tr><tr><td>Illiterate</td><td>34</td><td>24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Residence</td><td>Rural</td><td>77</td><td>65</td></tr><tr><td>Urban</td><td>23</td><td>35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Religious background</td><td>Muslim</td><td>98</td><td>99</td></tr><tr><td>Non-Muslim</td><td>2</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Frequency of citation (FC)</title><p id="Par13">FC is the number of informants who reported medicinal uses of each species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Relative importance (RI)</title><p id="Par14">The relative importance (RI) of animal species cited by the informants is calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{RI}=\mathrm{PP}+\mathrm{AC} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>RI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>PP</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>AC</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where PP is the number of pharmacological properties (reported specific ailments) attributed to a species divided by the maximum number of properties attributed to the most resourceful species (species with the highest number of properties). AC is the number of ailment categories treated by a given species divided by the maximum number of ailment categories treated by the most resourceful species. A value of 2 is the highest possible value for relative importance (RI) indicating the most versatile species with the greatest number of medicinal properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Fidelity level (FL)</title><p id="Par16">The value of FL highlights the percentage of informants who declare the similar uses of some species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. It is calculated by<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{FL}\ \left(\%\right)=\left(\mathrm{Np}/N\right)\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi>FL</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Np</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where Np is the informants&#x02019; number, calming medicinal use of animal species contrary to a specific disease and <italic>N</italic> is the total number of informants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Use value (UV)</title><p id="Par18">The use value (UV) can be used to prove the relative importance of species. UV of a species is calculated using the equation:<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{UV}=\sum U/n $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mi>UV</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where UV is the use value of a species, <italic>n</italic> is the number of citations per species, and <italic>U</italic> is the number of informants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Similarity index (SI)</title><p id="Par20">Similarity index (SI) is calculated using the formula:<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{SI}={M}_{\mathrm{s}}/{M}_{\mathrm{t}}\ \left(0\ \mathrm{SI}\le 1\right) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mi>SI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>SI</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>M</italic><sub>s</sub> is the similar number of medicinal applications in present and previous research records of a species and <italic>M</italic><sub>t</sub> is the total number of medicinal applications in present research records.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par22">Data on traditional uses of animal species to treat various ailments were statistically analyzed using principal component analysis (PCA) and cluster analysis (CA) methods with the help of statistical software as described earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Ethnography</title><p id="Par23">The data were collected from male Muslims (98%) and non-Muslims (2%) in Jhelum, with both genders male (99%) and female (1%) with religion as Muslims (99%) and non-Muslims (1%) in Lahore. The respondents have different occupations as health practitioners, farmer, teachers, herdsman, and hunters from both districts. They have the education as primary, illiterate, SSC, graduate, and post-graduate. Most of the respondents have age 41&#x02013;50, while lowest age respondents belong to 20&#x02013;30-year age in both districts. Most of the respondents belong to almost two thirds from rural and the other from the urban area in both districts Jhelum and Lahore (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Ethnomedicinal application of animal species</title><p id="Par24">The inhabitants of the study area possess significant traditional knowledge and use different animals to treat various health disorders. Out of 57 animal species, 55 were used in Jhelum and 54 in Lahore to treat nervous disorders, paralysis, joint pain, asthma, and fever and to heal wounds and used as aphrodisiacs (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Nutritional deficiency, lack of a hygienic environment, and social evils may attribute to the high prevalence of these diseases in both study areas. <italic>Bufo stomaticus</italic> (Indus valley toad), <italic>Heteropneustes fossilis</italic> (scorpion cat-fish), <italic>Lissemys punctate andersoni</italic> (Indian flap-shelled turtle), and <italic>Oligochaeta</italic> spp. (earthworms) were the commonly utilized species in Lahore. Conversely, the inhabitants of Jhelum use <italic>Hoplobatrachus tigerinus</italic>, (Indian bullfrog), <italic>Naja naja naja</italic>, (black cobra), <italic>Pteropus giganteus</italic> (Indian flying fox bat), and <italic>Bagarius bagarius</italic> (bag arid catfish) to treat various diseases.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of medicinal uses of animal species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3">Sr. #</th><th rowspan="3">Scientific name, Common name, Vernacular name, Code</th><th colspan="5">District Jhelum (J)</th><th colspan="5">District Lahore (L)</th><th colspan="4">Previous reports</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2">PU/MA</th><th rowspan="2">Disease treatment</th><th rowspan="2">FC</th><th rowspan="2">UV</th><th rowspan="2">RI</th><th rowspan="2">PU/MA</th><th rowspan="2">Disease treatment</th><th rowspan="2">FC</th><th rowspan="2">UV</th><th rowspan="2">RI</th><th rowspan="2">Diseases treated</th><th rowspan="2">Ref.</th><th colspan="2">SI</th></tr><tr><th>J</th><th>L</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="16">Amphibian</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;1</td><td><italic>Bufo stomaticus</italic> L&#x000fc;tken, Indus Valley toad, Maidani daddo, BS</td><td/><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>Skin/T</td><td>Allergy</td><td>7</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.3</td><td>Thelitis, dermatitis, decubitus wounds, ripened abscess, brunchest, pneumonia, bolianerengia</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;2</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Hoplobatrachus tigerinus</italic> (Daudin), Indian Bullfrog, Wada daddo, HT</td><td rowspan="4">Fat/T</td><td>Sexual enhancement</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="4">0.38</td><td rowspan="4">0.39</td><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4"/><td rowspan="4">Diarrhea, dysentery, cold and cough, burn, wound, acidity</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0</td><td rowspan="4">0</td></tr><tr><td>Muscular pain</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Headache</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="16">Reptiles</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;3</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Lissemys punctata andersoni</italic> Webb, Indian Flap-shelled Turtle, Hara Kachupra, LPA</td><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6">0.00</td><td rowspan="6">0.00</td><td>Carapace/T</td><td>Allergy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.29</td><td rowspan="6">0.3</td><td rowspan="6">Rashes, burns, asthma, lung diseases, cough, tuberculosis, Diarrhea, indigestion, malaria fever, diabetes, urinary obstruction, arthritis, Bronchitis, menorrhagia, sexual dysfunction, wounds, dermatitis, acne, piles</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Fat/T</td><td>Sexual enhancement</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Backbone pain</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Epilepsy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Cession</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Bile/T</td><td>Strangulation</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;4</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Laudakia agrorensis</italic> (Stoliczka), Monitor lizard, Goh, Wada Kirla, LA</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Burn</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="2">0.22</td><td rowspan="2">0.38</td><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2">0.00</td><td rowspan="2">0.00</td><td rowspan="2">Cough, fever, jaundice, burn, joint pain, skin disease, arthritis, malaria, sexual stimulant</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">0.51</td><td rowspan="2">0</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual male power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">&#x02003;5</td><td rowspan="5"><italic>Saara hardwickii</italic> (Gray), Indus Valley spiny-tail ground lizard, Sanda, UH</td><td rowspan="5">Fat/T</td><td rowspan="2">Sexual enhancement</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="5">0.84</td><td rowspan="5">1.56</td><td rowspan="5">Fat/ T</td><td>Sexual enhancement</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="5">0.73</td><td rowspan="5">1.21</td><td rowspan="5">Increase sexual power</td><td rowspan="5">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="5">0.25</td><td rowspan="5">0.25</td></tr><tr><td>Weakness</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Muscular pain</td><td>5</td><td>Ear pain</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>joint pain</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="2">Backbone pain</td><td rowspan="2">5</td></tr><tr><td>Head-ach</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">&#x02003;6</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>Naja naja</italic> (L.), Black cobra, Kala Naag, NNN</td><td rowspan="2">Skin/ T</td><td rowspan="2">Sharpen eye side</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="3">0.50</td><td rowspan="3">0.39</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Muscular pain</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="3">0.53</td><td rowspan="3">0.90</td><td rowspan="3">Muscular pain, arthritis and sexual weakness, leprosy, cancer</td><td rowspan="3">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="3">0</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual weakness</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Oil/ T</td><td>Snake bite</td><td>2</td><td>Oil/ T</td><td>Snake bite</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;7</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Echis carinatus sochureki</italic> Stemmler, Sind Valley saw snake viper, Daba sap, ECH</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ T</td><td>Snake bite</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="2">0.29</td><td rowspan="2">0.38</td><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2"/><td rowspan="2">0.00</td><td rowspan="2">0.00</td><td rowspan="2">Snake bite</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">0.50</td><td rowspan="2">0</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual enhancement</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="16">Mammals</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">&#x02003;8</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>Lepus nigricollis dayanus</italic> Blanford, Desert hare, Jungli saya/Jungli khargush, LND</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="3">0.87</td><td rowspan="3">1.18</td><td>Hair/ T</td><td>Burning sensation</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="3">0.78</td><td rowspan="3">0.92</td><td rowspan="3">Tonic, chicken pox, wheezing, stomach and joint pain, high blood pressure, Asthma, burning sensation, paralysis.</td><td rowspan="3">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]</td><td rowspan="3">0.67</td><td rowspan="3">0.50</td></tr><tr><td>Weakness</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>Asthma</td><td>4</td><td>Asthma</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;9</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Hystrix indica</italic> Kerr., Indian crested porcupine, Kanday wali say, HCR</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="2">0.36</td><td rowspan="2">0.77</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="2">0.50</td><td rowspan="2">0.60</td><td rowspan="2">Skin infection, rheumatic pain, colic, boiled, stomach-ache, foot mouth disease, easy delivery of a child, premenstrual pain, weakness and muscle fatigue, asthma</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">0.08</td><td rowspan="2">0.14</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>10</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;10</td><td><italic>Pteropus giganteus</italic> (Br&#x000fc;n.), Indian flying fox bat, Chamgadar, PGI</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Enhance sexual male power</td><td>7</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.38</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Enhance sexual male power</td><td>9</td><td>0.33</td><td>0.30</td><td>Asthma, bronchitis, enhance sexual power</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]</td><td>0</td><td>0.20</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;11</td><td><italic>Rattus rattus</italic> (L.), House rat, Wada Choha, RR</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>8</td><td>0.13</td><td>0.38</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>7</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.30</td><td>Convulsions, semen enhancement, wounds healing, joint pain</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]</td><td>0.20</td><td>0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">&#x02003;12</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>Ovis orientalis</italic> punjabiensis Lydekker, Urial, Heeran, OO</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td rowspan="3">Enhance power</td><td rowspan="3">18</td><td rowspan="3">0.83</td><td rowspan="3">0.40</td><td rowspan="3">Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="3">0.73</td><td rowspan="3">0.91</td><td rowspan="3"/><td rowspan="3"/><td rowspan="3">0</td><td rowspan="3">0</td></tr><tr><td>Backbone pain</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual enhancement</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;13</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Hemiechinus collaris</italic> (Gray), Long eared desert hedgehog, Chotay kanday ali say/Kandyari Choha, HCO</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>9</td><td rowspan="2">0.33</td><td rowspan="2">0.77</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td rowspan="2">Joint pain, Backbone pain</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="2">0.30</td><td rowspan="2">0.60</td><td rowspan="2">Rheumatic pain, body ache</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">0.50</td><td rowspan="2">0.50</td></tr><tr><td>Backbone pain</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;14</td><td><italic>Canis aureus</italic> L., Golden jackal, Gidar, CAA</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>7</td><td>0.29</td><td>0.38</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>8</td><td>0.25</td><td>0.30</td><td>Rheumatic pain, body ache</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]</td><td>1.0</td><td>1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;15</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Herpestes javanicus</italic> (E. Geoffroy Saint-Hilarie), Small Indian mongoose, Neola, HJ</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>8</td><td rowspan="2">0.27</td><td rowspan="2">0.77</td><td rowspan="2">Fat/ T</td><td rowspan="2">Sexual power</td><td rowspan="2">9</td><td rowspan="2">0.22</td><td rowspan="2">0.30</td><td rowspan="2">Sexual power, impotence by males</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">1.0</td><td rowspan="2">1.0</td></tr><tr><td>Backbone pain</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">&#x02003;16</td><td rowspan="5"><italic>Camelus dromedarius</italic> L., Dromedary, Ount, CD</td><td rowspan="5">Milk/ O</td><td>Hepatitis B and C</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="5">0.75</td><td rowspan="5">0.78</td><td rowspan="5">Milk/ O</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="5">0.67</td><td rowspan="5">1.50</td><td rowspan="5">Acidity, hepatitis B and C, malaria, cold, coughs, stannic pain, migraine headache, lumbago (for buffalo)</td><td rowspan="5">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]</td><td rowspan="5">0.33</td><td rowspan="5">0.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Cancer</td><td rowspan="4">10</td><td>Diabetes</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Hepatitis B and C</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Allergy</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Cancer</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">&#x02003;17</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic> (L.), Goat, Bakri, CAH</td><td rowspan="2">Milk/ O</td><td rowspan="2">enhance energy sexual power</td><td rowspan="2">20</td><td rowspan="3">0.86</td><td rowspan="3">0.80</td><td>Milk/ O</td><td>Enhance sexual power</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="3">0.90</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td><td rowspan="3">Fever, eye tonic, tonsillitis, asthma, tuberculosis, menstrual disorder, toothache, anemia, cough, dysentery, bronchitis, jaundice, diarrhea, blindness, joint pain, sexual enhancement, rhinitis, skin blisters</td><td rowspan="3">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Testis/ O</td><td>Enhance sperm production</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Fever</td><td>8</td><td>Bone soup/ O</td><td>Heal wound</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">&#x02003;18</td><td rowspan="5"><italic>Bos taurus</italic> L., Cattle, Gay, BT</td><td>Ghai and fat/T</td><td>Feet wounds</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="5">0.73</td><td rowspan="5">1.55</td><td>Ghai and fat/ T</td><td>Feet wounds</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="5">0.82</td><td rowspan="5">1.21</td><td rowspan="5">Fever, bone fever, memory loss, paralysis, asthma, stomach ache, gastritis, diarrhea, eye infection, sore throats, tuberculosis, pesticide, measles, wound, cough, body pain, poison effect, acne and facial pimples, blood cancer, appetite stimulant, malaria, hysteria</td><td rowspan="5">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]</td><td rowspan="5">0.43</td><td rowspan="5">0.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Milk and meat/O</td><td rowspan="3">Body pain, Fever</td><td rowspan="3">10</td><td>Milk and meat/ O</td><td>Body pain, Fever</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Ghai and milk/O</td><td>Poison effect</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Testis and milk/ O</td><td>Enhance the sperm production.</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Ghai and milk/O</td><td>Poison Effect</td><td>2</td><td>Testis and milk/ O</td><td>Enhance the sperm production</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">&#x02003;19</td><td rowspan="12"><italic>Bubalus bubalis</italic> (L.), Buffalo, Mujh, BB</td><td>Milk and turmeric/O</td><td>Wound</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="12">0.74</td><td rowspan="12">3.08</td><td>Milk and turmeric/ O</td><td>Wound</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="12">0.72</td><td rowspan="12">2.39</td><td rowspan="12">Pain, wound, jaundice, ascites, rheumatic pain, weakness, osteoporosis, thrombosis, improves heart strength, pre-menstrual pain, injury</td><td rowspan="12">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>]</td><td rowspan="12">0.11</td><td rowspan="12">0.09</td></tr><tr><td>Milk and almond/ O</td><td>Enhance physical and mental health</td><td>1</td><td>Milk and almond/ O</td><td>Enhance physical and mental health</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Colostrum/ O</td><td>Enhance immunity</td><td>2</td><td>Colostrum/ O</td><td>Enhance immunity</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Milk, Fenugreek seed, turmeric, white piper grind and mixed all/ O</td><td>Diabetes</td><td>1</td><td>Milk, Fenugreek seed, turmeric, white piper grind and mixed all/ O</td><td>Diabetes</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Milk mixed with grind water caltrop/ O</td><td rowspan="2">Enhance sexual power</td><td rowspan="2">2</td><td>Milk mixed with grind water caltrop/ O</td><td>Enhance sexual power</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Milk mixed with grind water caltrop/ O</td><td rowspan="2">Enhance sexual power</td><td rowspan="2">1</td></tr><tr><td>Milk mixed with grind water caltrop/ O</td><td>Enhance sexual power</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">O&#x02009;=&#x02009;Milk mixed with grind seeds of dates/ O</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="5">Milk mixed with grind seeds of dates/ O</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Heart diseases</td><td>3</td><td>Heart diseases</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Stones of bladder</td><td>2</td><td>Stones of bladder</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Stones of spleen</td><td>1</td><td>Stones of spleen</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Enhance sexual power</td><td>3</td><td>Enhance sexual power</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;20</td><td><italic>Manis crassicaudata</italic> &#x000c9;.. Geoffroy, Indian pangolin, Sipa/ Sipple, MC</td><td>Scale/T</td><td>enhance sexual Power</td><td>9</td><td>0.33</td><td>0.39</td><td>Scale/ T</td><td>enhance sexual Power</td><td>9</td><td>0.22</td><td>0.30</td><td>Feet swelling, piles, blood pressure, head ach, asthma, anti-haemorrhoidal, warts, ear pain, angina, back pain, heals bone inflammation, anti-poison, heals torn veins and arteries, infertility, gastro-intestinal disorders, safe parturition, stomach ulcers, rheumatism and fibroid, sexual power</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]</td><td>1.0</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;21</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Homo sapien</italic>s L., Human, Insan, HS</td><td>Saliva/T</td><td>Herpes</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="2">0.33</td><td rowspan="2">0.77</td><td>Saliva/ T</td><td>Herpes</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="2">0.25</td><td rowspan="2">0.59</td><td rowspan="2">Eye infections, wound, hiccup, herpes, ear pain, conjunctivitis, eye pain, antiseptic in</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">1.0</td><td rowspan="2">1.0</td></tr><tr><td>Urine/T</td><td>Ear pain</td><td>2</td><td>Urine/ T</td><td>Ear pain</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;22</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Ovis aries</italic> L., Sheep, Bairh, OA</td><td rowspan="3">Milk/T</td><td rowspan="3">Skin burn and cracks</td><td rowspan="3">16</td><td rowspan="4">0.69</td><td rowspan="4">1.17</td><td>Milk/ T</td><td>Skin burn and cracks</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="4">0.77</td><td rowspan="4">1.21</td><td rowspan="4">Edema, fractures, joint pain, sterility, flu, skin burn and crack, muscular pain, swellings, weakness, rheumatism, arthritis, swells, breast infection, headache, brain diseases, phlegm, dizziness, night blindness, heart failure, epilepsy, scabies</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0.75</td><td rowspan="4">0.75</td></tr><tr><td>Soup/ O</td><td>Flu</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Weakness and joint pain</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Meat/O</td><td>Weakness and joint pain</td><td>10</td><td>Testis/ O</td><td>Enhance sperm production</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;23</td><td><italic>Felis chaus</italic> Schreber, Jungle cat, Jungli billi, FC</td><td>Fat/T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>8</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.39</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>8</td><td>0.63</td><td>0.30</td><td>Leucoderma, joint pain</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>1.0</td><td>1.0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;24</td><td><italic>Felis domesticus</italic> Erxleben, Domestic cat, Billi, FD</td><td>Fat/T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>9</td><td>0.33</td><td>0.39</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>9</td><td>0.44</td><td>0.30</td><td>Fever, arthritis, Rheumatic pain, skin infections, Goiter</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]</td><td>1.0</td><td>1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">&#x02003;25</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>Oryctolagus cuniculus</italic> (L.), Domestic rabbit, Khargush/Saya, OC</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="2">0.72</td><td rowspan="2">0.78</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>12</td><td rowspan="2">0.78</td><td rowspan="2">0.61</td><td rowspan="2">Bronchial diseases, stomachache, burn, weakness</td><td rowspan="2">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]</td><td rowspan="2">0.30</td><td rowspan="2">0.30</td></tr><tr><td>Asthma</td><td>8</td><td>Asthma</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="16">Birds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;26</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Passer domesticus</italic> (L.), House Sparrow, Chiri, PD</td><td rowspan="4">Meat/O</td><td>Weakness</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="4">0.75</td><td rowspan="4">0.78</td><td rowspan="4">Meat/ O</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="4">0.80</td><td rowspan="4">0.61</td><td rowspan="4">Increase sexual desire, aphrodisiac, allergy, paralysis, impotency, gas trouble, constipation, Chickenpox, weakness, fever, delay dentition (child)</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0.50</td><td rowspan="4">0.50</td></tr><tr><td>Energy</td><td>4</td><td>Energy</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Fatigue</td><td>2</td><td>Fatigue</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Fever</td><td>9</td><td>Weakness</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8">&#x02003;27</td><td rowspan="8"><italic>Gallus gallus</italic> (L.), Domestic chicken, Murghi, Kukri, GG</td><td rowspan="3">Egg mixed with milk/O</td><td>Weakness</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="8">0.86</td><td rowspan="8">1.57</td><td rowspan="8">Egg/ O</td><td>Breast cancer</td><td>9</td><td rowspan="8">0.89</td><td rowspan="8">2.41</td><td rowspan="8">Sprains, strains, nourishing food, eye-each, BP, bronchitis, hemorrhoids, diabetes, burst furuncles, asthma, indigestion, jaundice, diabetes, sinusitis, to ease birth, shortness of breath, bronchitis, nervous problems, rheumatism, stuffy nose, weak bones, flu, weakness, sore throat, furuncle, burns, night blindness, optic infection, evil eye</td><td rowspan="8">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]</td><td rowspan="8">0.30</td><td rowspan="8">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Low blood pressure</td><td rowspan="2">5</td><td>Weight loss</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Eye sight</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Meat/O</td><td>Fever</td><td>10</td><td>Deficiency of protein</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Cold</td><td rowspan="4">10</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>CNS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Bones and teeth nourishment</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">&#x02003;28</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>Columba livia</italic> Gmelin, Blue rock pigeon, Jangli kabotar, CL</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>20</td><td rowspan="3">0.89</td><td rowspan="3">0.42</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>22</td><td rowspan="3">0.93</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td><td rowspan="3">Menorrhagia, Bronchitis, puberty in young girls, paralysis, epilepsy, anemia, infertility, Menorrhagia, abscess</td><td rowspan="3">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td><td rowspan="3">0.33</td></tr><tr><td>Weakness</td><td>4</td><td>Weakness</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>Enhance energy</td><td>4</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;29</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Coturnix coturnix</italic> (L.), Common quail, Batera, CCO</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>22</td><td rowspan="4">0.81</td><td rowspan="4">0.81</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="4">0.83</td><td rowspan="4">0.94</td><td rowspan="4">Skin diseases, anemia, body weakness, enhance memory, sexual power, fever</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0.40</td><td rowspan="4">0.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>sexual power</td><td>5</td><td>sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>against cold</td><td>5</td><td>against cold</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;30</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Francolinus francolinus</italic> (L.), Black francolin, Kala tittar, FFR</td><td rowspan="4">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="4">0.77</td><td rowspan="4">0.80</td><td rowspan="4">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="4">0.80</td><td rowspan="4">0.92</td><td rowspan="4">Bronchitis, weakness</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0</td><td rowspan="4">0</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Paralysis</td><td>6</td><td>Paralysis</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>4</td><td>Against cold</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;31</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Anas platyrhynchos f. domesticus</italic>, Domestic duck, Batakh, APD</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>10</td><td rowspan="6">0.84</td><td rowspan="6">1.18</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Fever</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="6">0.88</td><td rowspan="6">1.81</td><td rowspan="6">Weak eye-side, weakness, low blood pressure</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.30</td><td rowspan="6">0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Egg/ O</td><td>Fever</td><td>8</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Weak eye side</td><td rowspan="4">14</td><td rowspan="4">Egg/ O</td><td>Weak eye side</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Increase protein</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>CNS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Strengthened bones and teeth</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;32</td><td><italic>Streptopelia tranquebarica</italic> (Hermann), Red turtle dove, Surakh totru, STR</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>18</td><td>0.44</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>30</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.31</td><td>Maturity in girls</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>1.00</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;33</td><td><italic>Streptopelia decaocto</italic> (Frivaldszky), Indian ring dove, Kogi/Ghogi, SDE</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>16</td><td>0.44</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>32</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.31</td><td>Maturity in girls, sexual tonic</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]</td><td>1.00</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;34</td><td><italic>Streptopelia orientalis</italic> (Latham), Oriental turtle dove, Totru, SOR</td><td>Meat/O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>14</td><td>0.43</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>14</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.31</td><td>Maturity in girls</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>1.00</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;35</td><td><italic>Spelopelia senegalensis</italic> (L.), Little brown dove, Chhoti tutru/Chhoti kogi, SSE</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>15</td><td>0.38</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Early maturity in young female</td><td>13</td><td>0.46</td><td>0.30</td><td>Maturity in girls</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>1.00</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;36</td><td><italic>Athene brama</italic> (Temminck), Spotted owlet, Ullo, ABR</td><td>Blood/ T</td><td>Enhance male power and treat sexual weakness</td><td>21</td><td>0.79</td><td>0.41</td><td>Blood/ T</td><td>Enhance male power and treat sexual weakness.</td><td>24</td><td>0.75</td><td>0.32</td><td>Rickets, cough, sexual weakness</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;37</td><td><italic>Acridothere ginginianus</italic> (Latham), Bank myna, Lali, AGI</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Whooping cough</td><td>15</td><td>0.47</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Whooping cough</td><td>15</td><td>0.40</td><td>0.30</td><td/><td/><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">&#x02003;38</td><td rowspan="4"><italic>Anas platyrhynchos</italic> L., Mallard, Nilsir, APL</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td rowspan="3">Paralysis</td><td rowspan="3">7</td><td rowspan="4">0.53</td><td rowspan="4">0.77</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>paralysis</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="4">0.47</td><td rowspan="4">0.60</td><td rowspan="4">Erectile dysfunction, scarlet fever, body strength, weakness, paralysis</td><td rowspan="4">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]</td><td rowspan="4">0.5</td><td rowspan="4">0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Egg/ O</td><td>Eye sight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Egg/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>8</td><td>Protein</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;39</td><td><italic>Aquila nipalensis</italic> Hodgson, Tawny eagle, Baaz, ARN</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Breast swelling and pain</td><td>17</td><td>0.53</td><td>0.39</td><td>Fat/ T</td><td>Breast swelling and pain</td><td>17</td><td>0.47</td><td>0.31</td><td>Chest pain, breast swelling</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.50</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;40</td><td><italic>Upupa epops</italic> L., Common hoopoe, Hud-hud, UEP</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Kidney problems</td><td>9</td><td>0.44</td><td>0.39</td><td>Meat/ O</td><td>Kidney problems</td><td>9</td><td>0.56</td><td>0.30</td><td>Gall bladder stone, kidney problems</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]</td><td>1.00</td><td>1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="16">Fishes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;41</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Rita rita</italic> (Hamilton), Rita, Khaga, RRI</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="6">0.81</td><td rowspan="6">1.17</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="6">0.86</td><td rowspan="6">1.21</td><td rowspan="6">Joint pain</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.21</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>2</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>5</td><td>Energy</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>1</td><td>Against cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;42</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Sperata seenghala</italic> (Sykes), Giant river catfish, Singhari, SPSA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="6">0.72</td><td rowspan="6">1.16</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>4</td><td rowspan="6">0.67</td><td rowspan="6">1.20</td><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6">0</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td/><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td/><td rowspan="3">Oil/O</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td/><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td/><td>Against cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">&#x02003;43</td><td rowspan="7"><italic>Channa punctata</italic> (Bloch), Spotted snakehead, Dola, CPU</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="7">0.84</td><td rowspan="7">1.18</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="7">0.81</td><td rowspan="7">1.22</td><td rowspan="7">Blood purification, appetite, malaria control, body pain, corn or calves</td><td rowspan="7">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>]</td><td rowspan="7">0</td><td rowspan="7">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>6</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Sexual power</td><td rowspan="2">3</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td/><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>5</td><td rowspan="2">Against cold</td><td rowspan="2">1</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;44</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Channa marulius</italic> (Hamilton), Bullseye snakehead, Sap machli, CMA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.81</td><td rowspan="6">1.17</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.86</td><td rowspan="6">1.21</td><td rowspan="6">Increase sex power of male increase hemoglobin level, rheumatic pain</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>2</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>6</td><td>Against cold</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">&#x02003;45</td><td rowspan="7"><italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic> (L.), Baringo tilapia, Chirra machhli, OAU</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="7">0.50</td><td rowspan="7">1.54</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="7">0.56</td><td rowspan="7">1.49</td><td rowspan="7">Abscesses, sharpen sight, carbuncle, scorpion bite</td><td rowspan="7">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>]</td><td rowspan="7">0</td><td rowspan="7">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>3</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Scorpion bite</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Sharpens eye sight</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>6</td><td>Energy</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>1</td><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;46</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Labeo calbasu</italic> (Hamilton), Black rohu, Kalbans, LCA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.50</td><td rowspan="6">1.15</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.57</td><td rowspan="6">1.49</td><td rowspan="6">Increase energy and memory, galactagogue</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.33</td><td rowspan="6">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>3</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td><td>Increase lactation in mother</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>6</td><td>Energy and cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;47</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic> (Steindachner), Gardd carp, Grass carp, CID</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="6">0.73</td><td rowspan="6">1.16</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.67</td><td rowspan="6">1.20</td><td rowspan="6">Against cold</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>1</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>8</td><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">&#x02003;48</td><td rowspan="7"><italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic> L., Aischgrund carp, Gulfam, CCA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td/><td rowspan="7">0.68</td><td rowspan="7">1.16</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="7">0.74</td><td rowspan="7">1.20</td><td rowspan="7">Erysipelas, lumbago, CNS</td><td rowspan="7">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>]</td><td rowspan="7">0</td><td rowspan="7">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td rowspan="2">Enhance energy</td><td rowspan="2">2</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="2">Against cold</td><td rowspan="2">4</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;49</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Cirrhinus mrigala</italic> (Hamilton), Mrigal carp, Marakhi, CMR</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.73</td><td rowspan="6">1.17</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.77</td><td rowspan="6">1.21</td><td rowspan="6">Joint pain, reduce weight</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>1</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>3</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>12</td><td>Against cold</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;50</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Labeo rohita</italic> (Hamilton), Roho labeo, Raho, LRO</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.88</td><td rowspan="6">1.19</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.85</td><td rowspan="6">1.22</td><td rowspan="6">Urine Problem, stomach ache, weakness, rheumatic pain, Gastric</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>12</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>1</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>15</td><td>Against cold</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;51</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Carassius auratus</italic> (L.), Goldfish, Sanhari, CAU</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.63</td><td rowspan="6">1.16</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.68</td><td rowspan="6">1.20</td><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6"/><td rowspan="6">0</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>6</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>3</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>7</td><td>Against cold</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">&#x02003;52</td><td rowspan="7"><italic>Gibelon catla</italic> (Hamilton), Catla, Thaila, CACA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="7">0.70</td><td rowspan="7">1.17</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="7">0.6</td><td rowspan="7">1.2</td><td rowspan="7">Increase energy and memory, galactagogue, rheumatic pain</td><td rowspan="7">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>]</td><td rowspan="7">0.33</td><td rowspan="7">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>12</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>2</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Against cold</td><td rowspan="2">1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Against cold</td><td rowspan="2">2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">&#x02003;53</td><td rowspan="7"><italic>Wallago attu</italic> (Bloch), Boal, Mali, WAT</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="7">0.74</td><td rowspan="7">1.17</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="7">0.70</td><td rowspan="7">1.21</td><td rowspan="7">Joint pain, liver tonic, blood dysentery and piles</td><td rowspan="7">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>]</td><td rowspan="7">0.17</td><td rowspan="7">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>13</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Liver diseases</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="2">Against cold</td><td rowspan="2">3</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;54</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Bagarius bagarius</italic> (Hamilton), Bagarid catfish, Foji Khaga, BBA</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.81</td><td rowspan="6">1.18</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.85</td><td rowspan="6">1.51</td><td rowspan="6">Body burns, stomach pain, body pain</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.37</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>4</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>9</td><td>Against cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">&#x02003;55</td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Heteropneustes fossilis</italic> (Bloch), Scorpion cat-fish, Singhi, HF</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="6">0.74</td><td rowspan="6">1.16</td><td>Brain/ O</td><td>Enhance memory</td><td>3</td><td rowspan="6">0.79</td><td rowspan="6">1.20</td><td rowspan="6">Sting, joint pain, increase hemoglobin level and fever, pain, wound healing</td><td rowspan="6">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>]</td><td rowspan="6">0.17</td><td rowspan="6">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Meat/ O</td><td>Enhance energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Sexual power</td><td>8</td><td>Sexual power</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>1</td><td>Reduce overweight</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Against cold</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="2">Oil/ O</td><td>Energy</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Joint pain</td><td>7</td><td>Against cold</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="16">Invertebrates</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="25">&#x02003;56</td><td rowspan="25"><italic>Apis mellifera</italic> L., Honey Bee, Shahd makhi, AME</td><td rowspan="9">Honey mixed with grind cinnamon/ O</td><td rowspan="2">Cold</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="25">0.89</td><td rowspan="25">5.39</td><td rowspan="10">Honey mixed with grind cinnamon/ O</td><td>Cold</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="25">0.83</td><td rowspan="25">5.95</td><td rowspan="25">Dark spots, bronchitis, skin lightening, cough, fever, cataract, burn, sexual impotence, cold, flu, aging, sore throat, shortness of breath, arthritis, tuberculosis, constipation</td><td rowspan="25">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>]</td><td rowspan="25">0.13</td><td rowspan="25">0.09</td></tr><tr><td>Cough</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Cough</td><td>1</td><td>Acidity</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Acidity</td><td>3</td><td>Obesity</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Obesity</td><td>1</td><td>Control blood pressure</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Control blood pressure</td><td rowspan="2">1</td><td>Muscle pain</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Belly pain</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Muscle pain</td><td>5</td><td>Antimicrobial</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Belly pain</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="2">Anti-inflammatory</td><td rowspan="2">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Fennel mixed with honey/ O</td><td rowspan="3">Indigestion</td><td rowspan="3">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Honey/T</td><td>Hair loss</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Pimple</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Honey/ O</td><td>Body pain</td><td>3</td><td>Insect bite</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Ulcer</td><td>1</td><td rowspan="3">Grind big raisins, fennel mixed with honey/O</td><td rowspan="3">Indigestion</td><td rowspan="3">1</td></tr><tr><td>Allergy</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Tumor</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Enhance immunity</td><td rowspan="2">1</td><td rowspan="5"/><td>Body pain</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Ulcer</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">Green tea, fennel, black cardamom, cinnamon mixed with honey/ O</td><td rowspan="7">Indigestion</td><td rowspan="7">1</td><td>Allergy</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Tumor</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Enhance immunity</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Lemon juice, olive oil mixed with honey (in equal quantity)/ O</td><td>Kidney stones</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Ghai, egg yolk, mixed with honey/ O</td><td>Weak eyesight</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Grind walnut mixed with honey/ O</td><td>Stomach diseases, increase energy</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Green tea, fennel, cardamom, cinnamon mixed with honey/ O</td><td>Indigestion</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;57</td><td><italic>Oligochaeta</italic> spp. Earth worm, Gundoya, LTE</td><td/><td/><td>0</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td><td>Dry and clean earthworm body take in dry mud pot and pot close with mud and warm it with cow/buffalo dung, now get a ash/ O</td><td>Backbone pain</td><td>6</td><td>0.17</td><td>0.30</td><td>Wound, impotence</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: O (mean oral), T (topical), PU (parts use), MA (mode of application)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">The medicinal uses of <italic>Ovis orientalis punjabiensis</italic> (urial), <italic>Francolinus francolinus</italic> (black francolin), <italic>Sperata sarwari</italic> (giant river catfish), <italic>Channa punctate</italic> (snake head), <italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic> (baringo tilapia), <italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic> (gradd carp), <italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic> (aischgrund carp), <italic>Labeo rohita</italic> (roho labeo), and <italic>Carassius auratus</italic> (goldfish) were reported for the first time from the study areas. These species are used to treat allergy, epilepsy, fever, joint pain, and backache and to enhance memory and as aphrodisiac. Additionally, they have a zero similarity index with previous reports. However, some species such as <italic>Canis aureus</italic> (golden jackal), <italic>Herpestes javanicus</italic> (small Indian mongoose), <italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, (human), <italic>Felis chaus</italic> (jungle cat), <italic>Felis domesticus</italic> (domestic cat), <italic>Upupa epops</italic> (common hoopoe), <italic>Manis crassicaudata</italic> (Indian pangolin), <italic>Streptopelia tranquebarica</italic> (red turtle dove), <italic>Streptopelia decaocto</italic> (Indian ring dove), <italic>Streptopelia orientalis</italic> (oriental turtle dove), and <italic>Spelopelia senegalensis</italic> (little brown dove) exhibited the highest similarity index (SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) with previous studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Body part(s)</title><p id="Par26">Meat was the most utilized body part and used in 36 recipes in Jhelum and 34 recipes in Lahore (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), followed by oil and brain used in 20 and 16 recipes, respectively, in both districts, and fat used in 15 and 16 recipes in Jhelum and Lahore respectively. Milk, skin, bones, eggs, scale, saliva, blood, urine, testis, and carapace were used in less than five recipes. Local inhabitants of Lahore and Jhelum use chopped brains of different species such as common quail, rita, giant river catfish, spotted snakehead, bulls eye snakehead, baringo tilapia, black rohu, gradd carp, aischgrund carp, mrigal carp, Roho labeo, goldfish, catla, boal, bagarid catfish, and scorpion cat-fish to enhance the efficiency of the brain and nervous system. Likewise, testis of <italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic> (goat), <italic>Bos taurus</italic> (cattle), and <italic>Ovis aries</italic>, (sheep) are used to enhance the sperm production. However, these uses were more common in Lahore compared to Jhelum. Eggs of <italic>Gallus gallus</italic> (domestic chicken), <italic>Anas platyrhynchos domesticus</italic> (domestic duck), and <italic>Anas platyrhynchos</italic> (mallard) are used to treat fever, cold, weakness, low blood pressure, and weak eye side in Jhelum, while in Lahore they are used to treat breast cancer, weight loss, and cold and to enhance the performance of the CNS and strength of bones and teeth.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Body parts of animal species used in different recipes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par27">It has been reported that omega-3 fatty acid in animal fat ore oil reduces inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The present study revealed that inhabitants of the study areas use fat and oil to treat backache, breast swelling, cold, headache, burn, rheumatic pains, snake bite, and skin infections and as a sex stimulant (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These uses are comparable to previous reports that animal fats or oil are useful in atherosclerosis, neurological disorder, and thrombotic and aging effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Number of animal species used to treat various diseases in Jhelum and Lahore</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Pictorial views of traditional uses of animal species in the study areas</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Milk of <italic>Bubalus bubalis</italic> (buffalo), <italic>Bos taurus</italic> (cattle), <italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic> (goat), <italic>Camelus dromedarius</italic> (dromedary), <italic>Equus africanus asinus</italic> (donkey), and <italic>Ovis aries</italic> (sheep) is used as a sexual stimulant and antidote; to treat fever, diabetes, blood pressure, backache, and joint pain; for fertility; and to expel kidney stones. It is well known that milk contains high levels of proteins, vitamins, lipids, and minerals, which reduce joint pain, strengthen the body, and increase sexual potency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].</p><p id="Par29">The inhabitant of Lahore use bone soup of <italic>Capra aegagrus hircus</italic> (goat) to heal internal wounds and fractures (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This confirms that matrix contains up to 95% collagen fibers, elastic protein, and inorganic minerals like calcium phosphate, which improves fracture resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Local communities use scales of Indian pangolin (<italic>Manis crassicaudata</italic>) as a sexual stimulant (in both districts) and to remove hook worms (in Lahore only). The health benefits of Pangolin scales might be due to the presence of different chemical constituents such as cholesterol, stearic acid, volatile oil, minerals, proteins, glycine, isoleucine, leucine, lysine, proline, serine, tyrosine, and valine amino acids among several others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. However, due to illegal hunting and extensive use in traditional medicines, Indian pangolin is at the verge of extinction and has been included in &#x0201c;Red Listed&#x0201d; species by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>].<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Relationship between informant numbers and the number of application in study sites. (<bold>a</bold>) for Jehlum and (<bold>b</bold>) for Lahore</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">Human&#x02019;s urine is used against herpes and to treat ear pain in both districts. It has been known that the urine of cattle, dromedary, sheep, goat, hyrax, rhinoceros, and ass is also useful in the treatment of acne, asthma, anemia, antifungal, burn, back pain, chronic ailment, disinfection, foot diseases, fever, skin infections, TB, mouth infection, syphilis, rashes, CNS, memory loss, throat, and ear and eye infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. In addition, urine of dromedary inhibits enhancement of apoptosis, cell proliferation, and control of cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p21 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] and has high resistance against heat and fungal diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Frequency of citation (FC)</title><p id="Par31">Animal species, reported by the maximum number of informants as frequently used to treat various diseases, have high frequency of citation (FC) which ranged from 1 to 32 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In different areas of district Lahore, <italic>Streptopelia decaocto</italic> (Indian ring dove) and <italic>S. tranquebarica</italic> (red turtle dove) were reported as the most frequently utilized species for maturity in young girls with FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;32 each. <italic>Athene brama</italic> (spotted owlet) and <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon) were also among the commonly used species with FC value of 24 and 22, respectively. In different localities of Jhelum district, <italic>Coturnix coturnix</italic> (common quail) with FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;22 was the most commonly used species for the enhancement of memory followed <italic>Athene brama</italic> (spotted owlet), <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon), and <italic>Capra aegagrus</italic> (goat) which have FC values of 21, 20, and 20, respectively, whereas the lowest FC&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 was calculated for <italic>Homo sapien</italic>s (human) from Jhelum and earthworms from Lahore.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Fidelity level (FL)</title><p id="Par32">Fidelity level (FL) is used to identify species that are most preferred by the inhabitants to treatment of certain ailments. Animal species with topmost medicinal uses in a particular area have maximum fidelity level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. The fidelity levels of animal species used by the inhabitants of Lahore and Jhelum districts are given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Among the species reported from Lahore: <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon) depicted highest FL (92.86%), followed by <italic>Capra aegagrus</italic> (goat) and <italic>Anas platyrhynchos domesticus</italic> (domestic duck) with percentage FL&#x02009;=&#x02009;89.66 and 78.13, respectively, whereas earthworm had the lowest FL 16.67%. Among the animal species reported from different parts of Jhelum, <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon), <italic>Ovis orientalis punjabiensis</italic> (urial), and <italic>Athene brama</italic> (spotted owlet) were dominant with maximum percentage fidelity levels of 89.29, 83.33, and 79.71, respectively. However, <italic>Hystrix indica</italic> (Indian crested porcupine) had the lowest FL of 18.18% in Jhelum. The animal species with the highest FL could be used for in-depth chemical profiling and pharmaceutical properties. This will authenticate not only the medicinal worth of these species but could also be useful for novel animal-based drug discovery. Altaf et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>] document that the species <italic>B. taurus</italic>, <italic>Oryctolagus cuniculus</italic>, <italic>Ovis aries</italic>, <italic>A. platyrhynchos domesticus</italic>, <italic>G. gallus</italic>, and <italic>P. domesticus</italic> show 100% FL.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of fidelity level in the both study areas</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>S #</th><th>Scientific name</th><th>Jhelum (FL)</th><th>Lahore (FL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>
<italic>Bufo Stomaticus</italic>
</td><td>0.000</td><td>28.57</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>
<italic>Hoplobatrachus Tigerinus</italic>
</td><td>37.50</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>
<italic>Lissemys punctata andersoni</italic>
</td><td>0.00</td><td>25.00</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>
<italic>Laudakia agrorensis</italic>
</td><td>22.22</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>
<italic>Uromastyx hardwickii</italic>
</td><td>72.00</td><td>72.73</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>
<italic>Naja naja naja</italic>
</td><td>50.00</td><td>40.00</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>
<italic>Echis carinatus sochureki</italic>
</td><td>28.57</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>
<italic>Lepus nigricollis dayanus</italic>
</td><td>76.67</td><td>68.75</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>
<italic>Hystrix indica</italic>
</td><td>18.18</td><td>30.00</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>
<italic>Pteropus giganteus</italic>
</td><td>28.57</td><td>33.33</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>
<italic>Rattus rattus</italic>
</td><td>12.50</td><td>28.57</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>
<italic>Ovis orientalis punjabiensis</italic>
</td><td>83.33</td><td>63.64</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>
<italic>Hemiechinus collaris</italic>
</td><td>22.22</td><td>20.00</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>
<italic>Canis aureus</italic>
</td><td>28.57</td><td>25.00</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>
<italic>Herpestes javanicus</italic>
</td><td>18.18</td><td>22.22</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>
<italic>Camelus dromedarius</italic>
</td><td>60.00</td><td>55.56</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td><italic>Capra aegagrus</italic> hircus</td><td>75.00</td><td>89.66</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>
<italic>Bos taurus</italic>
</td><td>59.09</td><td>68.18</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>
<italic>Bubalus bubalis</italic>
</td><td>60.87</td><td>60.00</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>
<italic>Manis crassicaudata</italic>
</td><td>33.33</td><td>22.22</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td><italic>Homo sapien</italic>s</td><td>16.67</td><td>25.00</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>
<italic>Ovis aries</italic>
</td><td>57.69</td><td>65.38</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>
<italic>Felis chaus</italic>
</td><td>50.00</td><td>62.50</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>
<italic>Felis domesticus</italic>
</td><td>33.33</td><td>44.44</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>
<italic>Oryctolagus cuniculus</italic>
</td><td>61.11</td><td>66.67</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>
<italic>Passer domesticus</italic>
</td><td>60.00</td><td>65.00</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>
<italic>Gallus gallus</italic>
</td><td>74.29</td><td>77.14</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>
<italic>Columba livia</italic>
</td><td>89.29</td><td>92.86</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>
<italic>Coturnix coturnix</italic>
</td><td>73.81</td><td>73.81</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>
<italic>Francolinus francolinus</italic>
</td><td>66.67</td><td>70.00</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>
<italic>Anas platyrhynchos f. domesticus</italic>
</td><td>75.00</td><td>78.13</td></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>
<italic>Streptopelia tranquebarica</italic>
</td><td>44.44</td><td>47.37</td></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>
<italic>Streptopelia decaocto</italic>
</td><td>43.75</td><td>44.44</td></tr><tr><td>34</td><td>
<italic>Streptopelia orientalis</italic>
</td><td>42.86</td><td>43.75</td></tr><tr><td>35</td><td>
<italic>Spelopeliasenegalensis</italic>
</td><td>38.46</td><td>46.15</td></tr><tr><td>36</td><td>
<italic>Athene brama</italic>
</td><td>79.17</td><td>75.00</td></tr><tr><td>37</td><td>
<italic>Acridothere ginginianus</italic>
</td><td>46.67</td><td>40.00</td></tr><tr><td>38</td><td>
<italic>Anas platyrhynchos</italic>
</td><td>40.00</td><td>33.33</td></tr><tr><td>39</td><td>
<italic>Aquila nipalensis</italic>
</td><td>52.94</td><td>47.06</td></tr><tr><td>40</td><td>
<italic>Upupa epops</italic>
</td><td>44.44</td><td>55.56</td></tr><tr><td>41</td><td>
<italic>Rita rita</italic>
</td><td>66.67</td><td>71.43</td></tr><tr><td>42</td><td>
<italic>Sperata seenghala</italic>
</td><td>66.67</td><td>55.56</td></tr><tr><td>43</td><td>
<italic>Channa punctata</italic>
</td><td>74.19</td><td>70.97</td></tr><tr><td>44</td><td>
<italic>Channa marulius</italic>
</td><td>71.43</td><td>71.43</td></tr><tr><td>45</td><td>
<italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>
</td><td>37.50</td><td>43.75</td></tr><tr><td>46</td><td>
<italic>Labeo calbasu</italic>
</td><td>35.71</td><td>42.86</td></tr><tr><td>47</td><td>
<italic>Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>
</td><td>60.00</td><td>53.33</td></tr><tr><td>48</td><td>
<italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic>
</td><td>57.89</td><td>63.16</td></tr><tr><td>49</td><td>
<italic>Cirrhinus mrigala</italic>
</td><td>59.09</td><td>68.18</td></tr><tr><td>50</td><td>
<italic>Labeo rohita</italic>
</td><td>78.79</td><td>75.76</td></tr><tr><td>51</td><td>
<italic>Carassius auratus</italic>
</td><td>52.63</td><td>57.89</td></tr><tr><td>52</td><td>
<italic>Gibelon catla</italic>
</td><td>59.26</td><td>59.26</td></tr><tr><td>53</td><td>
<italic>Wallago attu</italic>
</td><td>60.87</td><td>60.87</td></tr><tr><td>54</td><td>
<italic>Bagarius bagarius</italic>
</td><td>70.37</td><td>74.07</td></tr><tr><td>55</td><td>
<italic>Heteropneustes fossilis</italic>
</td><td>63.16</td><td>63.16</td></tr><tr><td>56</td><td>
<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>
</td><td>77.14</td><td>66.67</td></tr><tr><td>57</td><td><italic>Oligochaeta</italic> spp.</td><td>0.000</td><td>16.67</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Relative importance (RI)</title><p id="Par33">The relative importance of animal species used by the inhabitant of Lahore and Jhelum districts is mentioned in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Most of the animal species were found to be highly versatile in their uses such as <italic>Apis mellifera</italic> (honey bee) with RI of 5.95 and 5.39 in Lahore and Jhelum, respectively, followed by <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon) having RI of 2.4 (Lahore) and 1.6 (Jhelum) and <italic>Uromastyx hardwickii</italic> (spiny-tail ground lizard) and <italic>Heteropneustes fossilis</italic> (singhi) with RI of 1.56 (Jhelum) and 1.5 (Lahore). The maximum RI values might be a sign of high affordability and accessibility of these species in the study areas.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Use value (UV)</title><p id="Par34">Results of use value (UV) authenticate the relative importance of species or family for a population. This index was anticipated to craft a connotation between each species and the uses allocated to it by analyzing the index in relation to the use groups. Comparative assessment of UV of different animal species among the local communities residing in different parts of Lahore and Jhelum is given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Among the reported animal species, the highest UVs of 0.89 and 0.88 were calculated for <italic>Columba livia</italic> (blue rock pigeon) from Jhelum and <italic>Gallus gallus</italic> (domestic chicken) from Lahore, whereas the lowest UVs of 1.6 and 0.12 were attained by earthworm and <italic>Rattus rattus</italic> (house rat) in Lahore and Jhelum in respective order. The high UVs of these species certified their consistent use in the treatment of different diseases. In addition, citation by the maximum number of informants and use reports viewing that these species are well known and commonly utilized for medicinal purpose in the study areas.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Principal component analysis (PCA) and cluster analysis (CA)</title><p id="Par35">Results of PCA are given in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, b</xref>. For district Jhelum, variables loaded onto component 1 include the following: FC (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004), UV (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01), RI (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.015), and FL (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.999), while on component 2 they included the following: FC (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02), UV (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.038), RI (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.998), and FL (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.015). For Lahore district, variables loading onto component 1 were FC (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0067), UV (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.011), RI (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.016), and FL (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.999) and component 2 were FC (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02), UV (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.021), RI (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.999), and FL (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;0.017). The first two axes of the PCA showed 99.9% variation in samples (component 1: 99.9%; component 2: 0.1%) from Jhelum (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>) and 99.87% variation in samples (component 1: 99.87%; component 2: 0.119%) from Lahore (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). Each principal component is not correlated with other principal components recorded from Jhelum and Lahore, respectively. Findings are resembled with reported study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>].<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Principal components analysis (PCA) (code are present in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The positions of the arrows relative to components 1 and 2 show how strongly independent variables (UV, RFC, FL and RI) are correlated with each other from both districts Jhelum (<bold>a</bold>) and Lahore (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par36">The statistical analysis shows that different groups are present in the cluster analysis, which are differentiated on the basis of values. The statistical analysis shows that two groups are present in the cluster analysis in Jhelum, i.e., group 1 (G1) and group 2 (G2). G1 and G2 have distance/variability of 45 points; G1 has species as LA, HCO, HCR, HJ, HS, RP, LPA, BS, and LTE (code are present in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). G2 has two subgroups, i.e., subgroup 1 (SG1) and subgroup 2 (SG2) have 30 variability points. SG1 was further divided into two groups as SG1A and SG1B (variability&#x02009;=&#x02009;14 points); SG2 was further divided into two groups as SG2A and SG2B (variability&#x02009;=&#x02009;15 points) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a, b</xref>).The statistical analysis shows that two groups are present in the cluster analysis in Lahore, i.e., group 1 (G1) and group 2 (G2). G1 and G2 have distance/variability of 54 points; G1 has species as ECS, HT, and LA (code are present in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). G2 has two sub groups, i.e., subgroup 1 (SG1) and subgroup 2 (SG2) have 33 variability points. SG1 was further divided into two groups as SG1A and SG1B (variability&#x02009;=&#x02009;14 points); SG2 was further divided into two groups as SG2A and SG2B (variability&#x02009;=&#x02009;24 points) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a, b</xref>). Findings are resembled with the reported study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>].<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Cluster analysis showing the similarities among species (code are present in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) in different variables (UV, RFC, FL, and RI) of Jhelum (<bold>a</bold>) and Lahore (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_253_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par37">Traditional knowledge of local communities, particularly on the medicinal application of animal species to treat health disorders, indicates their strong association with the surrounding environment. Medicinal uses of herptiles and ichthyo fauna of Pakistan were studied for the first time. Furthermore, application of <italic>O. orientalis punjabiensis</italic>, <italic>F. francolinus</italic>, <italic>S. sarwari</italic>, <italic>C. punctate</italic>, <italic>O. aureus</italic>, <italic>C. idella</italic>, <italic>C. carpio</italic>, <italic>L. rohita</italic>, and <italic>C. auratus</italic> to cure various diseases in humans has rarely been reported before. Our findings provide baseline data that could be valuable in conservation and sustainable use of animal biodiversity in this region. Screening of pharmacological active substances and in vitro or in vivo assessment of biological activities of animal species with maximum FL, UV, RI, and RFM could be important for animal-based novel drugs.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Local informants and the employees of Wildlife and Park, Fisheries and Aquaculture Departments of the Punjab Government are thankfully acknowledged.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par38">We do not have any funding to conduct this survey. Therefore, waiver request was sent to the Editorial office, which agreed to grant a full waiver to this manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par39">All data have already been included in the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Declaration</title><p id="Par40">Ethnomedicinal applications of animal species by the local communities of Punjab, Pakistan.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MA designed the study, conducted the field work, and prepared the first draft; MU, ARA, and NM were involved in the field survey and data collection; AA was involved in the data analysis; AMA contributed to the data analysis, interpolation, and final write up. All the authors critically read this article and approved as the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>The present study is purely based on the field survey instead of human or animal trials. Therefore, ethical approval and consent to participate is not applicable. However, formal consent was taken from informants regarding data collection and publication. In addition, ethical guidelines of the International Society of Ethnobiology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ethnobiology.net">http://www.ethnobiology.net</ext-link>/) were strictly followed.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Present paper does not contain any individual person&#x02019;s data; therefore, this section is not applicable to our study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adeola</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of wild animals and their parts in the culture, religious festivals, and traditional medicine, of Nigeria</article-title><source>Environ Conserv</source><year>1992</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0376892900030605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa-Neto</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal-based medicines: biological prospection and the sustainable use of zootherapeutic resources</article-title><source>An Acad Bras Cienc</source><year>2005</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0001-37652005000100004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15692677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15692677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of crude extract of earthworm on promoting blood circulation to removing stasis. Zhongguo Zhong xi yi jie he za zhi Zhongguo Zhongxiyi jiehe zazhi</article-title><source>Chinese J Integ Trad West Med</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>743</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why study the use of animal products in traditional medicines?</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-1-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unnikrishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animals in Ayurveda</article-title><source>Amruth Suppl</source><year>1998</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oudhia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional knowledge about medicinal insects, mites and spiders in Chhattisgarh, India</article-title><source>Insect Environ</source><year>1995</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beetz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uvn&#x000e4;s-Moberg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotrschal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychosocial and psychophysiological effects of human-animal interactions: the possible role of oxytocin</article-title><source>Front Psychol</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>234</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22279440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agosta</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bombardier beetles and fever trees: a close-up look at chemical warfare and signals in animals and plants</source><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa-Neto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conhecimento ictiol&#x000f3;gico tradicional ea distribui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o temporal e espacial de recursos pesqueiros pelos pescadores de Conde, Estado da Bahia, Brasil</article-title><source>Etnoecol&#x000f3;gica</source><year>2000</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dedeke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Soewu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pilot survey of ethnozoological utilisation of vertebrates in Southwestern Nigeria</article-title><source>Indilinga African J Indig Knowl Syst</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect antibacterial proteins</article-title><source>J Sericultural Sci Japan</source><year>1998</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>182</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitin: a magic bullet</article-title><source>Food Insect News</source><year>1989</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunin</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Does biodiversity matter? Evaluating the case for conserving species. Biodiversity: a biology of numbers and difference</source><year>1996</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Launet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dans les f&#x000f4;rets, &#x000e0; la recherche des m&#x000e9;dicaments de demain</article-title><source>Sci et Vie</source><year>1993</year><volume>904</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisset</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One man&#x02019;s poison, another man&#x02019;s medicine?</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>1991</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-8741(91)90105-M</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1881170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1881170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ernest Guenther award in chemistry of natural products. Amphibian skin: a remarkable source of biologically active arthropod alkaloids</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jm0204845</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12570366?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12570366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The natural history of amphibian skin secretions, their normal functioning and potential medical applications</article-title><source>Biol Rev</source><year>1997</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0006323197005045</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9336100?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9336100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasites, pests, and pets in a global world: new perspectives and challenges</article-title><source>J Exotic Pet Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jepm.2009.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The medicinal animal markets in the metropolitan region of Natal City, Northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2010</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.04.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20460145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20460145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>NAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Voeks</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animals for the gods: magical and religious faunal use and trade in Brazil</article-title><source>Hum Ecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10745-012-9516-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Feij&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barboza</surname><given-names>RRD</given-names></name><name><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>WMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes-Ferreira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro-Estrela</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Langguth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Game mammals of the Caatinga biome</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships between fauna and people and the role of ethnozoology in animal conservation</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ojango JMK, Okeyo AM, Philipsson J. Capacity building for sustainable use of animal genetic resources in developing countries. Appl. Animal Husb. Rural Develop. 2009;2:23-26.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabricant</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnsworth</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of plants used in traditional medicine for drug discovery</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2001</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.01109s169</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11250806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roberts TJ. The mammals of Pakistan. Revised ed. Karachi: Oxford University Press; 1997.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasiq</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>A field guide to birds of Pakistan Bookland, Lahore</source><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Annotated checklist of amphibians and reptiles of Pakistan</article-title><source>Asi Herp Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Zoogeography palaeontology and wildlife management</source><year>1998</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GOP</collab></person-group><source>Punjab development statistics</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Lahore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Government of Punjab: Bureau of Statistics Government of the Punjab</publisher-name><fpage>411</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><source>District Pre-Investment Study - 2012, Jhelum</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Lahore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Government of Punjab: Directorate of Industries, Punjab Poonch House</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>The culture of rural and urban areas of Pakistan</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Land use in the semi-arid zone of West Pakistan</article-title><source>Pakistan Geogr Rev</source><year>1963</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimmett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Inskipp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Inskip</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Birds of the Indian subcontinent. Christopher Helm an imprint of A and C Black (Publisher) Ltd, 35 Bedford Row, London WCIR 4JH</source><year>1998</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peculiarities of Mangla reservoir: biodiversity with sustainable use options</article-title><source>J Animal Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>380</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><source>District Pre-Investment Study - 2012, Lahore</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Lahore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Government of Punjab: Directorate of Industries, Punjab Poonch House</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baloch</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urbanization of arable land in Lahore City in Pakistan: a case-study</article-title><source>J Agric Biotechnol Sustain Devel</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>126</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bird ecology from the Ravi River of Lahore: habitat degradation</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>821</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wildlife diversity in the Punjab (Pakistan)</article-title><source>PJBS</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>420</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Close</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecological and cultural importance of a species at risk of extinction</article-title><source>Pacific Lamprey Fisheries</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joshua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avian diversity with the varying urban congestions of Lahore</article-title><source>J Anim Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>482</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Javid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Azmat</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The amphibians and reptiles collected from different habitat types in district Kasur, Punjab, Pakistan</article-title><source>Pakistan J Zool</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1204</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roberts TJ. Field guide to the large and medium-sized mammals of Pakistan. Karachi: Oxford University Press; 2005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roberts TJ. Field guide to the small mammals of Pakistan. Karachi: Oxford University Press; 2005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roberts TJ. The birds of Pakistan. Vol. I. Karachi: Oxford University Press; 1991.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Roberts TJ. The birds of Pakistan. Vol. II. Karachi: Oxford University Press; 1992.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Khan MS. Amphibian and reptiles of Pakistan. Malabar: Krieger Publisher Company; 2006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mirza MR. Fresh water fishes of Pakistan. Lahore: Urdu Science Board; 2004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alexiades MN, Sheldon JW. Selected guidelines for ethnobotanical research: a field manual. New York: New York Botanical Garden; 1996.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>NLE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Informant consensus: a new approach for identifying potentially effective medicinal plants</article-title><source>Plants in Indigenous Medicine and Diet, Biobehavioural Approaches</source><year>1986</year><publisher-loc>Bedford Hills</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Redgrave Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The useful plants of Tambopata, Peru: I. Statistical hypotheses tests with a new quantitative technique</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>1993</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02862203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Past: Palaeontological statistical software package for education and data analysis</article-title><source>Palaeontol Electron</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>9</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fats and oils for optimum health. The Center for Development</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breteler</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular risk factors for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease: An epidemiologic perspective</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-4580(99)00110-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10867200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10867200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential fatty acids and the brain</article-title><source>Canadian J Psychiat</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/070674370304800308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemme</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverri Perico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paarlberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Polan&#x000ed;a Vorenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez Balmaceda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Status and prospects for smallholder milk production. A global perspective. FAO, Roma (Italia)</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alabdulkarim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of camel milk on blood glucose, cholesterol, triglyceride and liver enzymes activities in female albino rats</article-title><source>World Appl Sci J</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1394</fpage><lpage>1397</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabahelkhier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Omer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative determination of biochemical constituents between animals (goat, sheep, cow and camel) milk with human milk</article-title><source>Res J Recent Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Contarini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Povolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospholipids in milk fat: composition, biological and technological significance, and analytical strategies</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2808</fpage><lpage>2831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms14022808</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23434649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vats</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study on use of animals as traditional medicine by Sukuma tribe of Busega District in North-Western Tanzania</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0001-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25559394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Textbook of medical physiology Elsevier</source><year>2011</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jia CS. Pangolin. Chinese Herb Med. 2013; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chineseherbinfo.com">http://chineseherbinfo.com</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaling up pangolin protection in China</article-title><source>Front Ecol Environ</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/14.WB.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohani</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eroding ethnozoological knowledge among Magars in Central Nepal</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>473</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohani</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional uses of animals among Jirels of Central Nepal</article-title><source>Ethno Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09735070.2011.11886398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Yousef</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaafar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Otaibi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Jammaz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Hussein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aboussekhra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Camel urine components display anti-cancer properties in vitro</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.07.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22922085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Neta</surname><given-names>ROS</given-names></name><name><surname>Trov&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>TLP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional uses of medicinal animals in the semi-arid region of northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>4269</fpage><lpage>4268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-8-41</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Varela</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal use of fauna by a traditional community in the Brazilian Amazonia</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-8-37</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23013927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23013927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological study of medicinal animals on Jeju Island, Korea</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.11.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23266277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23266277</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of ethnomedicinal practices for treating skin diseases in communities on Jeju Island (Korea)</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>680</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of mammals in local communities living in conservation areas in the northeast of Brazil: an ethnozoological approach</article-title><source>Trop Conserv Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/194008291400700305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Senapati</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Palai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversified uses of cow urine</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Pharm Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Awadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Judaibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of heating and storage on the antifungal activity of camel urine</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabesh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakashraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quantitative ethnozoological study of traditionally used animals in Pachamalai hills of Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>51</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.05.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26002766?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26002766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabesh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyanar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Damodaran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological study of animals used by traditional healers in Silent Valley of Kerala, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.12.055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25571847?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25571847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srithi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Balslev</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wangpakapattanawong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Srisanga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Trisonthi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant knowledge and its erosion among the Mien (Yao) in northern Thailand</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2009.02.035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19429381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19429381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tareen</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tareen</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabeen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>S-U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaseen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of medicinal plants in district Mastung of Balochistan province-Pakistan</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.08.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25260579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Javid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Umair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal and cultural practices of mammals and birds in the vicinity of river Chenab, Punjab-Pakistan</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-017-0168-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Assessment of Avian and Mammalian Diversity at Selected Sites along river Chenab in Wildlife and Ecology</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Lahore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Veterinary and Animal Sciences</publisher-name><fpage>197</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhan</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-veterinary zoo-therapies and occult practices in greater Cholistan desert (Pakistan)</article-title><source>Sci Int (Lahore)</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>243</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borah</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological study of animals based medicine used by traditional healers and indigenous inhabitants in the adjoining areas of gibbon wildlife sanctuary, Assam, India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-017-0167-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benarjee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramulua</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological study in a tropical wildlife sanctuary of Eturunagaram in the Warangal district, Andhra Pradesh</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>704</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnozoological studies and medicinal values of vertebrate origin in the adjoining areas of Pench National Park of Chhindwara District of Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J life Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>283</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of traditional man-animal relationship in Chhindwara district of Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title><source>J Global Biosci</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1463</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rout</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-zoological studies and medicinal values of similipal biosphere reserve, Orissa, India</article-title><source>Afr J Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sujana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal products in traditional medicine from Attappady hills of western Ghats</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>329</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravorty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Rochow</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertebrates used for medicinal purposes by members of the Nyishi and Galo tribes in Arunachal Pradesh (North-East India)</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-7-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lalmuanpuii</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosangkima</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-medicinal practices among the Mizo ethnic group in Lunglei district, Mizoram</article-title><source>Sci Vision</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Saboor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadiq</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobiological study in Kala Chitta hills of Pothwar region, Pakistan: multinomial logit specification</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-10-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24467739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24467739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadavul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajalakshmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekhawat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-medico-biological studies of South India</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohani</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Man-animal relationships in Central Nepal</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-6-31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chinlampianga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological diversity of Northeast India: empirical learning with traditional knowledge holders of Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galave</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Katewa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional veterinary medicines used by liestock owner of Rajhastan, India</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betlu</surname><given-names>ALS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge of zootherapeutic use among the Biate tribe of Dima Hasao District, Assam, Northeastern India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23281594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aloufi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zootherapy: a study from the northwestern region of the kingdom of Saudi Arabia and hashemite kingdom of Jordan</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>569</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chellappandian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandikumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutheeswaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulraj</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabakaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duraipandiyan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhabi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Documentation and quantitative analysis of local ethnozoological knowledge among traditional healers of Theni district, Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.03.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24680989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24680989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mootoosamy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahomoodally</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quantitative ethnozoological assessment of traditionally used animal-based therapies in the tropical island of Mauritius</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24824877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24824877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paudyal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-medicinal uses of animals and plants among the migratory tangbetons of Pokhara, Nepal</article-title><source>J Instr Sci Technol</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3126/jist.v19i1.13840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaroli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahawar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnozoological study in the adjoining areas of Mount Abu wildlife sanctuary, India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-6-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20144243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20144243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal use of fauna in the indigenous medicine system of Gendewuha and Kumeraaftit Kebeles of Metema Woreda, North West Ethiopia</article-title><source>Int J Innov Res Devel</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>464</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yirga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Teferi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebreslassea</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoological study of traditional medicinal animals used by the people of Kafta-Humera District, Northern Ethiopia</article-title><source>Int J Med Medical Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>320</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haileselasie</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional zootherapeutic studies in Degu&#x02019;a Tembien, Northern Ethiopia</article-title><source>Curr Res J Biol Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>569</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso-Castro</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carranza-&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maldonado-Miranda</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>del Rosario</surname><given-names>J-SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Quezada-Rivera</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo-M&#x000e1;rquez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa-Z&#x000fa;&#x000f1;iga</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Galicia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000ed;os-Reyes</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>de Le&#x000f3;n-Rubio</surname><given-names>M&#x000c1;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zootherapeutic practices in Aquism&#x000f3;n, San Luis Potos&#x000ed;, M&#x000e9;xico</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2011.09.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21963568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21963568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of fauna in the traditional medicine of native Toba (qom) from the Argentine Gran Chaco region: an ethnozoological and conservationist approach</article-title><source>Ethnobiol Conserv</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ajagun</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anyaku</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Afolayan</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of the traditional medical and non-medical uses of animals species and parts of the indigenous</article-title><source>J Herb Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Patil MB, Shaikh M. Ethnozoological Study of Nandurbar District, Maharashtra State. Int J Sci Info. 2016;4:189-95.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>ALB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerqu</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional aspects of the use of plants and animals in local medical systems and their implications forresilience</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>348</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2016.08.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27538794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27538794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Modak</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobiological treatments of neurological conditions in the Chota Nagpur Plateau, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>198</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2016.12.040</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28017696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28017696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zootherapy goes to town: the use of animal-based remedies in urban areas of NE and N Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.07.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17719192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17719192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of animal-derived remedies as complementary medicine in Brazil</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2007</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/B571107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yeshi K, Morisco P, Wangchuk P. Animal derived natural products used in the Bhutanese Sowa Riga medicine. J Ethnopharmacol. 2017; 207:192-202.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Adwait</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folk therapies of katkaries from Maharashtra</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>558</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soewu</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayodele</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilisation of Pangolin (<italic>Manis</italic> sps) in traditional Yorubic medicine in Ijebu province, Ogun State, Nigeria</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-5-39</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19961597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19961597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><label>113.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben&#x000ed;tez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animals used for medicinal and magico-religious purposes in western Granada Province, Andalusia (Spain)</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2011.07.036</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21801827?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR114"><label>114.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>NAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commercialization of animal-derived remedies as complementary medicine in the semi-arid region of Northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2009.04.049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19422902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19422902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR115"><label>115.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alves RRN, Oliveira MGG, Barboza RRD, Lopez LCS, Oliveira MGG. An ethnozoological survey of medicinal animals commercialized in the markets of Campina Grande, NE Brazil. Human Ecol Rev. 2010;17:11&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR116"><label>116.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souto</surname><given-names>WMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barboza</surname><given-names>RRD</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional knowledge of sertanejos about zootherapeutic practices used in ethnoveterinary medicine of NE Brazil</article-title><source>Ind J Trad Knowledge</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>265</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR117"><label>117.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobo-Salcedoa</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso-Castro</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarate-Martinez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folk medicinal use of fauna in Mapimi, Durango, M&#x000e9;xico</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20937375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR118"><label>118.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Saikia K, Ahmed R. Wetland fish biodiversity of Majuli river island (India) and their medicinal values. The Clarion. 2012;2:81-86.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR119"><label>119.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teronpi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamuli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnozoology of the Karbis of Assam, India: Use of ichthyofauna in traditional health-care practices</article-title><source>Anc Sci Life</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0257-7941.118547</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24167335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24167335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR120"><label>120.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahawar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaroli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional zootherapeutic studies in India: a review</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-4-17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18634551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18634551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR121"><label>121.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Emdad</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x02018;Every mother is a mini-doctor&#x02019;: Ethnomedicinal uses of fish, shellfish and some other aquatic animals in Bangladesh</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2011</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2010.12.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21185366?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21185366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR122"><label>122.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Umair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of distribution and ethnocultural uses of the sol (<italic>Channa marulius</italic>) in Punjab, Pakistan</article-title><source>J Wildl Ecol</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR123"><label>123.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fish-based remedies in Spanish ethnomedicine: a review from a historical perspective</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-10-37</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24885245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR124"><label>124.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Umair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Awan</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the diversity and ethno-medicinal uses of the carps in Punjab, Pakistan</article-title><source>J Wildl Ecol</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR125"><label>125.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mawla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Debnath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmatullah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants of folk medicinal practitioners in four villages of Natore and Rajshahi districts, Bangladesh</article-title><source>Am Eur J Sustain Agric</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>416</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>