<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Young Pharm</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JYPharm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Young Pharmacists : JYP</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0975-1483</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0975-1505</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3035883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21331189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JYPharm-2-42</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0975-1483.62211</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pharmacognosy</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibacterial Activity of <italic>Lantana camara</italic> Linn and <italic>Lantana montevidensis</italic> Brig Extracts from Cariri-Cear&#x000e1;, Brazil</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FFG</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><italic>Departamento de Qu&#x000ed;mica-Biol&#x000f3;gica, Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Pesquisa de Produtos Naturais, Universidade Regional do Cariri, Rua Cel. Ant&#x000f4;nio Luiz 1161, Pimenta, 63105 - 000, Crato-CE, Brazil</italic></aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>1</label><italic>Vice-Reitoria de Pesquisa e P&#x000f3;s-Gradua&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o, Universidade de Fortaleza, Av. Washington Soares 1321, Edson Queiroz, 60811-905, Fortaleza-CE, Brazil</italic></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><italic><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Galberto Martins da Costa; E-mail: <email xlink:href="galberto.martins@gmail.com">galberto.martins@gmail.com</email></italic></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Mar</season><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Journal of Young Pharmacists</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The use of medicinal plants with therapeutics properties represents a secular tradition in different cultures, mainly in underdeveloped countries. <italic>Lantana camara</italic> Linn and <italic>Lantana montevidensis</italic> Briq (Verbenaceae) found in tropical and subtropical areas around the world are popularly known as &#x0201c;camar&#x000e1;&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;chumbinho.&#x0201d; In popular medicines, both plants are used as antipyretic and carminative and in the treatment of respiratory system infections. In this study, the antibacterial activity of the ethanolic extracts of <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> leaves and roots against gram-positive and gram-negative strains standard and multi-resistant bacteria isolated from clinical material are presented. In order to determine the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC), the microdilution method was used. The extracts demonstrated antibacterial activity against all tested bacteria, but the <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> fresh leaves extract present the best result against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (MIC 8 &#x003bc;g/mL) and against multi-resistant <italic>E. coli</italic> (Ec 27) (MIC 16 &#x003bc;g/mL). These results drive new researches with both species in order to isolate the constituents responsible for the activity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Lantana camara</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Lantana montevidensis</italic></kwd><kwd>antibacterial activity</kwd><kwd>microdilution</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The use of medicinal plants with therapeutical purposes represents a secular tradition in different cultures. Vegetal species have been shown effective to treat many infections, such as tumors[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT1">1</xref>] Considering the fact that several microorganisms become resistant to conventional antibiotics and the Brazilian vegetal biodiversity, research groups have paid attention to natural products as source of new molecules with pharmacological potential that could be more efficient against nosocomial pathogens and less toxic to human body.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT4">4</xref>]</p><p>The Verbenaceae family comprises 100 genera and about 2600 species distributed in tropical and subtropical regions around the world.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT5">5</xref>] <italic>Lantana</italic> is a genus of about 150 species of perennial flowering plants popularly used as antirheumatic, stimulant, antibacterial, biologic control, and as ornamental plant.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT7">7</xref>]</p><p><italic>Lantana camara</italic> Linn, typical in Americas and Africa, and <italic>Lantana montevidensis</italic> Briq, native to Brazil and Uruguay are popularly known as &#x0201c;camar&#x000e1;&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cambar&#x000e1;&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;chumbinho.&#x0201d; They are shrubs introduced in many countries as ornamental plants and considered as invasive species in many parts of the world.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT8">8</xref>] In popular medicine, both species are used as carminative, antispasmodic, antiemetic, and to treat respiratory infections as cough, cold, asthma, and bronchitis. Previous studies related antitumoral, antifungal, antimalarial, analgesic, and hepatotoxic activities.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT9">9</xref>]</p><p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate the <italic>in vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of ethanolic extracts from <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> leaves and roots using the microdilution method to assay the susceptibilities of five bacteria strains (American Type Culture Collection - ATCC) and two multi-resistant strains isolated from clinical material.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Plant material</title><p>The leaves of <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> were collected in March, 2009, from the Small Aromatic and Medicinal Plants Garden of the Natural Products Research Laboratory (LPPN) at Universidade Regional do Cariri (URCA), city of Crato, Cear&#x000e1; state, Brazil. The exsiccate was deposited at the Herbarium Caririensis &#x0201c;D&#x000e1;rdano de Andrade Lima&#x0201d;, Biology Department, under registry numbers 1662 and 1619, respectively, for <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Extracts preparation</title><p>Ethanolic extracts were prepared using the cold extraction method. <italic>L. camara</italic> (240 g of the fresh leaves and 185 g of the roots) and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> (400 g of the fresh leaves and 714 g of the roots) were placed in a flask containing cold ethanol and left in this position for 72 h at ambient temperature. A rotary vacuum pump extractor was used to remove the ethanol from the extracts (under reduced pressure). The extracts were weighted and stored.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Antibacterial assays</title><p>The antibacterial activities of the extracts were investigated by employing a microdilution method, recommended by NCCCLS M7-A6.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT10">10</xref>] The assay was carried out with five bacterial species obtained from Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Oswaldo Cruz-FIOCRUZ: <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 12692), <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic> (ATCC 13135), <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 15442), <italic>V&#x000ed;brio cholareae</italic> (ATCC 15748), <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 2992) and two multiresistant strains obtained from clinical material: <italic>E. coli</italic> (Ec 27, from sputum) and <italic>S. aureus</italic> (Sa 358, from cirurgical wound).</p><p>Brain Hear Infusion Broth (BHI 3.8%) was used for bacterial growth (24 h, 35 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C). The inoculum was an overnight culture of each bacterial species in BHI broth diluted in the same media to a final concentration of approximately 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> UFC/mL (0.5 nephelometric turbidity units - McFarland scale). After this, the suspension was diluted to 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> UFC/mL in 10% BHI. 100 &#x003bc;L of each dilution were distributed in 96-well plates plus extracts in different concentrations, achieving 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> UFC/mL as the final concentration of the inoculum.</p><p>Extracts were dissolved in distilled water and dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) to a concentration of 103 &#x003bc;g/mL. Further serial dilutions were performed by addition of BHI broth to reach a final concentration in the range of 512 a 8 &#x003bc;g/mL. All experiments were performed in triplicate, and the microdilution trays were incubated at 35 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C for 24 h. Antibacterial activity was detected using a colorimetric method by adding 25 &#x003bc;L of resauzurin staining (0.01%) aqueous solution in each well at the end of the incubation period. The minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) was defined as the lowest essential oil concentration able to inhibit the bacteria growth, as indicated by resauzurin staining (bacteria died cells are not able to change the staining color by visual observation-blue to red).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><p>Several new antibacterial agents are currently being developed in response to the emergence of bacterial resistance to existing drug. New vegetal sources presenting antimicrobial activity and low toxicity could be a viable alternative, with low cost and easily accessible to poor communities where the species are found.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT11">11</xref>] The antibacterial activity of ethanolic extract from <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> presented excellent results against the pathogenic microorganisms tested [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T0001" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antibacterial activity of <italic>L. camara</italic> and <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> extracts</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microorganisms</th><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">MIC (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>L. camara</italic><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><italic>L. montevidensis</italic><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. vulgaris</italic> (ATCC 13315)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 15442)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>V. cholareae</italic> (ATCC 15748)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 12692)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> (Ec 27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. aureus</italic> (Sa 358)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">512</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;1024</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LE = Leaves extract; RE = Roots extract</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The extracts presented antibacterial activity against clinically relevant pathogens (gram positive and gram negative). <italic>L. camara</italic> leaves extract was active against <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> and <italic>V. cholerae</italic> (MIC 128 &#x003bc;g/mL for both strains); in addition the root extract was effective against <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (64 and 128 &#x003bc;g/mL, respectively). The leaves and roots <italic>L. montevidensis</italic> extracts were active against <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (MIC 8 &#x003bc;g/mL) and two strains of <italic>E. coli</italic> (MIC 16 &#x003bc;g/mL for the multiresistant strain) as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Previous studies using extracts from <italic>Lantana</italic> species showed that they were able to inhibit the growth of gram-positive bacteria strains.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT12">12</xref>] However, in this study, the antibacterial activity against gram-negative bacteria was verified, mainly <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. This is relevant information as Navon-Venezia (2005)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT13">13</xref>] reported that since 1980, after the introduction of carbapenems, no new antibiotics have been used for the treatment of infections caused by multiresistant gram-negative bacilli (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, for example).</p><p>The results that we present here are relevant, as the literature has shown that gram-positive bacteria are more sensitive to antibiotics. The gram-negative bacteria display some particularities that inhibit antibiotics penetration, as the lipopolyssacaride layer that determines the permeability and susceptibility to antibiotics.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT14">14</xref>] We suggest that data obtained here may suffer seasonal influence and/or be associated with the presence of chemical compounds (terpenes, triterpenes, quinones, alkaloids, and flavonoids) derived from <italic>Lantana</italic> species secondary metabolism as reported in phytochemical studies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to the Brazilian Agency FUNCAP for financial support and FIOCRUZ for the microbial lines.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Source of Support:</bold> Brazilian Agency FUNCAP for financial support and FIOCRUZ for the microbial lines</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="CIT1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estudo qu&#x000ed;mico, biol&#x000f3;gico e farmacol&#x000f3;gico das esp&#x000e9;cies <italic>Allamanda blanchetti</italic> e <italic>Allamanda schottii</italic> Pohl para a obten&#x000e7;&#x000f5;o de fra&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es e mol&#x000e9;culas bioativas de potencial terap&#x000ea;utico</article-title><source>Tese de Doutorado. Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Florian&#x000f3;polis, SC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferronato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchesan</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezenti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bednarski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Onofre</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atividade antimicrobiana de &#x000f3;leos essenciais produzidos por <italic>Baccharis dracunculifolia</italic> DC. e <italic>Baccharis uncinella D.C</italic>. (Asteraceae)</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source><year>2007</year><fpage>224</fpage><fpage>30</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triagem da atividade antibacteriana <italic>in vitro</italic> do l&#x000e1;tex e extratos de <italic>Cr&#x000f3;ton urucurana Baillon</italic></article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>593</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salvagnini</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietro</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000f5;o da atividade antibacteriana de folhas de <italic>Myrtus communis L.</italic>(Myrtaceae)</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>1993.Bot&#x000e2;nica: <italic>Introdu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o &#x000e0; Taxonomia Vegetal</italic> S&#x000e3;o Paulo</article-title><source>Companhia Editora Nacional</source><year>1993</year><edition>11th ed</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dua</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repellency of <italic>Lantana camara</italic> (Verbenaceae) flowers against <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes</article-title><source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8887218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghisalberti</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Lantana camara</italic> L.(Verbenaceae)</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><year>2000</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11449493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranjhan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tulloh</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JHG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional and metabolic disorders of buffaloes</article-title><source><italic>Buffalo production</italic></source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>2</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravinder</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Daizy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Batish</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname></name><name><surname>Kuldip</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status, invasiveness and environmental threats of three tropical American invasive weeds (<italic>Parthenium hysterophorus L., Ageratum conyzoides L., Lantana camara L.</italic>) in India</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1501</fpage><lpage>1510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards; Methods for Dilution Antimicrobial Susceptibility Tests for bacteria that grow aerobically, Approved Standard M7-A6</article-title><year>2003</year><edition>6th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Wayne</publisher-loc><publisher-name>NCCLS</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FFG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ang&#x000e9;lico</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>CKB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldas</surname><given-names>GFR</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>NKA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composi&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o qu&#x000ed;mica e avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da atividade antibacteriana e toxicidade do &#x000f3;leo essencial de Croton zehntneri (variedade estragol</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn 2007</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>586</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>AJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da atividade antimicrobiana dos extratos etan&#x000f3;licos de <italic>Lantana macrophylla</italic> e <italic>Aeagiphyla vitelliniflora, Verbenaceae</italic></article-title><source>XII Semin&#x000e1;rio de Inicia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Cient&#x000ed;fica da UESC, Resumos</source><year>2005</year><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navon-Venezia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Ami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> infections in the healthcare seting</article-title><source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source><year>2005</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15985826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CIT14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contributions of the lipopolysaccharide outer core oligosaccharide region on the cell surface properties of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></article-title><source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17182100</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>