<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Integr Cancer Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Integr Cancer Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ICT</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spict</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Integrative Cancer Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1534-7354</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-695X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6247547</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30289008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1534735418803766</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1534735418803766</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>: Potential Roles in Cancer
Treatment and Palliative Care</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cruceriu</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534735418803766">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1534735418803766">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balacescu</surname><given-names>Ovidiu</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534735418803766">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1534735418803766">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1534735418803766"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rakosy</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1534735418803766">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-1534735418803766"><label>1</label>The Oncology Institute &#x0201c;Prof. Dr. Ion
Chiricuta,&#x0201d; Cluj-Napoca, Romania</aff><aff id="aff2-1534735418803766"><label>2</label>&#x0201c;Babes-Bolyai&#x0201d; University, Cluj-Napoca,
Romania</aff><aff id="aff3-1534735418803766"><label>3</label>University of Medicine and Pharmacy
&#x0201c;Iuliu Hatieganu,&#x0201d; Cluj-Napoca, Romania</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-1534735418803766">Ovidiu Balacescu, Department of Functional
Genomics, Proteomics and Experimental Pathology, The Oncology Institute &#x0201c;Prof.
Dr. Ion Chiricuta,&#x0201d; 34-36 Republicii Street, Cluj-Napoca 400015, Romania. Email:
<email>ovidiubalacescu@iocn.ro</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1068</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Inc unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A continuous challenge in cancer management is to improve treatment efficacy and
to diminish its side effects. Consequently, new conventional and unconventional
drugs and bioactive compounds from plants are constantly developed,
characterized, and used for in vitro and in vivo models. This review focuses on
the antitumor properties of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>, its
biological and molecular effects in tumor cells and animal models, as well as
its role in cancer palliative care. A systematic review of studies describing
the cytotoxic role of <italic>C officinalis</italic> and its therapeutic role on
cancer cells were carried out using the PubMed database. Albeit <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts have cytotoxic activity toward different
cancer cell lines, a high grade of variation between studies was observed,
depending on plant organ subjected to extraction, extraction method, and the
cancer cell lines used for each study. Nevertheless, its cytotoxic activity is
related to a few bioactive compounds, presenting multiple roles in both
activation of proapoptotic proteins and decreasing the expression of the
proteins that inhibit cell death. Moreover, due to its anti-genotoxic/protective
as well as antitumor and antimetastatic effects proven in animal models,
<italic>C officinalis</italic> could have important future implications in
developing novel cancer treatment strategies, while until now it has been used
especially for diminishing the side effects of radiotherapy.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Calendula</italic></kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd><kwd>cytotoxicity</kwd><kwd>genoprotective</kwd><kwd>antimetastatic</kwd><kwd>palliative care</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1-1534735418803766"><funding-source id="funding1-1534735418803766"><institution-wrap><institution>Autoritatea National&#x00103; pentru Cercetare
Stiintific&#x00103;</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100005802</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-1534735418803766">Grant P_40_318/2016</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section1-1534735418803766"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer ranks second among all causes of mortality worldwide, with 8.2 million
cancer-related deaths in 2012. Regarding its incidence, 12 million new cases were
recorded in 2012, while this number is expected to rise by about 70% over the next 2 decades.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Depending on cancer stage, its phenotype, and localization, the ongoing
treatment options include surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy, immunotherapy, and,
when suited, hormonal therapies. If the surgery and radiotherapy are successfully
used to cure solid tumors in early stages, chemotherapy represents the most
important choice of cancer armamentarium for advanced cancers as well as
hematological malignancies. However, these treatment options are not always
efficient and have significant limitations, probably due to the high heterogeneity
of tumors and the fact that the majority of cancers are identified in advanced
stages. To increase the treatment efficacy and to reduce the tumor drug resistance,
a combinatory regimen is currently applied.</p><p>Even if chemotherapy represents one of the most important approaches to kill cancer
cells, it produces many side effects by damaging healthy tissues due to its action
against all cells entering division. Therefore, both short-term and long-term
cumulative cytotoxicity and several adverse effects including fatigue, hair loss,
anemia, nausea and vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, mood changes, kidney problems,
and dry skin are associated with adjuvant chemotherapy.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p><p>Another major problem in cancer treatment is that tumor cells become resistant to
radiochemotherapy, thus limiting the response to therapy.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Tumor cells might become resistant either by inheriting the resistance traits
from a cancerous cell subpopulation, an event known as baseline resistance and
recorded in about 50% of cancer patients or by acquiring resistance over time, as a
cellular response to specific drug exposure.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup></p><p>If chemotherapy is considered a nontarget therapy, inducing many side effects,
immunotherapy, including monoclonal antibodies, adoptive cell transfer, cytokines,
and cancer vaccines, represents a reliable targeted therapy. However, it is limited
to some specific tumor phenotypes. Furthermore, due to the high tumor heterogeneity
and the high mutation rate, cancerous cell may acquire resistance and thus cause
patient relapse.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup></p><p>In this context, new conventional and unconventional anticancer drugs and compounds
are constantly developed in an effort to improve cancer therapy and to diminish
treatment side effects. In this regard, one of the most important research fields
aiming to identify new compounds useful for cancer treatment is that related to
plants.</p><p>Plants have been proved to be a relevant source of bioactive phytochemicals with
cytotoxic and antitumor activity, increasing efforts being made to identify novel
plant compounds as possible effective drugs in cancer treatment. Bioactive agents
originating from plants like <italic>Catharanthus roseus, Podophyllum</italic>
species, <italic>Taxus brevifolia, Camptotheca acuminata, Cephalotaxus</italic>
species, or <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> have been long known to possess
anticancer properties, with some of them being used in the treatment of different
malignancies in clinical setting.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr7-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Paclitaxel, a drug widely used
nowadays in the treatment of different types of cancer and part of the World Health
Organization&#x02019;s List of Essential Medicines, represents a good example of such a compound.<sup><xref rid="bibr8-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> It was originally isolated from the bark of the Pacific yew, <italic>Taxus
brevifolia</italic>,<sup><xref rid="bibr9-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and based on its success, it has begun to be semisynthetically made under the
name of Taxol/Onxol. Besides their potential of becoming part of the standard
treatment in cancer, plant compounds or whole extracts are used in patient
palliative care and in complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). CAM are used by
around 49% of all cancer patients after the year 2000,<sup><xref rid="bibr10-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> herbal medicine being one of the most used types of CAM, even though many
such therapies have not demonstrated their effectiveness yet.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bibr12-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p><p><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L (<italic>Asteraceae</italic>), the pot
marigold, shows promising results regarding its potential use in cancer management.
In this article, we review the latest updates on <italic>C officinalis</italic>
anticancer activity, both in vitro and in vivo and its phytochemical constituents
that present cytotoxic activity, thereby its potential usage in cancer treatment and
CAM. Furthermore, we emphasize its putative role in patient&#x02019;s palliative care, based
on relevant recent research. An overview of <italic>C officinalis</italic>
anticancer activity is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1534735418803766">Figure 1</xref>.</p><fig id="fig1-1534735418803766" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Overview of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> anticancer activity.
Flowers/flos extracts: in vitro activity, in vivo activity, and in
palliative care; leaves/herba extracts: in vitro activity; roots extract: in
vitro activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534735418803766-fig1"/></fig></sec><sec id="section2-1534735418803766"><title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>: Overview</title><p><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> has long been used in traditional medicine,
and since 2008, it is recognized as an herbal medicinal product by the European
Medicines Agency. Both flowers and leaves of <italic>Calendula</italic> are used
nowadays in folk medicine as anti-inflammatory and antispasmodic medicine, in the
treatment of poorly healing wounds, minor burns, bruises, and rashes, and also in
discomfort alleviation caused by stomach ulcers or inflammation of the oral and
pharyngeal mucosa.<sup><xref rid="bibr13-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p>Topical <italic>C officinalis</italic> formulations are generally considered safe to
use. According to the Safety Assessment of <italic>C officinalis</italic>&#x02013;derived
Cosmetic Ingredients implemented by the Cosmetic Ingredient Review Expert Panel,
different <italic>Calendula</italic> extracts and oils are not significantly toxic
at conventional concentrations but might be mild ocular irritants.<sup><xref rid="bibr14-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> For the majority of patients, <italic>Calendula</italic> products are not
allergenic, but rare cases of sensitization are reported in the literature.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p><p>Several pharmacological activities were reported for different fractions of <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts, among which the most important are the following: anti-inflammatory,<sup><xref rid="bibr16-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> anti-edematous,<sup><xref rid="bibr17-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>and antioxidant activity<sup><xref rid="bibr18-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>; antibacterial<sup><xref rid="bibr19-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> and antifungal activity<sup><xref rid="bibr20-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup>; anti-HIV<sup><xref rid="bibr21-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> and antiviral activity<sup><xref rid="bibr22-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>; wound healing<sup><xref rid="bibr23-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and immunostimulant activity.<sup><xref rid="bibr24-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> The biological activity of each extract is due to its constituents, mostly
plant secondary metabolites. The major classes of compounds found in <italic>C
officinalis</italic> are terpenoids, flavonoids, phenolic acids, carotenoids,
coumarins, quinones, volatile oils, amino acids, and lipids.<sup><xref rid="bibr25-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup></p><p>With the expansion of CAM based on herbs as cancer treatment,<sup><xref rid="bibr10-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> the interest in the putative anticancer efficacy of <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts and compounds has increased. Its cytotoxic effect
on tumor cell lines and its anticancer activity in vivo were first described more
than 25 years ago,<sup><xref rid="bibr26-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> but valuable insight have been gained since. The main antitumor properties of
<italic>C officinalis</italic> on tumor cells and animal models, as well as its
role for palliative care in human cancers, are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1534735418803766">Figure 2</xref>.</p><fig id="fig2-1534735418803766" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The main antitumor properties of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> on in
vitro and in vivo models, as well as its role for palliative care in human
cancers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534735418803766-fig2"/></fig></sec><sec id="section3-1534735418803766"><title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>: Cytotoxic Constituents</title><p>In the past decade, 3 different bioactive compounds isolated from <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts were identified as possessing significant
cytotoxicity toward cancer cell lines in vitro.</p><p>Lutein, isolated through silica gel column fraction chromatography from a methanol
extract of <italic>C officinalis</italic> aerial parts and detected with nuclear
magnetic resonance, was found to possess selective cytotoxic activity toward breast
cancer cell lines.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> The &#x000bc; IC<sub>50</sub> value was 100 &#x000b5;g/mL for MDA-MB-231 cell line and
&#x0003e;100 &#x000b5;g/mL for MCF7 cell line, suggesting that lutein has a greater cytotoxic
activity toward triple-negative breast cancer rather than luminal breast cancer.
Furthermore, significantly lower doses of lutein were cytotoxic toward breast cancer
cell lines, when compared with its activity against the healthy breast cell line
MCF10A. The expression levels of several proapoptotic proteins like p53, bax, and
caspase-3 were increased in lutein-treated cancer cells (except caspase-3 in MCF7,
where the protein was absent), while the expression of Bcl-2, a protein that
inhibits programmed cell death, decreased after treatment.</p><p>Two triterpene glycosides, calenduloside F
6&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-<italic>n</italic>-butyl ester and calenduloside G
6&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-methyl ester, were identified by nuclear magnetic
resonance analysis in the <italic>n</italic>-BuOH-soluble fraction of the methanolic
extract obtained from <italic>C officinalis</italic> dried flowers. Both compounds
were tested in vitro for their cytotoxic activity in 60 cell lines derived from
leukemia, non&#x02013;small cell lung cancer, colon cancer, central nervous system cancer,
melanoma, ovarian cancer, renal cancer, prostate cancer, and breast cancer. At 48
hours after treatment, the IC<sub>50</sub> values for the calenduloside F
6&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-<italic>n</italic>-butyl ester compound were &#x0003c;10 &#x000b5;M for
a wide majority of the tested cell lines, while for the calenduloside G
6&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-methyl ester compound, they were &#x0003c;20 &#x000b5;M, with the
exception of 2 cell lines.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="section4-1534735418803766"><title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>: In Vitro Cytotoxic Activity of
Extracts</title><p>Several recent reports have demonstrated that <italic>C officinalis</italic> extracts
have cytotoxic activity toward different cancer cell lines, but the half maximal
inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) varies widely among the studies,
depending on the extraction solvent and method, the plant organs subjected for
extraction, and the cancer cell line used for each study.</p><p><italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers/flos extracts were investigated extensively in
the past decade, a wide variety of solvents being used for extraction and numerous
cell lines being tested (<xref rid="table1-1534735418803766" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>). Matysik et al<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> tested the methanol, ethyl acetate, and heptane extracts of <italic>C
officinalis</italic> flos against T47D human breast carcinoma cell line and
normal human skin fibroblasts (HSF). After a 24-hour stimulation at a concentration
of 75 &#x000b5;g/mL, the ethyl acetate extract had the lowest cytotoxicity against both cell
lines, the percentage of viable cells being 70.7% for HSF and 58.4% for T47D.
Furthermore, it was observed that higher cell densities were better adapted to
higher doses, the authors suggesting that the compounds found in the ethyl acetate
fraction might be involved in the wound healing activity. Both methanol and heptane
extracts were highly toxic, no HSF cells, and only around 15% of the T47D cells
being viable after 24-hour treatment with each extract at a concentration of 75
&#x000b5;g/mL. The cytotoxic activity of the heptane extract was assigned to different
triterpenes like &#x003b2;-amyrin, while phenolic acids and flavonoid glycosides were
considered responsible for the in vitro effect of the methanol fraction.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></p><table-wrap id="table1-1534735418803766" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The Solvents Used for <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> Flowers/Flos
Extracts; the IC<sub>50</sub> Doses and the Selective Coefficients in the
Antitumor Action for the Extracts on Different Cancer Cell Lines; Other
Cytotoxic Effects (Viability, Growth Inhibition) at Specific Doses and Time Intervals<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1534735418803766">a</xref></sup>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534735418803766-table1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nr Crt</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solvent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tested Cell Line</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub> at 24 Hours</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coefficient of Selectivity</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Other Cytotoxic Effects</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">T47D</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">~50 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">No selectivity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dose at 24 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viability</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">75 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heptane</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~50 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethyl acetate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">~125 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Boiled distilled water<sup><xref rid="bibr30-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HeLa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">750 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">NS</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">NS</td><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fem-X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA-MB-361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2250 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LS174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2300 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K562</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">870 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">LACE</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">B16</td><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">NS</td><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">NS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dose at 72 hours</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth inhibition</td><td rowspan="13" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12" colspan="1">250 &#x000b5;g/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANDO-2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA-MB-231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DU-141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A-549</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMIN PC-1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DLD 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HeLa</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U937</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jurkat T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1534735418803766"><p>Abbreviations: IC<sub>50</sub>, half maximal inhibitory concentration;
NS, not specified.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-1534735418803766"><label>a</label><p>The selectivity coefficient was calculated as the ratio between the
IC<sub>50</sub> doses obtained for healthy cell lines (human skin
fibroblasts by Matysik et al<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>; peripheral blood mononuclear cells by Mati&#x00107; et al<sup><xref rid="bibr30-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>) and the IC<sub>50</sub> doses for the tumor cell lines.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Mati&#x00107; et al<sup><xref rid="bibr30-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> investigated the selective cytotoxicity of <italic>C officinalis</italic>
flower extract against 5 different cancer cell lines (HeLa, Fem-X, MDA-MB-361,
LS174, and K562) in comparison with its effect on healthy immunocompetent peripheral
blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs). The extraction was carried through infusion in
boiled distilled water. The IC<sub>50</sub> value after a 24-hour treatment for the
cancer cell lines varied between 360 &#x000b5;g/mL for the FemX human melanoma cell line and
2300 &#x000b5;g/mL for LS174 human colon carcinoma. Interestingly, the lowest cytotoxicity
was found against PBMCs, with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 3120 &#x000b5;g/mL. In this
context, the pot marigold extract proved to be selective against cancer cell lines
when compared with PBMCs, the selectivity coefficient (ratio between IC<sub>50</sub>
for PBMCs&#x02013;IC<sub>50</sub> for tumor cells) in the antitumor action being 4.16 for
HeLa cells, 8.67 for FemX cells, and 3.59 for K562 cells.</p><p>In the attempt to increase the performance of <italic>C officinalis</italic> flower
extracts, Jimenez-Medina et al<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> investigated the cytotoxic effects of a novel aqueous laser-activated extract
of <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers (LACE). The extract was obtained by
subjecting the flowers to laser therapy at a wavelength of 650 nm for 15 minutes and
further on by suspension of the treated plant material in water. The flower
suspension was maintained at 4&#x000b0;C for 7 to 15 days, and during this period several
additional laser treatments were applied. The in vitro effects of the LACE extract
were determined on 12 different cancer cell lines and also on human peripheral blood
lymphocytes (PBLs). At a concentration of 250 &#x000b5;&#x000b5;g/mL, the treatment with LACE
determined a growth inhibition (GI) of 70% to 100% for all tested cell lines, except
the leukemia cell line U937. LACE was found producing significantly higher
inhibition of tumor cell proliferation when compared with the regular aqueous
extract, yielding similar results as those obtained for the chemotherapeutic drug
paclitaxel. After a 96- to 144-hour treatment with 250-&#x000b5;g/mL LACE, cells belonging
to several cancer cell lines accumulated in the G0/G1 phase, suggesting a cell cycle
arrest in this phase. Furthermore, several proteins like cyclin E and D1, involved
in the progression through the G1 phase and entry in the S phase, had decreased
expression levels after treatment with LACE, in the same cell lines. Treatment with
LACE also induced apoptosis, in some cell lines the caspase-3 protein being
activated by the extract. In contrast with the cytotoxic activity of LACE on cancer
cell lines, the extract proved to significantly increase the proliferation of PBL
cells, with a 3- to 5-fold increase in comparison to the control. Similar results
were also obtained with the regular aqueous <italic>Calendula</italic> extract. The
PBL subpopulations that proliferated after LACE treatment were mainly B lymphocytes,
CD4<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, and natural killer T lymphocytes.</p><p>Although most of the studies were focused on <italic>C officinalis</italic>
flower/flos extracts, 2 recent studies have presented data on the effects of other
parts of this plant. dos Santos et al<sup><xref rid="bibr32-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> studied the cytotoxic effect of leaves extracted in methanol for 51 species
from Brazil, and <italic>C officinalis</italic> was proved to be one of the most
active plants against tumor cells. The IC<sub>50</sub> values measured at 72 hours
after treatment on 4 different cancer cell lines (HL-60, HCT-8, B16, and MCF7)
varied between 50.5 and 83.9 &#x000b5;g/mL, with the highest cytotoxicity against murine
skin melanoma (B16 cell line) and the lowest against breast cancer (MCF7 cell line).
When the concentration was increased to125 &#x000b5;g/mL, the extract caused a cell GI (%)
of more than 90% against all tested cell lines.</p><p>Wegiera et al<sup><xref rid="bibr33-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> conducted an experiment in which the cytotoxic effects of <italic>C
officinalis</italic> roots, herba, and flowers were compared. The plant material
was subjected to extraction in methanol, and the effect was quantified against
J-45.01 cell line (human acute T leukemia). Surprisingly, the highest cytotoxicity
(IC<sub>50</sub>) was found for the roots extract (230 &#x000b5;g/mL), followed by the
flower (330 &#x000b5;g/mL) and herba (410 &#x000b5;g/mL) extracts. After a 24-hour treatment at a
concentration close to the IC<sub>50</sub> value, 35% of the cells were found in an
early apoptotic stage and approximatively 15% in a late apoptotic/necrotic stage for
the roots and herba extracts. On the other hand, using the same experimental design,
35% of the cells that were stimulated with the flower extract were found in a late
apoptotic stage and 15% in an early stage. An increase in both early and late
apoptotic cells was reported in a time-dependent manner, with a 10-fold increase in
the late apoptotic cells fraction after a 48-hour stimulation with the flowers
extract.</p></sec><sec id="section5-1534735418803766"><title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>: In Vivo Toxicity, Chemoprotective
Activity, and Anticancer Activity</title><p>The in vivo activity of <italic>C officinalis</italic> flower extract was
investigated recently regarding toxicity, anti-genotoxic/protective and antitumor
activity, as well as anti-metastatic effects, in different animal models (<xref rid="table2-1534735418803766" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table2-1534735418803766" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>The In Vivo Activity of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> Flowers
Extracts; Doses of Administration, the Cellular Effects, and the
Mechanisms/Genes Modulated by These Extracts on Specific Animal Models.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1534735418803766-table2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nr Crt</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solvent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In Vivo Activity</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal Models</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doses (BW)/Treatment Time</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physiological Effects</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mechanisms/Genes Involved/Activation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Hydro-alcohol</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swiss albino mice</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02a7d;5 g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No acute toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Wistar rats</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02a7d;5 g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No acute toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02a7d;1 g/kg/30 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No subacute toxicity; no alteration in hematological
profile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal and hepatic overload: ALT &#x02191;; BUN &#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">LACE</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balb/c, C57BL/6, and CBA mice</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balb/c 55 mg/kg/30 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No local or systemic toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LD<sub>50</sub> = 550 mg/kg (day 15)</td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wistar rats</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balb/c 550 mg/kg/30 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No local or systemic toxicity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LD<sub>50</sub> = 2750 mg/kg (day 15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Antitumoral effect</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Nude mice bearing ANDO-2 cell line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 mg/kg, orally/12 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60% tumor growth inhibition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survival rate: 75% (day 135)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 mg/kg, intraperitoneally/9 weeks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60% tumor growth inhibition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survival rate: 60% (day 135)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hydro-alcohol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemopreventive effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fischer 344 rats</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 mg/kg/7 days before carcinogenesis initiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of AHF: 49% decrease; area of AHF: 55% decrease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT &#x02193;</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotoxic effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fischer 344 rats</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 mg/kg/7 days before carcinogenesis initiation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of AHF: 42% increase; area of AHF: 46% increase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT &#x02191;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methanol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemopreventive effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swiss albino mice</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 mg/kg/32 weeks (16 during promotion and 16 after
carcinogenesis)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of tumors: 15% decrease; tumor size: decreased</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell proliferation &#x02193;: PCNA &#x02193;, p38 MAPK &#x02193;; apoptosis &#x02191;: p53 &#x02191;;
inflammation &#x02193;: NF&#x003ba;B&#x02193;, COX-2 &#x02193;; immune surveillance &#x02191;: LC &#x02191;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethanol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimetastatic effect</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C57BL/6 mice bearing B16F-10 cell line</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 mg/kg/10 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Life span: 43.3% increase; 74% inhibiton of lung tumor nodes
formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sia &#x02193;; GGT&#x02193;; Lox &#x02193;; P4H &#x02193;; MMP-2 &#x02193;; MMP-9 &#x02193;; TIMP-1 &#x02191;; TIMP-2
&#x02191;;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-1534735418803766"><p>Abbreviations: BW, body weight; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; BUN, blood
urea nitrogen; LD<sub>50</sub>, lethal dose 50%; AHF, altered hepatocyte
foci; GGT, &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase; PCNA, proliferating cell nuclear
antigen; p38 MAPK, p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase; p53, p53 tumor
suppressor protein; NF&#x003ba;B, nuclear factor NF&#x003ba;B; COX-2, cyclooxygenase-2;
LC, Langerhans cells; Sia, sialic acid; Lox, lysyl oxidase; P4H, prolyl
hydroxylase; MMP-2, matrix metalloproteinases-2; MMP-9, matrix
metalloproteinases-9; TIMP-1, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1;
TIMP-2, tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-2.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Silva et al<sup><xref rid="bibr34-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> investigated the toxicity of the <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers
hydro-alcohol extract, in Wistar rats and in Swiss albino mice strain. No acute
toxicity was recorded after oral administration of the extract in doses up to 5 g/kg
body weight in both animal models. No subacute toxicity was observed in Wistar rats
after treatment with doses up to 1 g/kg body weight. Several hematologic
(erythrocyte count, mean corpuscular volume, different leucocytes count, etc) and
biochemical (glucose, triglycerides, proteins, cholesterol quantities, etc)
parameters were determined in blood or serum and proved to remain within the
reference range after treatment. However, both blood urea nitrogen and alanine
aminotransferase were found increased in blood in a dose-dependent manner,
suggesting the possibility of renal and hepatic overload.</p><p>Based on the in vitro success of LACE extract on different cancer cell lines,
Jimenez-Medina et al<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> also investigated the in vivo toxicity of LACE extract in Balb/c, C57BL/6,
and CBA mice and also in Wistar rats. After oral administration of 11 and 55 mg/kg
body weight LACE extract for 30 consecutive days in all tested mice, no toxicity,
local or systemic, was observed. Similar results were obtained for a dose of 11, 55,
and 550 mg/kg body weight LACE in Wistar rats. Following the toxicity assays, the in
vivo antitumor activity was investigated in nude mice bearing ANDO-2 human melanoma
cell line. The mice were administrated with 50 mg/kg body weight (orally) and 25
mg/kg body weight (intraperitoneal route) of LACE. The extract showed a tumor GI of
60%, similar result being also obtained with the chemotherapeutic drug Taxol.
Furthermore, at 135 days after ANDO-2 injection, the survival rate was 75% in
LACE-oral group and 60% in LACE-intraperitoneal group, while no mice were still
alive in the control group.</p><p>Changing the approach, Barajas-Farias et al<sup><xref rid="bibr35-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> evaluated the anti-genotoxic effects of <italic>C officinalis</italic>
flowers aqueous-ethanol extract in male Fischer 344 rats in which the carcinogenesis
was initiated with <italic>N-</italic>nitrosodiethylamine and promoted with
2-acetylaminofluorene. The in vivo activity of the extract was evaluated based on
the area and number of altered hepatocyte foci (AHF) or &#x003b3;-glutamyl
transpeptidase&#x02013;positive foci in the resistant hepatocyte model in rats. In the
control group, in which the animals were treated only with the carcinogens, the area
and number of AHF were 5.5% and 17.5 AHF/cm<sup>2</sup>, respectively. In the
treated group, after the administration of the extract in the range of 0.1 to 2.5
mg/kg body weight, both parameters decreased, with a maximum inhibition of 55% in
the area and 49% in the number of the AHF, at a dose of 2.5 mg/kg body weight. On
the other hand, when the treatment was administrated in doses higher than 20 mg/kg
body weight, the extract proved to have genotoxic activity, with an increment of 40%
and 53% in the area and number of AHF at a dose of 40 mg/kg body weight.
Furthermore, at the same dose of 40 mg/kg body weight, the extract could promote the
carcinogenesis but not initiate it. Therefore, the <italic>C officinalis</italic>
extract has a dual dose-dependent effect in vivo, being anti-genotoxic (protective)
when administrated in low doses but becoming genotoxic in high doses.</p><p>Ali et al<sup><xref rid="bibr36-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> investigated the chemopreventive effects of a methanolic extract obtained
from <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers in a DMBA-initiated, croton oil-promoted
skin carcinogenesis model in Swiss albino mice. The extract was administrated at a
dose of 10 mg/kg body weight every time the mice were treated with croton oil and
further on for 16 weeks, after the promoter application ended. The extract reduced
the number, incidence, and multiplicity of tumors on the skin, the average number of
tumors per tumor-bearing mouse decreasing with approximatively 15% in the
extract-treated group. The tumor size was also reduced, and a normal skin
stratification was observed in the treated group. The expression of the
proliferating cell nuclear antigen (PCNA) and the cell cycle progression marker p38
MAPK were both suppressed by the extract, suggesting a reduction in tumor cell
proliferation in the treated group. Furthermore, higher levels of the p53 tumor
suppressor protein were found in the tumors of the extract-treated group when
compared with the control tumor-bearing mice; thus, the extract might induce
apoptosis. Other relevant effects observed in the <italic>C
officinalis</italic>&#x02013;treated group were reduced skin inflammation, which might be a
good chemopreventive target, and enhanced immune surveillance, by retention of the
Langerhans cells in the epidermis.</p><p>Preethi et al<sup><xref rid="bibr37-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> investigated the antimetastatic activity of <italic>C officinalis</italic>
flowers extract in C57BL/6 mice injected with B16F-10 melanoma cells. The extract,
ethanol based, was orally administrated at a dose of 250 mg/kg body weight for 10
consecutive days. The extract increased the life span by 43.3% among treated animals
when compared with untreated tumor-bearing mice. Levels of salicylic acid, often
found increased in tumors, and &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase, a proliferation marker,
were found significantly reduced in the serum of treated animals. At 21 days after
injection with B16F-10 cells, the treated group showed reduced number of lung tumor
nodes, reduction of tumor size, relatively tumor-free alveoli and bronchioles, and
alveolar passage similar to the healthy group, suggesting a lung metastasis
inhibition by the <italic>C officinalis</italic> extract. Furthermore, several
metastasis markers involved in the synthesis or degradation of extracellular matrix
components were differently expressed in treated animals when compared with the
untreated group, supporting the histopathological results. Hydroxyproline, a marker
for lung fibrosis and hexosamine, a substrate for collagen synthesis, were found
reduced in the extract-treated group. Lysyl oxidase (Lox), an enzyme inducing
cross-linking in the extracellular matrix, and prolyl hydroxylase (P4H), an enzyme
implicated in the synthesis of collagen, were both inhibited by the extract. MMP-2
and MMP-9, matrix metalloproteinases responsible for degrading the basal membrane,
and thus promoting invasion, were found downregulated by the extract. Moreover, the
expression of the tissue inhibitors of the metalloproteases TIMP-1 and TIMP-2 was
activated. Therefore, the authors conclude that <italic>C officinalis</italic>
flower extract increases life span but also inhibits lung metastasis in
tumor-bearing mice.</p></sec><sec id="section6-1534735418803766"><title><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> in Cancer Palliative Care</title><p>Albeit <italic>C officinalis</italic> has demonstrated the cytotoxic and antitumor
effects in in vitro and in vivo models, its use in human cancer management is
generally limited to the treatment of the secondary effects induced by
radiochemotherapy. Palliative care, an important part of cancer management nowadays,
is focused on improving the quality of life in cancer patients by treating the
symptoms and side effects of the disease and its treatment. With this purpose, more
and more cancer patients are using CAM, including herbal remedies,<sup><xref rid="bibr10-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> even though little supporting scientific data are available at this moment.<sup><xref rid="bibr12-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Several recent clinical trials have suggested that <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts could be a relevant resource in diminishing the
side effects of radiotherapy in breast, head, and neck cancer patients.</p><p>In a simple-blinded phase III randomized clinical trial including 254 breast cancer
patients, the liposoluble fraction of <italic>C officinalis</italic> extracted in
petroleum jelly was evaluated about its putative role in prevention of acute
radiation-induced dermatitis of grade 2 or higher. The prevention capacity was
assessed compared with trolamine, a topical agent often prescribed during
radiotherapy as part of the breast cancer palliative care. The incidence of grade 2
or 3 skin acute toxicity in the <italic>Calendula</italic>-treated group was 41%,
while 63% of the patients treated with trolamine showed mild to severe dermatitis.
Furthermore, in the <italic>Calendula-</italic>treated group, no allergic reactions
were observed and the extract proved to be more effective in reducing pain among
patients. Therefore, <italic>C officinalis</italic> might be a good nonsteroid agent
for the prevention of radiation-induced dermatitis in breast cancer patients.<sup><xref rid="bibr38-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> Albeit the effectiveness of <italic>Calendula</italic> was better than that
of trolamine, it should be noted that the choice of trolamine as a reference was not
based on its effectiveness in the treatment of radiotherapy-induced dermatitis, but
on the data of the randomized RTOG (Radiation Therapy Oncology Group) study, which
suggest its curative properties.<sup><xref rid="bibr39-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> Moreover, in a recent meta-analysis, trolamine was found to be ineffective in
the prevention and treatment of radiation dermatitis<sup><xref rid="bibr40-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>; thus, its usage as a control in such a clinical trial is questionable.</p><p>Another randomized, 2-armed, blinded, phase III trial was conducted on 420 patients
to compare the effectiveness of 2 different commercial products: the topical
<italic>Calendula</italic> cream (Weleda AG, Sweden) and an aqueous emulsion
with strong moisturizing and protective qualities (Essex-Schering-Plough), in
prevention of acute radiation skin reaction (ARSR) in breast cancer patients. The
incidence of severe ARSR was similar in the 2 treated groups, with 23% of the
patients presenting severe skin reactions for the topical <italic>Calendula</italic>
cream and 19% for the aqueous cream&#x02013;treated group. Therefore, the skin care product
chosen had little effect on radiation-induced dermatitis.<sup><xref rid="bibr41-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> Overall, the patients in both groups reported lower levels of skin toxicity
(23% and 19%) when compared with the patients included in the previous clinical
trial (41% and 63% for the <italic>Calendula</italic>- and trolamine-treated group,
respectively). The authors suggest that the decreased levels of the skin reaction
symptoms are due to an improved photon therapy and a fewer smokers included in their
study. Moreover, the differences between the study design and the number of patients
could stand of the bottom of the differences between the data provided by these
studies.</p><p>Radiodermatitis is a common side effect of radiotherapy, but it occurs more often in
patients with head and neck cancer, due to the area of the treatment field. A
randomized double-blind controlled clinical trial was conducted on 51 head and neck
cancer patients to evaluate the effectiveness of <italic>C officinalis</italic> in
the prevention and treatment of radiodermatitis in comparison with a lotion based on
essential fatty acids (EFA), an often recommended palliative therapy in head and
neck cancer patients. Each product was applied on the skin, twice a day, during the
radiotherapy period. <italic>Calendula</italic> proved to be more effective in
preventing the development of radiodermatitis, after 15 treatment sessions, the
incidence of grade 1 dermatitis being 40.73% for the EFA group and only 25% in the
<italic>Calendula</italic>-treated group. Furthermore, after the last session of
radiotherapy, the incidence of grade 2 or 3 radiodermatitis was 21.43% for the
<italic>Calendula</italic>-treated group, while in the EFA group, it was almost
double (46.16%). Although <italic>Calendula</italic> proved to be a better
palliative care option than EFA treatment for the prevention of radiation-induced
dermatitis in head and neck cancer patients, it has to be mentioned that only 27
patients were finally included for statistical analysis.<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Furthermore, even though EFA lotions are an often recommended palliative
therapy in some clinics,<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> there are no available studies in the literature that prove their
effectiveness in the prevention of radiation-induced skin toxicity.</p><p>Another relevant side effect of radiotherapy in head and neck patients is the
radiation-induced oropharyngeal mucositis (OM), with more than 80% of the patients
reporting an inflammation of the oral mucosa during treatment.<sup><xref rid="bibr43-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> In this context, a placebo-controlled clinical trial conducted on 40 head and
neck cancer patients proved that <italic>C officinalis</italic> flower extract
mouthwash significantly decreased the intensity of radiation-induced OM after 2, 3,
and 6 weeks of treatment. The authors suggest that the inhibition of OM occurrence
is at least partially caused by the extract antioxidant capacity.<sup><xref rid="bibr44-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p><p>Using different referent agents, such as hyaluronic acid <italic>Aloe vera</italic>,
corticosteroid cream, commercial emulsion with strong moisturizing and protective
qualities, or placebo, makes the data difficult to compare between studies.
Moreover, different kinds of study designs including simple- or double-blind
randomized studies may introduce sources of bias in treatment assignments.
Generally, the studies have partially described the biases risks and how they could
be avoided. In a previous study, it was highlighted that trials with inadequate or
unclear randomization design lead to overestimation of the treatment effects up to
40% compared with data from trials with proper randomization.<sup><xref rid="bibr45-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup></p><p>However, even if data from previous studies are not really comparable, it is already
stated that <italic>Calendula</italic> could be considered for human cancer
management, especially for the treatment of the secondary effects induced by
radiochemotherapy. Further studies based on proper randomization design and using
high number of patients will certainly establish the efficiency and usefulness of
<italic>Calendula</italic> in cancer management.</p></sec><sec id="section7-1534735418803766"><title>Conclusions, Challenges, and Perspectives</title><p><italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> extracts and isolated compounds have revealed
a reliable potential in cancer management, both in treatment and in palliative care.
Several extracts present significant in vitro selective cytotoxicity toward large
panels of cancer cell lines when compared with healthy cells. The cytotoxic activity
against cancer cell lines reported for different <italic>C officinalis</italic>
extracts varies widely among recent studies (IC<sub>50</sub> values between 50.5 and
2300 &#x000b5;g/mL). Most of the recent research was conducted on flowers/flos extracts,
even though Wegiera et al<sup><xref rid="bibr33-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> suggested that root extracts might possess higher cytotoxicity toward cancer
cell lines. Accordingly, even if no study presented data on a combination of flower
and roots extracts, we consider that this approach could represent a challenge that
has to be explored in the near future. Methanol is the most used solvent for
extraction. Extracts obtained through infusion in distilled water have lower
cytotoxic activities, even though Jimenez-Medina et al<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> reported much better results if the aqueous extract is laser-activated.
Nevertheless, the methanolic extract of <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers did
not have selective cytotoxicity toward cancer cell lines when compared with HSFs,
while the ethyl acetate extract selectively killed tumor cells in the same
experimental design.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> The aqueous extract obtained from flowers also proved to possess selective
cytotoxic activity against different cancer cell lines when compared with healthy PBMCs.<sup><xref rid="bibr30-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Furthermore, the laser-activated aqueous extract proved to have
immunostimulant activity, by increasing the proliferation of several PBL subpopulations.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> As a consequence, different extraction procedures that use distilled water as
the extraction solvent might be better options than extraction in methanol, even
though the cytotoxic activity against cancer cell lines is lower for the aqueous
extracts.</p><p>However, all the IC<sub>50</sub> values reported for the <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts are rather high, none of them being smaller than
20 &#x000b5;g/mL, the standard threshold concentration used in conventional drug discovery
studies, according to the US National Cancer Institute.<sup><xref rid="bibr46-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> In this context, the required dose for effective cytotoxicity in vivo, based
on the in vitro results, would be most probably higher than the safe dose.
Furthermore, achieving in vivo plasma concentration higher than 20 &#x000b5;g/mL for
extracts is difficult, leading to limitations in the uptake of the active compounds.<sup><xref rid="bibr47-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Therefore, the chances that singular extracts from <italic>C
officinalis</italic> to be used as a treatment option in clinical settings are
greatly diminished. However, the required doses for effective cytotoxicity in vivo
might be decreased by using synergistic combinations with other plant formulas, a
highly recommended approach for drugs isolated from plants.<sup><xref rid="bibr47-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> Further in vitro investigations are needed to assess the synergistic effect
of <italic>C officinalis</italic> extracts with other known anticancer plant
compounds.</p><p><italic>C officinalis</italic> extracts proved to have no or low general toxicity in
animal models, while they possessed chemopreventive, antitumor, and antimetastatic
activity in vivo. Research conducted to date has emphasized different <italic>C
officinalis</italic> extracts without in vivo toxicity when used for oral
administration from 1 to 5 g/kg body weight in mice and rat models, respectively,<sup><xref rid="bibr34-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> or up to 55 mg/kg body weight in mice and 550 mg/kg in rats.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Nevertheless, the posttreatment possibility of hepatic and renal overload was suggested.<sup><xref rid="bibr34-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Both aqueous-ethanol<sup><xref rid="bibr35-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> and methanol<sup><xref rid="bibr36-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> extracts of <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers proved to have
chemopreventive/anti-genotoxic activities in 2 different carcinogenesis models, at
much lower effective concentrations than the toxicity threshold concentration
identified in all other studies.<sup><xref rid="bibr29-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="bibr32-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> However, Barajas-Farias et al<sup><xref rid="bibr35-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> suggest that the extract not only becomes genotoxic if administrated in high
doses but also could replace the carcinogenesis promoter. The in vivo antitumor
cytotoxic activity was proven in nude mice bearing ANDO-2 human melanoma cell line,
in which the LACE extract inhibited the tumor growth by 60% and significantly
extended the animal&#x02019;s life span.<sup><xref rid="bibr31-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> Moreover, another <italic>C officinalis</italic> flowers extract increased
the life span by 43% in lab mice injected with B16F-10 melanoma cells and possessed
antimetastatic activity in these tumor-bearing mice.</p><p>Only 3 compounds were individually identified in <italic>C officinalis</italic>
extracts to possess cytotoxic activity against different cancer cell lines. However,
there is a high possibility for other constituents, mainly terpenoids and
polyphenols, to be further identified as antitumor agents. Lutein was found to have
selective cytotoxicity toward breast cancer cell lines, by inducing apoptosis in
these cells.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Other 2 triterpene glycosides were identified as highly cytotoxic against a
large panel of cancer cell lines in vitro.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> According to the US National Cancer Institute plant screening program, for a
compound to be considered cytotoxic toward cancer cell lines, the IC<sub>50</sub>
values have to be &#x0003c;10 &#x000b5;M.<sup><xref rid="bibr46-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup> Therefore, at least the calenduloside F
6&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-<italic>n</italic>-butyl ester compound shows promising
results as a potential anticancer drug.</p><p>Finally, <italic>C officinalis</italic> extracts might be good alternatives to
current palliative treatments, which aim to diminish the side effects of
radiotherapy. Two phase III randomized clinical trials, totalizing 674 breast cancer
patients, tested the effectiveness of <italic>Calendula</italic> extracts in the
prevention of acute radiation-induced dermatitis.<sup><xref rid="bibr38-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="bibr41-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> In the first one, the extract
proved to be superior in its activity when compared with trolamine.<sup><xref rid="bibr38-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> However, in a recent study, trolamine proved to be ineffective in the
prevention of radiotherapy-associated dermatitis.<sup><xref rid="bibr40-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> In the second clinical trial, Sharp et al<sup><xref rid="bibr41-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> found no differences in the prevention of ARSR when comparing the standard
<italic>Calendula</italic> cream and a topical aqueous cream often prescribed
during radiation treatment. None of these studies use a vehicle-controlled placebo;
thus, the effectiveness of the <italic>Calendula</italic>-based treatments is not
actually assessed. Taking into consideration these conflicting data and the absence
of the placebo groups from the studies, <italic>Calendula</italic> products might be
good alternatives to the topical palliative treatments of radiation-induced
dermatitis in breast cancer patients, but further investigations regarding their
efficacy are necessary.</p><p>Two other clinical trials suggest that different <italic>C officinalis</italic>
extracts are effective in the prevention and treatment of radiodermatitis<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> and of radiation-induced OM<sup><xref rid="bibr44-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> in head and neck cancer patients. The first extract showed better results in
preventing dermatitis than the EFA treatment.<sup><xref rid="bibr42-1534735418803766" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> However, there are no data available at this moment to prove the
effectiveness of EFA lotions in preventing radiation-induced OM. Furthermore, no
placebo group was used in this clinical trial; thus, issues regarding the actual
effectiveness of the <italic>Calendula</italic> extract are raised again.</p><p>In conclusion, <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> shows promising results
regarding its potential usage in cancer management, especially in cancer prevention,
treatment, and in palliative care. However, without knowing the bioactive
constituents responsible for the in vitro and in vivo selective cytotoxicity as well
as for the prevention of radiotherapy-induced side effects, moving forward to
relevant preclinical trials is hampered. Therefore, intensive research is essential
toward identifying novel <italic>C officinalis</italic> constituents, which might
become relevant resources in cancer management.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This work was
supported in part by ANCS (Grant P_40_318/2016).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-1534735418803766"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>World Cancer Report 2014</source>.
<publisher-loc>Lyon, France</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International
Agency for Research on Cancer</publisher-name>;
<year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-1534735418803766"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azim</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jr</surname><given-names>de</given-names></name><name><surname>Azambuja</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Colozza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccart</surname><given-names>MJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term toxic effects of adjuvant chemotherapy in breast
cancer</article-title>. <source>Ann Oncol</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1939</fpage>-<lpage>1947</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21289366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-1534735418803766"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luqmani</surname><given-names>YA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms of drug resistance in cancer
chemotherapy</article-title>. <source>Med Princ Pract</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>suppl
1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-1534735418803766"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lippert</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruoff</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Volm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Intrinsic and acquired drug resistance in malignant tumors. The
main reason for therapeutic failure</article-title>.
<source>Arzneimittelforschung</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>-<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18677966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-1534735418803766"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaumaya</surname><given-names>PT.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cancer immunotherapy: present status, future perspective, and a
new paradigm of peptide immunotherapeutics</article-title>. <source>Discov
Med</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>-<lpage>176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23545045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-1534735418803766"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezzuto</surname><given-names>JM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Botanicals in cancer chemoprevention</article-title>.
<source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source>.
<year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12549763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-1534735418803766"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nirmala</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samundeeswari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankar</surname><given-names>PD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Natural plant resources in anti-cancer therapy&#x02014;a
review</article-title>. <source>Res Plant Biol</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-1534735418803766"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>World Health Organization</collab>. <source>WHO Model List of Essential
Medicines</source>. <edition>20th ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health
Organization</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-1534735418803766"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>BA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>How Taxol/paclitaxel kills cancer cells</article-title>.
<source>Mol Biol Cell</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>2677</fpage>-<lpage>2681</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25213191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-1534735418803766"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horneber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bueschel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Less</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwahlen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>How many cancer patients use complementary and alternative
medicine: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>.
<source>Integr Cancer Ther</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22019489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-1534735418803766"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olaku</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Herbal therapy use by cancer patients: a literature review on
case reports</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>508</fpage>-<lpage>514</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21185719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-1534735418803766"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posadzki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Adverse effects of herbal medicines: an overview of systematic
reviews</article-title>. <source>Clin Med (Lond)</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23472485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-1534735418803766"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastogi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>AK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Review on pharmacological update: <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> Linn</article-title>. <source>Inventi Impact:
Planta Activa</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-1534735418803766"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergfeld</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Belsito</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Final report of the Cosmetic Ingredient Review
Expert Panel amended safety assessment of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic>-derived cosmetic ingredients</article-title>.
<source>Int J Toxicol</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6
suppl</issue>):<fpage>221S</fpage>-<lpage>243S</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21164072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-1534735418803766"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calapai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Miroddi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minciullo</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputi</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangemi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>RJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contact dermatitis as an adverse reaction to some topically used
European herbal medicinal products-part 1:</article-title>
<source>Achillea millefolium</source>-<source>Curcuma longa. Contact
Dermatitis</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-1534735418803766"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preethi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of flower extract of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> Linn and its possible mechanism of
action</article-title>. <source>Indian J Exp Biol</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>-<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19374166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-1534735418803766"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zitterl-Eglseer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurenitsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-oedematous activities of the main
triterpendiol esters of marigold (<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>
L)</article-title>. <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>.
<year>1997</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-1534735418803766"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Salobir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Salobir</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The comparison of in vivo antigeno-toxic antioxidative capacity
of two propylene glycol extracts of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>
(marigold) and vitamin E in young growing pigs</article-title>
<source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr (Berl)</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18700847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-1534735418803766"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antimicrobial and phytochemical estimation of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> against human pathogenic</article-title>.
<source>Int J Innov Bio Sci</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-1534735418803766"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gazim</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraga</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Svidzinski</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>DA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antifungal activity of the essential oil from <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> L (asteraceae) growing in Brazil</article-title>.
<source>Braz J Microbiol</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-1534735418803766"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalvatchev</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Walder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Garzaro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-HIV activity of extracts from <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> flowers</article-title>. <source>Biomed
Pharmacother</source>.
<year>1997</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-1534735418803766"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogdanova</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolaeva</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shcherbakova</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolstova</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Moskalenko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pershin</surname><given-names>GN.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Study of antiviral properties of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> [in Russian]</article-title>. <source>Farmakol
Toksikol</source>.
<year>1970</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>-<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4318166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-1534735418803766"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parente</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rde</surname><given-names>SLJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tresvenzol</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinaud</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>NM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Wound healing and anti-inflammatory effect in animal models of
<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L growing in
Brazil</article-title>. <source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>375671</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22315631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-1534735418803766"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varlijen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural analysis of rhamnoarabinogalactans and
arabinogalactans with immunostimulating activity from</article-title>
<source>Calendula officinalis. Phytochemistry</source>.
<year>1989</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2379</fpage>-<lpage>2383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-1534735418803766"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>JAT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biology of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> Linn: focus on pharmacology, biological activities
and agronomic practices</article-title>. <source>Med Aromat Plant Sci
Biotechnol</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-1534735418803766"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boucaud-Maitre</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Algernon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Raynaud</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytotoxic and antitumoral activity of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> extracts</article-title>.
<source>Pharmazie</source>.
<year>1988</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3380875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-1534735418803766"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behbahani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of in vitro anticancer activity of <italic>Ocimum
basilicum, Alhagi maurorum, Calendula officinalis</italic> and their
parasite</article-title>
<source>Cuscuta campestris. PLoS One</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e116049</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25548920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-1534735418803766"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ukiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akihisa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory, anti-tumor-promoting, and cytotoxic activities
of constituents of marigold (<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>)
flowers</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod</source>.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1692</fpage>-<lpage>1696</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-1534735418803766"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matysik</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f3;jciak-Kosior</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paduch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The influence of <italic>Calendulae officinalis</italic> flos
extracts on cell cultures, and the chromatographic analysis of
extracts</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Biomed Anal</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>-<lpage>292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15925220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-1534735418803766"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mati&#x00107;</surname><given-names>IZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurani&#x00107;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Savikin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zduni&#x00107;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Na&#x00111;vinski</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Go&#x00111;evac</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Chamomile and marigold tea: chemical characterization and
evaluation of anticancer activity</article-title>. <source>Phytother
Res</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>852</fpage>-<lpage>858</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-1534735418803766"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez-Medina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Lora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Algarra</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Collado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A new extract of the plant <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>
produces a dual in vitro effect: cytotoxic anti-tumor activity and
lymphocyte activation</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16677386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-1534735418803766"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of native and exotic Brazilian plants
for anticancer activity</article-title>. <source>J Nat Med</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20127421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-1534735418803766"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wegiera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolarz</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jedruch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Korczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopro&#x00144;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytotoxic effect of some medicinal plants from
<italic>Asteraceae</italic> family on J-45.01 leukemic cell line&#x02014;pilot
study</article-title>. <source>Acta Pol Pharm</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22568040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-1534735418803766"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Toxicological studies on hydroalcohol extract of
<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L</article-title>.
<source>Phytother Res</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17221830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-1534735418803766"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barajas-Farias</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Carre&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Arce-Popoca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A dual and opposite effect of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> flower extract: chemoprotector and promoter in a
rat hepatocarcinogenesis model</article-title>. <source>Planta Med</source>.
<year>2006</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16534725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-1534735418803766"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lateef</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Assessment of augmented immune surveillance and tumor cell death
by cytoplasmic stabilization of p53 as a chemopreventive strategy of 3
promising medicinal herbs in murine 2-stage skin
carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Integr Cancer Ther</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>-<lpage>367</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24363284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-1534735418803766"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preethi</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Siveen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of metastasis of B16F-10 melanoma cells in C57BL/6
mice by an extract of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> L
flowers</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1773</fpage>-<lpage>1779</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21338232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-1534735418803766"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunyach</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Hombres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Montbarbon</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Phase III randomized trial of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> compared with trolamine for the prevention of acute
dermatitis during irradiation for breast cancer</article-title>. <source>J
Clin Oncol</source>.
<year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1447</fpage>-<lpage>1453</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-1534735418803766"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Randomized phase III study comparing Best
Supportive Care to Biafine as a prophylactic agent for radiation-induced
skin toxicity for women undergoing breast irradiation: Radiation Therapy
Oncology Group (RTOG) 97-13</article-title>. <source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol
Phys</source>.
<year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1307</fpage>-<lpage>1310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-1534735418803766"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meneses</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>ENS</given-names></name><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>EB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Use of trolamine to prevent and treat acute radiation dermatitis:
a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Rev Lat Am
Enfermagem</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>e2929</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29742271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-1534735418803766"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrahamsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatschek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergenmar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>No differences between <italic>Calendula</italic> cream and
aqueous cream in the prevention of acute radiation skin reactions&#x02014;results
from a randomised blinded trial</article-title>. <source>Eur J Oncol
Nurs</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>-<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23245940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-1534735418803766"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Danski</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vayego</surname><given-names>SA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Usage of <italic>Calendula officinalis</italic> in the prevention
and treatment of radiodermatitis: a randomized double-blind controlled
clinical trial [in Portuguese]</article-title>. <source>Rev Esc Enferm
USP</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25992820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-1534735418803766"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellm</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Mucositis incidence, severity and associated
outcomes in patients with head and neck cancer receiving radiotherapy with
or without chemotherapy: a systematic literature review</article-title>.
<source>Radiother Oncol</source>.
<year>2003</year>;<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12742264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-1534735418803766"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babaee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moslemi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalilpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Antioxidant capacity of <italic>Calendula
officinalis</italic> flowers extract and prevention of radiation induced
oropharyngeal mucositis in patients with head and neck cancers: a randomized
controlled clinical study</article-title>. <source>Daru</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23497687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-1534735418803766"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An overview of randomization techniques: an unbiased assessment
of outcome in clinical research</article-title>. <source>J Hum Reprod
Sci</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21772732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-1534735418803766"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiebig</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Preclinical screening for new anticancer
agents</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Figg</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group> eds. <source>Handbook of Anticancer Pharmacokinetics and
Pharmacodynamics</source>. <publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name>;
<volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-1534735418803766"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Natural Compounds in Cancer Therapy</source>. <edition>1st ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>Princeton, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oregon Medical
Press</publisher-name>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>