<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">AoB Plants</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">AoB Plants</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aobpla</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">aobpla</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>AoB Plants</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-2851</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4568204</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26209687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aobpla/plv086</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">plv086</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1005</subject><subject>1007</subject><subject>1023</subject><subject>1029</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gradients of metabolite accumulation and redifferentiation of nutritive cells associated with vascular tissues in galls induced by sucking insects</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>Ren&#x000ea; Gon&#x000e7;alves da Silva</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>Rosy Mary dos Santos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff><addr-line>Departamento de Bot&#x000e2;nica, Instituto de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas</addr-line>, <institution>Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</institution>, <addr-line>Av. Ant&#x000f4;nio Carlos, 6627, Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* Corresponding author's e-mail address: <email>rosy@icb.ufmg.br</email>; <email>rosy.isaias@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="an1"><p><bold>Associate Editor:</bold> John Runions</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>plv086</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Annals of Botany Company.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="plv086.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>Galls are structures entirely made of plant tissues manipulated by gall-inducing parasites. We analyzed the alterations of cell phenotypes caused by a sucking-insect, <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>, on the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> that led to the formation of a globoid gall morphotype. We found changed cell fates in the leaves compared to the galls, and different degrees of cell alterations in gall layers, which formed gradients. Surprisingly, the vascular parenchyma cells on <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls are nutritive. Herein, we show that even though the globoid shape is one of the most common in nature, the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> are unique entities.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Plant cells respond to abiotic and biotic stimuli, which generate adaptive phenotypes in plant organs. In the case of plant galls, cell phenotypes are adaptive for the gall inducer and assume characteristics mainly linked to its protection and nutrition. Herein, the cytological development and histochemical profile of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic> galls, a sucking insect, on the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> are compared with those of other galls, especially <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls, searching for conserved and divergent alterations in cell fates and cycles. Leaf cell fates are completely changed within galls, except for epidermal cells, but the comparison between <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. galls shows conserved fates. Nevertheless, cytological development of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls is different from the standby-redifferentiation of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls. Starch and lignins, and reducing sugars form centrifugal and centripetal gradients of accumulation, respectively. Proteins, total phenolics, terpenoids, proanthocyanidins and reactive oxygen species are detected in bidirectional gradients, i.e. weak or undetectable reaction in the median cortical cells that is gradually more intense in the cell layers towards the inner and outer surfaces of the gall. True nutritive cells associated with vascular tissues, together with the bidirectional gradients of metabolite accumulation, are herein reported for the first time in insect galls. The globoid galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>, though macro-morphologically similar to the galls of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic>, are distinct and unique among insect galls, as far as the cellular, subcellular and histochemical traits are concerned. Thus, the traits of the galls on <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> studied herein represent the extended phenotypes of their inducers.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Carbohydrate-related enzyme activity</kwd><kwd>cytology</kwd><kwd>development</kwd><kwd>gall</kwd><kwd>metabolic gradients</kwd><kwd>primary and secondary metabolites</kwd><kwd><italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (Brazil)</funding-source><award-id>307007/2012-2</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-2"><funding-source>Empresa Brasileira de Pesquisa Agropecu&#x000e1;ria</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-3"><funding-source>&#x02018;Manejo e biodiversidade de Psylloidea associados ao sistema integra&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o lavoura&#x02014;pecu&#x000e1;ria&#x02014;floresta e &#x000e0; citricultura no Brasil&#x02019;</funding-source><award-id>02.12.01.028.00.00</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-4"><funding-source>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (Brazil)</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-5"><funding-source>Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (Brazil)</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The capability of insects to induce galls depends on variable properties of plant cells, which are ultimately defined by the biotic and abiotic stimuli from the surrounding environment, and lead to different cell phenotypes (<xref rid="PLV086C31" ref-type="bibr">Gianoli and Valladares 2012</xref>). Plant cells under the influence of gall-inducing insects redifferentiate (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C46" ref-type="bibr">Lev-Yadun 2003</xref>) and often assume rapid cell cycles and new cell fates for the neo-ontogenesis of plant galls (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C16" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>). Even though specific galling insect taxa are classically known to induce conserved, morphologically different galls (<xref rid="PLV086C48" ref-type="bibr">Mani 1964</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C68" ref-type="bibr">Rohfritsch 1992</xref>), recent studies have documented extremely diverse aspects of cell biology in neotropical galls (<xref rid="PLV086C52" ref-type="bibr">Moura <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C56" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2009</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C57" ref-type="bibr">2010<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C30" ref-type="bibr">Formiga <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C18" ref-type="bibr">Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C5" ref-type="bibr">Bedetti <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C22" ref-type="bibr">Dias <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C25" ref-type="bibr">Ferreira and Isaias 2013</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C33" ref-type="bibr">Guimar&#x000e3;es <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C34" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>The metabolism of certain neotropical gall taxa has been assessed using cytological and histochemical methods (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C60" ref-type="bibr">2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C61" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C74" ref-type="bibr">Vecchi <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) in the search for gradients already described for nutritive tissues in Cynipidae and Cecidomyiidae galls (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>). In the Neotropical galls with true nutritive tissues, some of the metabolic gradients proposed by <xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner (1992)</xref> were corroborated (<xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C61" ref-type="bibr">2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). Unexpectedly, cytological and histochemical gradients, i.e. increasing degree of cell alterations and of metabolite accumulation in the cortical cells of the gall towards the larval chamber, are also reported for the galls induced by the sucking insect, <italic>Pseudophacopteron</italic> sp. (Psyllidae), on <italic>Aspidosperma australe</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>), which have nutritive-like parenchyma cells. Despite being regarded as structurally simple and devoid of nutritive cells (<xref rid="PLV086C49" ref-type="bibr">Meyer 1987</xref>), galls of sucking insects, namely <italic>Euphalerus ostreoides</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>) and <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>), also have cytological and histochemical characteristics of metabolically active cells. These cells are evidenced in the vascular tissues and parenchyma near the nymphal chamber. <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic> galls have gradients of primary and secondary metabolites, discrete accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and are photosynthesis deficient (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). Moreover, the completion of cell cycles through standby-redifferentiation is ensured by the chemical (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>) and cytological ROS-scavenging apparatus (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>).</p><p>Herein, we assess the cytology and histochemistry of the galls induced by <italic>Nothotrioza cattleianum</italic> Burckhardt (Triozidae) (<xref rid="PLV086C15" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) on <italic>Psidium cattleiani</italic> Sabine (Myrtaceae). The structural&#x02013;functional aspects related to cell biology in <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> galls are compared with those of other galls, especially the co-generic system of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>P. myrtoides</italic>. The galls of <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. on <italic>Psidium</italic> spp. are both globoid (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C38" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>) and have similar phenology (<xref rid="PLV086C12" ref-type="bibr">Butignol and Pedrosa-Macedo 2003</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C15" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). We expect that the developmental cytology and histochemical profile of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> galls should reveal conserved traits with regards to the sucking feeding habit of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> and also distinctive ones of a unique extended phenotype (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C3" ref-type="bibr">Bailey <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). The following questions are addressed: (i) Do the cells of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls have conserved cell fates in relation to the non-galled leaves, and in comparison to <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls? (ii) Do the cytological and histochemical profiles of <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. galls indicate unique neo-established tissue functionalities?</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Sampling</title><p>The population of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> Sabine (Myrtaceae) with galls induced by <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> Burckhardt is located at the Parque Estadual Pico do Marumbi, municipality of Piraquara, Paran&#x000e1; state, Brazil. Non-galled leaves (young and mature, <italic>n</italic> = 5 per developmental stage) and galls at the phases of induction, growth and development, maturation, and senescence (<italic>n</italic> = 5 per developmental stage) were collected during the years 2012 and 2013. The samples were fixed in 2.5 % glutaraldehyde (Grade I) and 4.5 % formaldehyde in phosphate buffer (0.1 M; pH 7.2) (<xref rid="PLV086C41" ref-type="bibr">Karnovsky 1965</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Light microscopy</title><p>Fixed samples were dehydrated in ethanol series (<xref rid="PLV086C40" ref-type="bibr">Johansen 1940</xref>), embedded in glycolmethacrylate (Leica<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>), sectioned (6&#x02013;10 &#x000b5;m) with a rotary microtome Hyrax (Zeiss<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>) and stained with 0.05 % toluidine O blue (pH 4.6) (<xref rid="PLV086C55" ref-type="bibr">O'Brien <italic>et al</italic>. 1964</xref>). Histological slides were observed and photographed using a light microscope (Leica<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> DM500) coupled with a digital camera (Leica<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> ICC50 HD).</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Histochemical analysis</title><p>Histochemical tests for primary and secondary plant metabolites, ROS and the activity of enzymes related to carbohydrate metabolism were performed using fresh samples of mature leaves and galls. Control tests were performed according to the references and also by comparison with blank sections. Samples were submitted to the tests/reagents, following the methods described subsequently.</p><sec id="s2c1"><title>Fehling's reagent (reducing sugars)</title><p>Equal parts of &#x02018;A&#x02019; (copper(II) sulfate 6.93 % w : v) and &#x02018;B&#x02019; (sodium potassium tartrate 34.6 and 12 % sodium hydroxide w : w : v) solutions and heat to pre-boiling temperature (<xref rid="PLV086C70" ref-type="bibr">Sass 1951</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c2"><title>Lugol's reagent (starch)</title><p>1 % potassium iodine&#x02013;iodide solution for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C40" ref-type="bibr">Johansen 1940</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c3"><title>Sudan red B (total lipids)</title><p>Saturated solution of Sudan red B in 70 % ethanol for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C9" ref-type="bibr">Brundrett <italic>et al</italic>. 1991</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c4"><title>Coomassie blue (total proteins)</title><p>0.25 % Coomassie blue solution for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C24" ref-type="bibr">Dunn 1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c5"><title>Ferric chloride (phenolics)</title><p>1 % ferric chloride solution for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C40" ref-type="bibr">Johansen 1940</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c6"><title><italic>p</italic>-Dimethylaminocinnamaldehyde (proanthocyanidins)</title><p>Fixation in 0.5 % caffeine sodium benzoate in 90 % butanol for 1&#x02013;2 h. Reaction in 1 % <italic>p</italic>-dimethylaminocinnamaldehyde (DMACA) (<xref rid="PLV086C28" ref-type="bibr">Feucht <italic>et al</italic>. 1986</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c7"><title>Nadi reagent (terpenoids)</title><p>1 % &#x003b1;-Naphtol, 1 % dimethyl-<italic>p</italic>-phenylenediamine in 0.01 M phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) for up to 30 min (<xref rid="PLV086C21" ref-type="bibr">David and Carde 1964</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c8"><title>Wiesner reagent (lignins)</title><p>2 % Phloroglucinol in acidified solution for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C40" ref-type="bibr">Johansen 1940</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c9"><title>DAB reagent (ROS)</title><p>0.5 % 3,3&#x02032;-diaminobenzidine (DAB) for 30 min in the dark (<xref rid="PLV086C69" ref-type="bibr">Rossetti and Bonatti 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c10"><title>Acid phosphatase activity</title><p>Incubation in 0.012 % lead nitrate and 0.1 M potassium sodium glycerophosphate in 0.5 M acetate buffer (pH 4.5) for 24 h, at room temperature. Reaction in 1 % ammonium sulfate for 5 min, after washing in distilled water (<xref rid="PLV086C32" ref-type="bibr">Gomori 1956</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c11"><title>Glucose-6-phosphatase activity</title><p>Incubation in 20 mg of potassium glucose-6-phosphate in 125 mL of 0.2 M Tris&#x02013;maleate buffer (pH 6.7), 3 mL of 2 % lead nitrate in 7 mL of distilled water for 15 min to 2 h, at 37 &#x000b0;C. Reaction in 1 % ammonium sulfate for 5 min, after washing in distilled water (<xref rid="PLV086C39" ref-type="bibr">Jensen 1962</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c12"><title>Phosphorylase activity</title><p>Incubation in 1 % glucose-1-phosphate in 0.1 M acetate buffer (pH 6.0) for 2 h at room temperature. Reaction in Lugol's reagent for 5 min (<xref rid="PLV086C39" ref-type="bibr">Jensen 1962</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c13"><title>Sucrose synthase activity</title><p>Fixation in 2 % paraformaldehyde with 2 % polyvinylpyrrolidone and 0.005 M dithiothreitol for 1 h at 4 &#x000b0;C. Incubation in 5 mL of 150 mM NADH, 5 mL (1 U) of phosphoglucomutase, 5 mL of 3 mM glucose-1,6-biphosphate, 5 mL (1 U) of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase, 5 mL (1 U) of uridine diphosphate glucose&#x02013;pyrophosphorylase, 280 mL of 0.07 % aqueous nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT), 350 mL of buffer and 50 mL of substrate for 30 min. Buffer comprised 100 mM HEPES, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid, 0.2 % bovine serum albumin, 2 mM ethylene glycol tetraacetic acid at pH 7.4. Substrate is composed of 0.75 M sucrose, 15 mM uridine diphosphate and 15 mM pyrophosphate (<xref rid="PLV086C75" ref-type="bibr">Wittich and Vreugdenhil 1998</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2c14"><title>Invertases activity</title><p>Incubation in 0.38 mM sodium phosphate (pH 7.5), 0.024 % NBT, 0.014 % phenazine methosulfate, 30 U of glucose oxidase&#x000a0;and 30 mM of sucrose at room temperature for 3 h (<xref rid="PLV086C23" ref-type="bibr">Doehlert and Felker 1987</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C76" ref-type="bibr">Zrenner <italic>et al</italic>. 1995</xref>).</p><p>Treated sections were mounted on glass slides with Kaiser's glycerol gelatin (<xref rid="PLV086C45" ref-type="bibr">Kraus and Arduin 1997</xref>), observed and photographed with a light microscope (Leica<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> DM500) coupled with a digital camera (Leica<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> ICC50 HD).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Transmission electron microscopy</title><p>The fixed samples were post-fixed in 1 % osmium tetroxide in phosphate buffer (0.1 M; pH 7.2), dehydrated in ethanol series (<xref rid="PLV086C54" ref-type="bibr">O'Brien and McCully 1981</xref>) and embedded in Spurr's<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> resin. Ultrathin sections were obtained with a diamond knife in the Reichert&#x02013;Jung Ultracut ultramicrotome (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany), attached to copper grids, contrasted with uranyl acetate and lead citrate (<xref rid="PLV086C67" ref-type="bibr">Reynolds 1963</xref>). The sections were analysed using a transmission electron microscope Tecnai&#x02122; G2-12&#x02014;SpiritBiotwin (FEI, Hillsboro, USA) at 120 kV, at the Centro de Microscopia of the Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (CM-UFMG).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Morphology and development of leaves and galls</title><p>The galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> are globoid and protruded to the abaxial surface of the leaves of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F1">1</xref>A). The young leaves of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> have uniseriate epidermis, homogenous chlorophyllous parenchyma with interspaced vascular bundles undergoing differentiation. As they mature, epidermis remains uniseriate; hypodermis differentiates under the adaxial surface of the epidermis, and dorsiventral chlorophyllous parenchyma, interspaced with collateral vascular bundles, is observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F1">1</xref>B). The galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> are induced on the young leaves, whose cells redifferentiate to form a depression on the leaf lamina, and ultimately generate a globoid gall with an ample chamber and relatively thin wall. In mature galls, such walls have uniseriate inner and outer epidermis, hyperplasic and hypertrophied homogenous parenchyma and collateral vascular bundles near the nymphal chamber (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F1">1</xref>C). The galls have a 1-year life cycle, with four developmental stages: induction, growth and development, maturation and senescence.
<fig id="PLV086F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>Morphology and anatomy of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> leaves and <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic> galls. (A) The detail of a simple leaf with globoid galls protruded to the abaxial surface. (B) Cross-section of mature leaf with uniseriate epidermis on both surfaces (arrowheads), hypodermis (hy) and vascular bundles (asterisks) interspaced to the dorsiventral chlorophyllous parenchyma (chp). (C) Cross-section of mature gall with uniseriate epidermis on both surfaces (arrowheads) and vascular bundles (asterisks) near the nymphal chamber (nc) interspaced to the homogenous chlorophyllous parenchyma (chp). Bars: (A) 3 cm; (B) 100 &#x000b5;m; (C) 200 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08601"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Cytological development of cell lineages</title><sec id="s3b1"><title>Epidermis</title><p>In the young leaves of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic>, epidermal cells have thin anticlinal walls, fragmented hyaline vacuoles, few chloroplasts and mitochondria, and large central nuclei with conspicuous nucleoli (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F2">2</xref>A; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the mature leaves, the walls are thicker, and the vacuoles have confluenced into a big central vacuole with phenolics; chloroplasts and mitochondria are rare, and the nuclei are small with peripheral heterochromatin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F2">2</xref>B and C). Galls are induced on young leaves, and exhibit epidermal cells with homogenously thin walls, with large hyaline vacuoles. Nuclei are peripheral and the electron-dense cytoplasm is reduced to a fine region near the cell walls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F2">2</xref>D). Epidermal cells in the galls at the stage of growth and development have heterogeneous thick cuticle, with protoplast similar to that of previous stage. At the phase of maturation, the inner epidermis is intermittent; cells exhibit heterogeneously thickened and polylamellate walls and thin cuticle (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F2">2</xref>E; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The protoplast is poorly altered in comparison to the cells of the previous stage. At senescence, the cells have vacuoles with phenolic inclusions and walls with disaggregated lamellae and end up undergoing autolysis.
<table-wrap id="PLV086TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>Structural and ultrastructural traits of the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> and galls induced by <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tissues</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epidermis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniseriate; continuous cell layer; low metabolic apparatus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uniseriate; discontinuous cell layer (inner epidermis); low metabolic apparatus</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyllous parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dorsiventral; cells with well-developed metabolic apparatus; many large plastoglobules</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homogenous; cells with underdeveloped metabolic apparatus; few small plastoglobules; lamellar and multivesicular bodies</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vascular and perivascular parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collateral vascular bundles; cells with developed respiratory and protein synthesis apparatus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collateral vascular bundles; cells with highly developed respiratory and protein synthesis apparatus; lomasomes, lamellar and multivesicular bodies</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="PLV086F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>Cytology of epidermal cells in the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> and galls of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>. (A&#x02013;C) Leaves. (D and E) Galls. (A) Cells with thin anticlinal primary walls (w), large nuclei (n) with conspicuous nucleoli (arrowhead), few chloroplasts (ch) and small vacuoles (v), with phenolic inclusions (ph). (B) The detail of a cell with polylamellate (arrowheads) cell wall (w), thick cuticle (cu) and hyaline vacuole (v). (C) The detail of a cell with homogenous secondary wall (w), small nucleus (n) and hyaline vacuole (v). (D) Induction phase. Cells with homogenous thickened walls (w), peripheral nuclei (n) and hyaline vacuoles (v). Discrete sites of periclinal divisions are observed (asterisk). (E) Maturation phase. Intermittent cell layer, with intercellular spaces (is), heterogeneous thickened and polylamellate walls and inconspicuous cuticle. Vacuoles (v) may contain phenolic inclusions (ph). Bars: (A&#x02013;C) 2 &#x000b5;m; (D and E) 5 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08602"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3b2"><title>Chlorophyllous parenchyma</title><p>In the young leaves, mesophyll cells have thin, homogenous primary cell walls and reduced intercellular spaces. Their vacuoles are large, sometimes fragmented around the nucleus, with electron-dense granular inclusions. Nuclei are large, with electron-dense euchromatin and conspicuous nucleoli (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F3">3</xref>A). Chloroplasts are elliptical, with organized grana, small starch grains and scarce electron-dense plastoglobules. Small round mitochondria are in association with chloroplasts, and rough endoplasmic reticulum (RER) is sometimes observed on the periphery of the cytoplasm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F3">3</xref>B; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In mature leaves, the palisade parenchyma cells have large phenolic-rich vacuoles, many chloroplasts with well-organized thylakoid lamellae and starch grains; nuclei are peripheral, with inconspicuous nucleoli (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F3">3</xref>C). Chloroplasts with large and numerous plastoglobules are frequent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F3">3</xref>D). Spongy parenchyma cells have large hyaline vacuoles, peripheral nuclei with inconspicuous nucleoli and chloroplasts with well-organized thylakoid lamellae, starch grains and rare plastoglobules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F3">3</xref>E and F).
<fig id="PLV086F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3.</label><caption><p>Cytology of chlorophyllous parenchyma cells in leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic>. (A and B) Young leaves. (C&#x02013;F) Mature leaves. (A) Cell with primary thin walls, large central nucleus (n) with conspicuous nucleolus (nu), fragmented vacuole (v) and chloroplasts (ch) with well-developed grana. Intercellular spaces (is) are reduced. (B) The detail of a cell with dense cytoplasm, RER (arrowheads) and mitochondria (mi) associated with chloroplasts with well-developed grana and starch grain (st). (C) Palisade parenchyma cells with homogenous walls (w), phenolic-rich vacuoles (ph), many chloroplasts with well-organized thylakoid lamellae and starch grains (asterisks) and peripheral nuclei (n) with inconspicuous nucleoli. (D) The detail of a chloroplast with low-stack grana (arrowheads) and large plastoglobules (asterisks). (E) Spongy parenchyma cell with homogenous primary wall (w), large vacuole (v), peripheral nucleus (n), chloroplasts (ch) and large intercellular space (is). (F) The detail of a chloroplast with well-developed thylakoid system, high-stack grana (arrowheads), starch grain (st) and associated mitochondria (mi). Bars: (A) 2 &#x000b5;m; (B and D) 500 nm; (C and E) 5 &#x000b5;m; (F) 1 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08603"/></fig></p><p>Galls at induction stage have hypertrophic and hyperplasic cells, with thin primary walls, sometimes fragmented vacuoles, with phenolic inclusions. They have large nuclei with conspicuous nucleoli, small mitochondria associated with chloroplasts with well-organized thylakoid lamellae and few small plastoglobules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>A). Polysomes, Golgi apparatus and multivesicular bodies are sometimes visualized in the periphery of the cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>B and C). At the phase of growth and development, the cells have secondary polylamellated walls, phenolic-rich vacuoles and electron-lucent cytoplasm poor in organelles. Nuclei are small, with little heterochromatin at the periphery; mitochondria are small, associated with chloroplasts with well-organized thylakoid lamellae, starch grains and few small plastoglobules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>D and E). Cells of mature galls are large, with big phenolic or hyaline vacuoles, reduced cytoplasm, sometimes with periplasmic spaces. Cell walls are secondary, either homogeneously thickened and polylamellate or irregularly thickened, sometimes polylamellate, with sites of different electron density (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>F and G). Organelles are scarce; lamellar bodies, degraded nuclei and small chloroplasts with underdeveloped thylakoid lamellae and plastoglobules are observed at the periphery of the cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>G and H). At gall senescence, the outer cortical cells exhibit thickened, polylamellate secondary walls and remain alive, with phenolic-rich vacuoles. Inner cortical cells have signs of degradation, with large periplasmic spaces, disrupted tonoplast and chloroplasts with vestigial thylakoid grana and plastoglobules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F4">4</xref>I and J; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<fig id="PLV086F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4.</label><caption><p>Cytology of chlorophyllous parenchyma cells in the galls of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>. (A&#x02013;C) Induction phase. (D and E) Growth and development phase. (F&#x02013;H) Maturation phase. (I and J) Senescent phase. (A) The detail of a cell with large nuclei (n) with conspicuous nucleoli (nu), small mitochondria (arrowheads) associated with chloroplasts (ch) with well-organized lamellae. (B) Abundant polysomes (arrowheads) and Golgi apparatus (go). (C) Multivesicular body (mvb) at cytoplasm periphery. (D) Cells with secondary polylamellate walls (w), phenolic-rich vacuoles (ph) and small nuclei (n) with inconspicuous nucleoli. (E) Mitochondria (mi) associated to chloroplast (ch) with well-organized thylakoid lamellae (asterisks), starch grains (st) and small plastoglobules (arrowheads). (F) Cells with irregularly thickened walls (w, asterisks), phenolic (ph) or hyaline vacuoles (v). (G) The detail of lamellar body (lb), undeveloped chloroplasts (ch) and cell walls (w) with sites of different electron density (asterisks). (H) Degraded nucleus (n), small mitochondria (arrowheads) and chloroplasts. (I) Degraded chloroplast with vestigial grana (asterisks) and plastoglobules (pg). (J) Cell with large periplasmic spaces (arrowheads), disrupted vacuole (v, asterisk) with phenolic inclusions (ph). Bars: (A, E and H) 1 &#x000b5;m; (B and C) 200 nm; (D and F) 5 &#x000b5;m; (G and J) 2 &#x000b5;m; (I) 500 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08604"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3b3"><title>Vascular and perivascular parenchyma</title><p>In the young leaves, the cells have thin primary walls, sometimes sinuous and with many plasmodesmata; nuclei are large, with inconspicuous nucleoli and dispersed heterochromatin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>A). They have large, sometimes fragmented hyaline vacuoles, dense cytoplasm with rounded mitochondria, small underdeveloped chloroplasts, with few plastoglobules, little RER and lamellar bodies continuous with the plasma membrane (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>B and C; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In mature leaves, cells have thin primary walls; cytoplasm is hyaline, with many mitochondria, scarce RER and large nuclei with dispersed heterochromatin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>D). Phenolic-rich vacuoles and periplasmic spaces are frequent. In the galls at induction phase, cells are thin walled, with electron-dense cytoplasm, large nuclei, abundant polysomes, sometimes evident Golgi apparatus, large mitochondria, abundant plasmodesmata with evident microtubules (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>E and F). Lamellar and multivesicular bodies are frequent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>G). At the phase of growth and development, cells have irregularly thickened walls with sites of different electron density and fragmented hyaline vacuoles. Cytoplasm is electron-lucent and organelle-rich, with abundant mitochondria and polysomes, Golgi apparatus, RER, large nuclei sometimes with conspicuous nucleoli and dispersed heterochromatin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>H). Lomasomes and multivesicular bodies are frequent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>I). Cells of mature galls have thickened and somewhat sinuous secondary walls, large vacuoles either hyaline or phenolic-rich, and abundant mitochondria. Cytoplasm is electron dense, and periplasmic spaces may be observed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>J). At gall senescence, cells are metabolically active, with organelle-rich cytoplasm. They have abundant mitochondria, polysomes and RER; nuclei are large, with peripheral heterochromatin. Lomasomes and lamellar bodies are rarely seen (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F5">5</xref>K; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<fig id="PLV086F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5.</label><caption><p>Cytology of vascular and perivascular parenchyma cells in the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> and galls of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>. (A&#x02013;C) Young leaves. (D) Mature leaves. (E&#x02013;K) Galls. (A) Cells with thin and sinuous walls (arrowheads), large nuclei (n) and hyaline vacuoles (v). Sieve elements (se) may be observed. (B) Cell with dense cytoplasm, many plasmodesmata (pd), round mitochondria (mi) and small underdeveloped chloroplasts (ch) with few small plastoglobules (arrowheads). (C) Lamellar body (lb) near the cell wall (w). (D) Cell with large nucleus (n) with dispersed heterochromatin, mitochondria (arrowhead) and hyaline vacuole (v). Vessel elements (ve) with secondary cell walls (sw) can be observed. (E&#x02013;G) Induction phase. (E) Cells with thin sinuous walls (arrowheads), hyaline vacuoles (v), large mitochondria (mi) and multivesicular bodies (dashed circle). (F) The detail of plasmodesmata (pd) with aligned microtubules (asterisks) and abundant polysomes (arrowheads). (G) The detail of lamellar bodies (lb). (H and J) Growth and development phase. (H) Cells with irregularly thickened walls (w), fragmented hyaline vacuoles (v), large nuclei (n) with conspicuous nucleoli (nu) and abundant mitochondria (mi). (I) The detail of cells with multivesicular bodies (asterisk) and lomasomes (arrowheads). (J) Cells during maturation phase, with thick walls (w), abundant mitochondria (mi) and periplasmic phases (arrowheads). (K) Cell during senescent phase, with abundant rough endoplasmic reticulum (rer), polysomes (arrowheads) and large mitochondria (mi). Bars: (A and H) 5 &#x000b5;m; (B, C, E and G) 1 &#x000b5;m; (D and J) 2 &#x000b5;m; (F, I and K) 500 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08605"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Histochemical profile of leaves and galls</title><sec id="s3c1"><title>Primary metabolites</title><p>In the leaves, reducing sugars and primary starch grains are, respectively, localized by Fehling's and Lugol's reagents throughout the chlorophyllous parenchyma and more rarely in the hypodermis. Reducing sugars are also localized in the phloem of vascular bundles. Lipid droplets and protein precipitates, respectively, stained by Sudan red B and Coomassie blue are observed more intensely in the chlorophyllous parenchyma and vascular bundles, and more scarcely in the epidermal cells and oil glands. The cuticle on both epidermal surfaces and the secretion of oil glands are also stained by Sudan red B. In the galls, reducing sugars are strongly stained by Fehling's reagent, forming a centripetal gradient of sugar accumulation from the outermost cell layers towards the inner cortex (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F6">6</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Primary starch grains are rarely stained, but they may form a discrete centrifugal gradient evidenced by the reaction to Lugol's reagent (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F6">6</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>). Protein precipitates are stained by Coomassie blue in the vascular bundles, perivascular parenchyma and outermost cortical cell layers, forming a bidirectional gradient from the median cortex towards the inner and outer cortices (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F6">6</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>). The cuticle of the outer epidermal cells and the secretion of oil glands were stained by Sudan red B (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F6">6</xref>D; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="PLV086TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>Histochemical traits of the leaves of <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic> and galls induced by <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Detected substances</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Reaction sites<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galls</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reducing sugars</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyllous parenchyma and vascular tissues</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centripetal gradient (weakly in the outermost cell layers and gradually more intense in the cell layers towards the nymphal chamber)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyllous parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centrifugal gradient (weakly in the innermost cell layers and gradually more intense in the cell layers towards the external surface of the gall)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyllous parenchyma, vascular tissues, cuticle and in the oil glands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cuticle of the outer epidermis and oil glands</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyllous parenchyma and vascular tissues</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional gradient (weakly or undetectable in the median cortical cells and gradually more intense in the cell layers towards the internal and external surfaces of the gall)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme activity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid phosphatase; sparsely in the cells of the spongy parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases; in the cells of vascular tissues and perivascular parenchyma</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total phenolics</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentrated in the palisade parenchyma; sparsely in the spongy parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional gradient</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palisade parenchyma and in the oil glands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional gradient</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proanthocyanidins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaxial surface of the epidermis and in the palisade parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional gradient</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lignins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mature xylem and fibres</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centrifugal gradient (in the mature xylem, weakly in the inner/median cortical cells and gradually more intense in the outer cortical cells)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ROS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentrated in the palisade parenchyma and in the phloem and xylem parenchyma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bidirectional gradient</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="PLV086F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6.</label><caption><p>Histochemical detection of primary metabolites and carbohydrate-related enzyme activity in the galls of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>. (A) Reaction of Fehling's reagent to reducing sugars in the chlorophyllous parenchyma (chp), with increased accumulation near the vascular bundles (vb) and tissues near the nymphal chamber (nc). (B) Reaction of Lugol's reagent to starch (arrowheads) in outer cortical cells. (C) Reaction of Coomassie blue to proteins (arrowheads) in a vascular bundle (vb) and perivascular parenchyma. (D) Reaction of Sudan red B to lipids in the oil glands (og) and cuticle (cu) of the outer epidermis. (E and F) Enzyme activity of glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases, respectively, near vascular bundles (vb) and perivascular parenchyma (arrowheads), surrounding the nymphal chamber (nc). Bars: (A) 200 &#x000b5;m; (B) 10 &#x000b5;m; (C) 30 &#x000b5;m; (D&#x02013;F) 60 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08606"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3c2"><title>Enzyme activity</title><p>Leaves have detectable activity of acid phosphatase exclusively in the cells of the spongy parenchyma. Galls have detectable activity of glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases in the vascular bundles and perivascular parenchyma of the median and inner cortices (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F6">6</xref>E&#x000a0;and F and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3c3"><title>Secondary metabolites</title><p>Phenolic substances and terpenoids are, respectively, evidenced by ferric chloride and Nadi solutions intensely in the palisade parenchyma of the leaves and more scarcely in the epidermis, hypodermis, phloem and spongy parenchyma. Terpenoids are also stained in the epithelium of the oil glands. Proanthocyanidins are detected by DMACA more intensely in the adaxial epidermis and palisade parenchyma and more weakly in the spongy parenchyma. Lignins react with Wiesner's reagent in the cell walls of xylem and periciclic fibres. Galls exhibit bidirectional gradients of phenolic substances, terpenoids and proanthocyanidins from the median cortex towards the inner and outer cortices (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F7">7</xref>A&#x02013;D and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>). Lignins are detected in the secondary walls of the outer cortical cells and in the xylem, forming a centrifugal gradient (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F7">7</xref>E and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<fig id="PLV086F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7.</label><caption><p>Histochemical detection of secondary metabolites and ROS in the galls of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic>. (A&#x02013;D) Reaction of ferric chloride solution, Nadi and DMACA to total phenolics (A), terpenoids (B) and proanthocyanidins (C and D), respectively. Most intense reactions are observed in the median and inner cortical cells near the vascular bundles (vb), in the outermost cortical cells and in the epidermal cells near the oil glands (og). (E) Reaction of Wiesner's solution to lignins mainly in the outer cortical cells of the chlorophyllous parenchyma (chp), near the oil glands (og). (F and G) Reaction of DAB to ROS mainly in the median and inner cortical cells, vascular bundles (vb) and outermost cortical cells and oil glands (og). Bars: (A, B, and E) 150 &#x000b5;m; (C, D, F and G) 75 &#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08607"/></fig>
<fig id="PLV086F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;8.</label><caption><p>General patterns of histochemical gradients in the cortex of <italic>Nothotrioza cattleiani</italic> galls on <italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic>. Shading from white to dark means increasing intensity of reaction. (1) Centripetal gradient of reducing sugars from the outermost cortical cells towards the innermost ones. (2, 9) Centrifugal gradients of starch and lignins, respectively, from the median cortical cells towards the outer cells. (3, 6, 7, 8, 10) Bidirectional gradients of proteins, phenolics, proanthocyanidins and ROS, respectively, from the median cortical cells towards both the inner and outer cell layers. (4, 5) Centripetal gradients of glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases activities, from the median cortical cells towards the inner cell layers, especially in the perivascular parenchyma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="plv08608"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s3c4"><title>Reactive oxygen species</title><p>Reactive oxygen species are detected intensely by DAB solution in the chlorophyllous parenchyma of leaves, and also in the phloem and vascular parenchyma. In the galls, ROS are detected weakly in a bidirectional gradient from the median cortex towards the inner and outer cortices. The most intense reactions are observed in the vascular bundles and perivascular parenchyma, and in the epithelium of the oil glands (Figs&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F7">7</xref>F&#x000a0;and G and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLV086F8">8</xref>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="PLV086TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Structural&#x02013;functional implications of cell fates</title><p>Cell redifferentiation (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C46" ref-type="bibr">Lev-Yadun 2003</xref>) is a crucial process by which gall-inducing insects coordinate cell reprogramming of plant organs towards gall morphogenesis. In the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>, this process takes place in the young leaves during the induction phase (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C15" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), similar to <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C16" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>). The induction of galls may occur on young and/or mature plant organs, as observed for the leaf galls induced by <italic>Calophya duvauae</italic> on <italic>Schinus polygamus</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C22" ref-type="bibr">Dias <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>). The selection of different induction sites affects the patterning of cell fates in gall structure, possibly influencing its adaptive value to the gall inducers (<xref rid="PLV086C56" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2009</xref>). Nevertheless, the selective pressures that affect gall morphology seem to be conserved across different gall systems, as convergent types of tissue organization and cell fates, i.e. vascular bundles interspersed with homogenous parenchyma cells, surrounded by sclerenchyma cells, are widely reported in the literature (<xref rid="PLV086C49" ref-type="bibr">Meyer 1987</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C68" ref-type="bibr">Rohfritsch 1992</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C73" ref-type="bibr">Stone and Sch&#x000f6;nrogge 2003</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C56" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2009</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C30" ref-type="bibr">Formiga <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C16" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>).</p><p>Despite structural similarities, most cell lineages in <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls on <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> have developmental dynamics different from those of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls on <italic>P. myrtoides</italic>. Epidermal cells are the exception to this tendency, as they have conserved cytological traits in both systems, namely vacuolated cells that are well organized in the outer surface of the galls but intermittent in the inner surface (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>). Chlorophyllous parenchyma cells in <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. galls have different time-based development. <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic> galls have parenchyma cells that develop by standby-differentiation (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>), in which cell structure remains nearly unaltered for a long period of time, and undergoes major changes from the stage of maturation to senescence. Conversely, the cytology of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls reveals that parenchyma cells gradually and constantly change from induction phase towards senescence. In galls of both <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp., the cell walls thicken and lignify in the outermost layers of the cortex, while the photosynthetic and respiratory apparatus of the cells are impaired. Gall structures are assumed to play defensive roles against natural enemies of the galling insects (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C73" ref-type="bibr">Stone and Sch&#x000f6;nrogge 2003</xref>). The changes of cell fate in the chlorophyllous parenchyma, which have thickened and lignified walls in the galls on <italic>Psidium</italic> spp., suggest the investment in a structure-based defence strategy that should increase the adaptive values of the galls to the <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp.</p><p>Contrary to the new cell fates of chlorophyllous parenchyma cells in <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls, vascular and perivascular parenchyma undergo less structural alteration. The fates of these cells are not altered from non-galled leaves to galls, and they maintain a well-developed metabolic apparatus, namely large nuclei, and dense cytoplasm with abundant polysomes and mitochondria, throughout gall development in both <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>) and <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls. The maintenance of structural&#x02013;functional characteristics of vascular tissues indicates that their primordial role in plants, i.e. conducting water and solutes (<xref rid="PLV086C13" ref-type="bibr">Buvat 1989</xref>), is maintained in galls. Such a strategy is adaptive (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C73" ref-type="bibr">Stone and Sch&#x000f6;nrogge 2003</xref>) for the gall inducers as far as their nutrition is concerned, since <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. are sap feeders (<xref rid="PLV086C10" ref-type="bibr">Burckhardt 2005</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C15" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), and thus dependent on the intake of water and solutes by vascular tissues. Altogether, the cellular characteristics of epidermis, chlorophyllous parenchyma and vascular and perivascular parenchyma corroborate the adaptive nature of the gall structure (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="PLV086C73" ref-type="bibr">Stone and Sch&#x000f6;nrogge 2003</xref>), as they directly relate to the maintenance of an adequate microenvironment, protection against natural enemies and enhancement of nutritional options for the gall inducers, as classically hypothesized by <xref rid="PLV086C62" ref-type="bibr">Price <italic>et al</italic>. (1987)</xref> for galls in general.</p><p>In relation to the non-galled leaves, cell fates are completely altered in galls, except for the outer epidermis, whose cell cycles are intensified, but the fates are maintained. In relation to <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls, cell fates are roughly the same, but the standby-redifferentiation observed in the chlorophyllous parenchyma cells during the stage of growth and development (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>) does not occur in <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Roles of cell metabolism in gall biology</title><p>The functional aspects of plant tissues in the context of gall structure have been related to the accumulation of defensive and nutritive metabolites (<xref rid="PLV086C35" ref-type="bibr">Hartley 1998</xref>) and to the establishment of histochemical and cytological gradients in Cynipid (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>), Cecidomyiidae (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C60" ref-type="bibr">2011<italic>a</italic></xref>) and Pseudophacopteronidae (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>) galls. In the galls of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic>, such gradients are not observed in gall cortices due to their low structural complexity and metabolism (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>). The galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> also lack cytological gradients, as the parenchyma cells are metabolically impaired, with low protein synthesis, scarce and underdeveloped mitochondria and chloroplasts. Nevertheless, the vascular and perivascular parenchyma cells appear increasingly metabolic during gall morphogenesis, i.e. large nuclei, abundant RER, mitochondria, ribosomes and polysomes. Such cell types have also been observed in the vascular and perivascular tissues in galls of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>) and share great similarities with the nutritive cells of cynipid (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>) and cecidomyiid galls (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C61" ref-type="bibr">2011<italic>b</italic></xref>).</p><p>Nutritive tissues have the most specialized cell types within gall structure, and they are constantly affected by the gall inducers during their feeding (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>). Both the impact of the feeding activity of the galling insects and the high metabolism intrinsic to these cell types often lead to the accumulation of ROS. In fact, ROS were histochemically localized in the nutritive tissues of galls induced by Cecidomyiidae on <italic>Aspidosperma spruceanum</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and on <italic>Copaifera langsdorffii</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C60" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>). Furthermore, ROS have been localized in the nutritive-like ground parenchyma around the nymphal chamber in the galls of Pseudophacopteronidae on <italic>A. australe</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>) and in the vascular bundles of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C16" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>a</italic></xref>) and <italic>E. ostreoides</italic> galls (<xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Vascular and perivascular parenchyma cells are metabolically active in the galls on <italic>P. myrtoides</italic>, with well-developed ROS-scavenging apparatus, i.e. lomasomes, lamellar and multivesicular bodies (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>). Such structures were previously described in the nutritive cells of galls induced by Thysanoptera (<xref rid="PLV086C63" ref-type="bibr">Raman and Ananthakrishnan 1983</xref>), in the fast-dividing nutritive cells of lepidoptera galls on <italic>Marcetia taxifolia</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C27" ref-type="bibr">Ferreira <italic>et al</italic>. 2015</xref>), and also herein for the galls on <italic>P. cattleianum</italic>. Lomasomes, lamellar and multivesicular bodies act together with the endoplasmic reticulum to recycle membrane systems (<xref rid="PLV086C72" ref-type="bibr">Staehelin 1997</xref>) to ensure the functionality of cells subjected to high oxidative stress.</p><p>In addition to the ROS-scavenging apparatus, high protein synthesis seems to be characteristic of nutrition-related tissues in galls, i.e. true nutritive tissues in galls of cynipids (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>), cecidomyiids (<xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C60" ref-type="bibr">2011<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C26" ref-type="bibr">Ferreira and Isaias 2014</xref>) and lepidoptera (<xref rid="PLV086C74" ref-type="bibr">Vecchi <italic>et al</italic>. 2013</xref>), and of nutritive-like parenchyma cells around the nymphal chamber of Psylloidea galls (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). In fact, the histochemical detection of proteins in the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> corroborates such premise and reveals another similarity among vascular and perivascular parenchyma cells in the galls of <italic>P. myrtoides</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>) and <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> and those of true nutritive tissues. The well-developed ROS-scavenging apparatus and high protein synthesis seem to be a widespread trait of nutrition-related cells across different galls. More than simply feeding on the vascular bundle cells, <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> induces the redifferentiation of true nutritive cells in and around the vascular system, which is herein reported for the first time in insect galls.</p><p>Other cell types, such as those of the chlorophyllous parenchyma, may also be subjected to high oxidative stress due to photosynthesis and respiration, which are ROS-generating processes (<xref rid="PLV086C50" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000f8;ller <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). Chloroplasts subjected to high oxidative stress may develop plastoglobules, which help to minimize oxidative damage to the photosynthetic apparatus (<xref rid="PLV086C2" ref-type="bibr">Asada 2006</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C50" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000f8;ller <italic>et al</italic>. 2007</xref>). In fact, the chlorophyllous parenchyma cells of non-galled leaves of <italic>P. myrtoides</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>), and of <italic>P. cattelainum</italic> accumulate ROS, and have conspicuous and numerous plastoglobules. Also, they have low-stack grana with electron-lucent thylakoids, which is characteristic of sun-type chloroplasts previously described by <xref rid="PLV086C47" ref-type="bibr">Lichtenthaler <italic>et al</italic>. (1981)</xref>, which photosynthesize at high levels. Galls that accumulate high amounts of ROS, such as the ones induced by the sucking insect <italic>Pseudophacopteron</italic> sp. on <italic>A. australe</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C61" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>), have plastoglobules in the chloroplasts. In this system, the stress imposed by the galling herbivore stimulates the differentiation of plastoglobules, which are not observed in non-galled leaves, and both galls and leaves photosynthesize at the same levels (<xref rid="PLV086C61" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). In the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>, the differentiation of plastoglobules is blocked, similar to the galls of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>), which are photosynthesis deficient (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). In both <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. galls, the chloroplasts have less lamellation throughout gall development and high-stack grana with electron-dense thylakoids, as described for shade-type leaves (<xref rid="PLV086C47" ref-type="bibr">Lichtenthaler <italic>et al</italic>. 1981</xref>), which photosynthesize at low levels. The cytological features of chloroplasts in the chlorophyllous parenchyma of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls indicate low cellular metabolism and corroborate the hypothesis that these galls may be photosynthesis-deficient, such as the ones of the co-generic system, <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C14" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro and Isaias 2014</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>).</p><p>Despite the low metabolism of chlorophyllous parenchyma cells in the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>, secondary and primary metabolites are histochemically localized in the cortex of mature galls, forming gradients somewhat similar to those reported for <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). In both <italic>Nothotrioza</italic> spp. galls, the scarcity of lipid droplets and essential oils is attributed to the characteristics of the host plants, <italic>P. myrtoides</italic> and <italic>P. cattleianum</italic>. These compounds are common in Myrtaceae (<xref rid="PLV086C65" ref-type="bibr">Ramos <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and represent a metabolic trait that is not changed due to gall formation, as observed for galls of <italic>Aceria lantanae</italic> on <italic>Lantana camara</italic> (Verbenaceae) (<xref rid="PLV086C51" ref-type="bibr">Moura <italic>et al</italic>. 2008</xref>). The centripetal gradients of reducing sugars, on the other hand, evidence the manipulation of plant cell metabolism in galls, which conspicuously accumulate sugars. Sugars are not synthesized at gall sites, but they are drained from non-galled organs (<xref rid="PLV086C11" ref-type="bibr">Burstein <italic>et al</italic>. 1994</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C64" ref-type="bibr">Raman <italic>et al</italic>. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C19" ref-type="bibr">Castro <italic>et al</italic>. 2012<italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref rid="PLV086C20" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Herein, this premise is confirmed for the galls of <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>, which have detectable activity of glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases in the vascular bundles and surrounding tissues, next to the larval chamber. These sites of enzyme activity are similar to those described in the galls on <italic>A. australe</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C58" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira and Isaias 2010<italic>b</italic></xref>), <italic>A. spruceanum</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C59" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>) and <italic>Lonchocarpus muehlbergianus</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>). Glucose-6-phosphatase is involved in the formation of sucrose after starch breakdown (<xref rid="PLV086C4" ref-type="bibr">Baroja-Fern&#x000e1;ndez <italic>et al</italic>. 2003</xref>) and invertases catalyse the irreversible conversion of sucrose into glucose and fructose (<xref rid="PLV086C42" ref-type="bibr">Koch 2004</xref>). The centrifugal histochemical gradient of starch in the galls of <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> indicates that starch is converted into soluble sugars in the cells surrounding the larval chamber, where enzyme activity is detected. A similar gradient of starch and related enzyme activity is described for the galls on <italic>L. muehlbergianus</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C37" ref-type="bibr">Isaias <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>), which reinforces the enzyme-mediated mobilization of starch, as a pattern for inner cortical cells of galls. The activities of enzymes related to carbohydrate metabolism determine the establishment of physiological sinks in plants (<xref rid="PLV086C43" ref-type="bibr">Koch 1996</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C44" ref-type="bibr">Koch and Zeng 2002</xref>) and are involved in tissue development and cell expansion (<xref rid="PLV086C66" ref-type="bibr">Rehill and Schultz 2003</xref>), crucial for gall development. In fact, the galls on <italic>Psidium</italic> spp. act as physiological sinks, but diverge in terms of the detectable carbohydrate-related enzymes. The activity of acid phosphatase is exclusive of <italic>P. myrtoidis</italic> galls (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>), while the activity of glucose-6-phosphatase and invertases is detected only in <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> galls.</p><p>Besides accumulating carbohydrates, the galls on <italic>P. cattleianum</italic> also have gradients of total phenolics and proanthocyanidins, similar to the galls on <italic>P. myrtoides</italic> (<xref rid="PLV086C17" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic>et al</italic>. 2014<italic>b</italic></xref>). The localization of such compounds in gall tissues is considered a defensive chemical strategy of gall inducers against natural enemies (<xref rid="PLV086C8" ref-type="bibr">Bronner 1992</xref>) for their unpalatability. In both galls, phenolic compounds are believed to control cell expansion and division by the modulation of indol-acetic acid (IAA) levels (<xref rid="PLV086C36" ref-type="bibr">Hori 1992</xref>). In fact, recent studies localized phenolics and IAA at the same sites in <italic>Piptadenia gonoacantha</italic> galls (<xref rid="PLV086C6" ref-type="bibr">Bedetti <italic>et al</italic>. 2014</xref>), thus confirming the developmental role of phenolics in galls. Also, phenolics mediate the morphogenesis of vascular tissues (<xref rid="PLV086C1" ref-type="bibr">Aloni 2001</xref>) and should be involved in the neoformation of vascular bundles near the nymphal chamber. Neoformed vascular bundles contribute to the establishment of the gall as a sink of photoassimilates and to the nutrition of the gall inducer, which contradicts the classical role of phenolics as plant-defensive compounds in galls, as widely attributed in literature (<xref rid="PLV086C35" ref-type="bibr">Hartley 1998</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C53" ref-type="bibr">Nyman and Julkunen-Tiitto 2000</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C29" ref-type="bibr">Formiga <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>). Another group of phenolic substances, the proanthocyanidins, accumulates both in the outermost and innermost cell layers of the <italic>Psidium</italic> spp. galls, with decreasing gradients towards the median cortex. Such substances act as antioxidants (<xref rid="PLV086C71" ref-type="bibr">Simmonds 2003</xref>; <xref rid="PLV086C7" ref-type="bibr">Bouaziz <italic>et al</italic>. 2005</xref>), and their distribution along the gradient of ROS concentration possibly prevents oxidative stress in gall tissues, keeping cell alterations to a minimum.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The similar phenotypes of the globoid galls of the double co-generic systems, <italic>N. cattleiani</italic>&#x02013;<italic>P. cattleianum</italic> and <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>P. myrtoides</italic>, are not extended to the cytological and histochemical levels. Nevertheless, the lack of cytological gradients and the formation of somewhat conserved histochemical profiles are common to both galls, with the centripetal accumulation of sugars and centrifugal detection of lignins, as conserved traits possibly linked to the taxonomical proximity of the involved species.</p><p>The bidirectional gradients of metabolite accumulation described for <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls, together with the redifferentiation of true nutritive cells associated with vascular bundles, are unique features. Also, cytological development in <italic>N. cattleiani</italic> galls is gradual from induction towards senescence, and different from the standby-redifferentiation of <italic>N. myrtoidis</italic> galls, which reinforce the species-specific subcellular aspects of these distinctive extended phenotypes.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Sources of Funding</title><p>Our work was funded by the <funding-source>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (Brazil)</funding-source> (grant number <award-id>307007/2012-2</award-id>), the <funding-source>Empresa Brasileira de Pesquisa Agropecu&#x000e1;ria</funding-source> (Project: <funding-source>&#x02018;Manejo e biodiversidade de Psylloidea associados ao sistema integra&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o lavoura&#x02014;pecu&#x000e1;ria&#x02014;floresta e &#x000e0; citricultura no Brasil&#x02019;</funding-source>, number <award-id>02.12.01.028.00.00</award-id>), <funding-source>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de Minas Gerais (Brazil)</funding-source> and <funding-source>Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (Brazil)</funding-source>.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Contributions by the Authors</title><p>Both authors substantially contributed to the preparation of manuscript and the research presented; they have seen and agreed to submit the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Paschoal C. Grossi, Rodolfo S. Bertoli, Sandra M. A. Gomes and the staff from Centro de Educa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Ambiental Mananciais da Serra (CEAM &#x02013; SANEPAR) for the logistical and technical support during field works,&#x000a0;and the Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Bot&#x000e2;nica Estrutural of the Universidade Federal do Paran&#x000e1; for laboratory support in Curitiba, Paran&#x000e1;, Brazil. We also thank John Runions and Simcha Lev-Yadun for useful comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="PLV086C1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aloni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Foliar and axial aspects of vascular differentiation: hypotheses and evidence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Growth Regulation</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s003440010001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Production and scavenging of reactive oxygen species in chloroplasts and their functions</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.082040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16760493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melika</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cs&#x000f3;ka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thur&#x000f3;czy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Host niches and defensive extended phenotypes structure parasitoid wasp communities</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biology</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1000179</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19707266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baroja-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saikusa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pozueta-Romero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Sucrose synthase catalyzes the de novo production of ADPglucose linked to starch biosynthesis in heterotrophic tissues of plants</article-title>. <source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
<volume>44</volume>:<fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12773636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedetti</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The influence of parasitoidism on the anatomical and histochemical profiles of the host leaves in a galling Lepidoptera&#x02013;<italic>Bauhinia ungulata</italic> system</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Bioci&#x000ea;ncias</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>249</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedetti</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modolo</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The role of phenolics in the control of auxin in galls of <italic>Piptadenia gonoacantha</italic> (Mart.) MacBr (Fabaceae: Mimosoideae)</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Systematics and Ecology</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bse.2014.02.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouaziz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grayer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>MSJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Damak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sayadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Identification and antioxidant potential of flavonoids and low molecular weight phenols in olive cultivar Chemlali growing in Tunisia</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>
<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf048859d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15656655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C8"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>The role of nutritive cells in the nutrition of cynipids and cecidomyiids</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorthouse</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Biology of insect-induced galls</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brundrett</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Efficient lipid staining in plant material with Sudan Red 7B or fluoral yellow 088 in polyethylene glycol-glycerol</article-title>. <source>Biotechnic and Histochemistry</source>
<volume>66</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10520299109110562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1716161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burckhardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Biology, ecology and evolution of gall-inducing psyllids (Hemiptera: Psylloidea)</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Biology, ecology, and evolution of gall-inducing arthropods</source>. <publisher-loc>Enfield</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Science Publishers</publisher-name>, <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wool</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eshel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Sink strength and clone-size of sympatric, gall-forming aphids</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Entomology</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butignol</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedrosa-Macedo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Biologia de <italic>Neotrioza tavaresi</italic> Crawford, 1925 (Hemiptera, Psyllidae), galhador da folha do ara&#x000e7;azeiro (<italic>Psidium cattleianum</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Entomologia</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0085-56262003000100001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buvat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<source>Ontogeny, cell differentiation and structure of vascular plants</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Cytological cycles and fates in <italic>Psidium myrtoides</italic> are altered towards new cell metabolism and functionalities by the galling activity of <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic></article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>252</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>646</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25272990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burckhardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Biology and systematics of gall-inducing triozids (Hemiptera: Psylloidea) associated with <italic>Psidium</italic> spp. (Myrtaceae)</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa</source>
<volume>3620</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26120700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014a</year>
<article-title>Developmental anatomy and immunocytochemistry reveal the neo-ontogenesis of the leaf tissues of <italic>Psidium myrtoides</italic> (Myrtaceae) towards the globoid galls of <italic>Nothotrioza myrtoidis</italic> (Triozidae)</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2093</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-014-1683-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25228569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014b</year>
<article-title>Unique histochemical gradients in a photosynthesis-deficient plant gall</article-title>. <source>South African Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2014.02.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>ACR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>GLD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012a</year>
<article-title>Morphological patterns of a hymenopteran gall on the leaflets of <italic>Caryocar brasiliense</italic> Camb. (Caryocaraceae)</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Plant Sciences</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>929</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/ajps.2012.37109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>ASFP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemos-Filho</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012b</year>
<article-title>Source-sink relationship and photosynthesis in the horn-shaped gall and its host plant <italic>Copaifera langsdorffii</italic> Desf. (Fabaceae)</article-title>. <source>South African Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2012.08.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>ASFP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Synchronism between <italic>Aspidosperma macrocarpon</italic> Mart. (Apocynaceae) resources allocation and the establishment of gall inducer <italic>Pseudophacopteron</italic> sp. (Hemiptera: Psylloidea)</article-title>. <source>Revista de Biolog&#x000ed;a Tropical</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1891</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15517/rbt.v61i4.12859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24432541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carde</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1964</year>
<article-title>Coloration deff&#x000e9;rentielle des inclusions lipidiques et terpeniques des pseudophylles du Pin maritime au moyen du r&#x000e9;actif NADI</article-title>. <source>Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des S&#x000e9;ances de l'Acad&#x000e9;mic des Sciences</source>
<volume>258</volume>:<fpage>1338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1340</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>GRP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Developmental pathway from leaves to galls induced by a sap-feeding insect on <italic>Schinus polygamus</italic> (Cav.) Cabrera (Anacardiaceae)</article-title>. <source>Anais da Academia Brasileira de Ci&#x000ea;ncias</source>
<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0001-37652013000100010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doehlert</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Felker</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Characterization and distribution of invertase activity in developing maize (<italic>Zea mays</italic>) kernels</article-title>. <source>Physiologia Plantarum</source>
<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1987.tb08695.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<source>Gel electrophoresis: proteins</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bios Scientific Publishers</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Developmental stem anatomy and tissue redifferentiation induced by a galling Lepidoptera on <italic>Marcetia taxifolia</italic> (Melastomataceae)</article-title>. <source>Botany</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>760</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/cjb-2013-0125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Floral-like destiny induced by a galling Cecidomyiidae on the axillary buds of <italic>Marcetia taxifolia</italic> (Melastomataceae)</article-title>. <source>Flora &#x02013; Morphology, Distribution, Functional Ecology of Plants</source>
<volume>209</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.flora.2014.06.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Multivesicular bodies differentiate exclusively in nutritive fast-dividing cells in <italic>Marcetia taxifolia</italic> galls</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-015-0759-8</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feucht</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>PPS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Distribution of flavanols in meristematic and mature tissues of <italic>Prunus avium</italic> shoots</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>125</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0176-1617(86)80237-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Formiga</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>SJMR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>GLG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Rela&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es entre o teor de fen&#x000f3;is totais e o ciclo das galhas de Cecidomyiidae em <italic>Aspidosperma spruceanum</italic> M&#x000fc;ll. Arg. (Apocynaceae)</article-title>. <source>Acta Botanica Brasilica</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-33062009000100012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Formiga</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>GLG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Responses of the host plant tissues to gall induction in <italic>Aspidosperma spruceanum</italic> M&#x000fc;ell. Arg. (Apocynaceae)</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Plant Sciences</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>834</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/ajps.2011.26097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gianoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Studying phenotypic plasticity: the advantages of a broad approach</article-title>. <source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source>
<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.2011.01793.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>
<article-title>Histochemical methods for acid phosphatase</article-title>. <source>Journal of Histochemistry and Cytochemistry</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/4.5.453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13367386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>ALA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bizarri</surname><given-names>CHB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>ACM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Characterisation of the effects of leaf galls of <italic>Clusiamyia nitida</italic> (Cecidomyiidae) on <italic>Clusia lanceolata</italic> Cambess. (Clusiaceae): anatomical aspects and chemical analysis of essential oil</article-title>. <source>Flora &#x02013; Morphology, Distribution, Functional Ecology of Plants</source>
<volume>208</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.flora.2013.03.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>ALA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>SMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>ACM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Structure of floral galls of <italic>Byrsonima sericea</italic> (Malpighiaceae) induced by <italic>Bruggmanniella byrsonimae</italic> (Cecidomyiidae, Diptera) and their effects on host plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Biology</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/plb.12060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23890089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The chemical composition of plant galls: are levels of nutrients and secondary compounds controlled by the gall-former?</article-title>
<source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>113</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28308028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C36"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Insect secretion and their effect on plant growth, with special reference to hemipterans</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorthouse</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohfristsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Biology of insect-induced galls</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Role of <italic>Euphalerus ostreoides</italic> (Hemiptera: Psylloidea) in manipulating leaflet ontogenesis of <italic>Lonchocarpus muehlbergianus</italic> (Fabaceae)</article-title>. <source>Botany</source>
<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b11-048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Illustrated and annotated checklist of Brazilian gall morphotypes</article-title>. <source>Neotropical Entomology</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13744-013-0115-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23949804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C39"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1962</year>
<source>Botanical histochemistry</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.H. Freeman and Company</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1940</year>
<source>Plant microtechnique</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Book Company Inc</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karnovsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1965</year>
<article-title>A formaldehyde&#x02013;glutaraldehyde fixative of high osmolarity for use in electron microscopy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cell Biology</source>
<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Sucrose metabolism: regulatory mechanisms and pivotal roles in sugar sensing and plant development</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>246</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2004.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15134743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Carbohydrate-modulated gene expression in plants</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>540</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.47.1.509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Molecular approaches to altered C partitioning: gene for sucrose metabolism</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Society of Horticultural Sciences</source>
<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>474</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C45"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arduin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<source>Manual b&#x000e1;sico de m&#x000e9;todos em morfologia vegetal</source>. <publisher-loc>Serop&#x000e9;dica</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Editora da Universidade Federal Rural do Rio de Janeiro</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lev-Yadun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Stem cells in plants are differentiated too</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D&#x000f6;ll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fietz</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahmsdorf</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Photosynthetic activity, chloroplast ultrastructure, and leaf characteristics of high-light and low-light plants and of sun and shade leaves</article-title>. <source>Photosynthesis Research</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00028752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24470202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C48"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1964</year>
<source>Ecology of plant galls</source>. <publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Dr. W. Junk Publishers</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C49"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<source>Plant galls and gall inducers</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gebr&#x000fc;der Borntraeger</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Oxidative modifications to cellular components in plants</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>
<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>481</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>MZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>GLG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Species-specific changes in tissue morphogenesis induced by two arthropod leaf gallers in <italic>Lantana camara</italic> L. (Verbenaceae)</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/BT07131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>MZD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>GLG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Ontog&#x000ea;nese da folha e das galhas induzidas por <italic>Aceria lantanae</italic> Cook (Acarina: Eriophyidae) em folhas de <italic>Lantana camara</italic> L. (Verbenaceae)</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Bot&#x000e2;nica</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Julkunen-Tiitto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Manipulation of the phenolic chemistry of willows by gall-inducing sawflies</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>13184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13187</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.230294097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11078506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C54"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCully</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<source>The study of plant structure principles and selected methods</source>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Termarcarphi Pty Ltd</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCully</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1964</year>
<article-title>Polychromatic staining of plant cell walls by toluidine blue O</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01248568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Influence of leaflet age in anatomy and possible adaptive values of the midrib gall of <italic>Copaifera langsdorffii</italic> (Fabaceae: Caesalpinioideae)</article-title>. <source>Revista de Biolog&#x000ed;a Tropical</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19637708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010a</year>
<article-title>Redifferentiation of leaflet tissues during midrib gall development in <italic>Copaifera langsdorffii</italic> (Fabaceae)</article-title>. <source>South African Journal of Botany</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2009.10.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010b</year>
<article-title>Cytological and histochemical gradients induced by a sucking insect in galls of <italic>Aspidosperma australe</italic> Arg. Muell (Apocynaceae)</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source>
<volume>178</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2010.02.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvim</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Do Cecidomyiidae galls of <italic>Aspidosperma spruceanum</italic> (Apocynaceae) fit the pre-established cytological and histochemical patterns?</article-title>
<source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>242</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-010-0128-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20306094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>ASFP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Lemos-Fillho</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011a</year>
<article-title>Is the oxidative stress caused by <italic>Aspidosperma</italic> spp. galls capable of altering leaf photosynthesis?</article-title>
<source>Plant Science</source>
<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2010.11.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>RGS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011b</year>
<article-title>Cytological and histochemical gradients on two <italic>Copaifera langsdorffii</italic> Desf. (Fabaceae)&#x02013;Cecidomyiidae gall systems</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>248</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>837</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-010-0258-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21207084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waring</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Adaptive nature of insect gall</article-title>. <source>Environmental Entomology</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ee/16.1.15</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthakrishnan</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Studies on some Thrips (Thysanoptera: Insecta) induced galls. 2. Fine-structure of the nutritive zone</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the Indian Natural Sciences Academy</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Florentine</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dhileepan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Metabolite mobilization in the stem galls of <italic>Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> induced by <italic>Epiblema strenuana</italic> inferred from the signatures of isotopic carbon and nitrogen and concentrations of total non-structural carbohydrates</article-title>. <source>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</source>
<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.2006.00403.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siani</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Essential oils from myrtaceae species of the Brazilian Southeastern maritime forest (Restinga)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Essential Oil Research</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10412905.2010.9700275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehill</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Enhanced invertase activities in the galls of <italic>Hormaphis hamamelidis</italic></article-title>. <source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source>
<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2703</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2720</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:JOEC.0000008014.12309.04</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14969357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1963</year>
<article-title>The use of lead citrate at high pH as an electron-opaque stain in electron microscopy</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Cell Biology</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.17.1.208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13986422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C68"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Patterns in gall development</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shorthouse</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rohfritsch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Biology of insect-induced galls</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossetti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonatti</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>In situ histochemical monitoring of ozone- and TMV-induced reactive oxygen species in tobacco leaves</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0981-9428(01)01250-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C70"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1951</year>
<source>Botanical microtechnique</source>. <edition>2&#x000aa; edn</edition>
<publisher-loc>Ames</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Iowa State College Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simmonds</surname><given-names>MSJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Flavonoid&#x02013;insect interactions: recent advances in our knowledge</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(03)00293-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12946403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staehelin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The plant ER: a dynamic organelle composed of a large number of discrete functional domains</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1165</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1997.11061151.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9225461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The adaptive significance of insect gall morphology</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00247-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vecchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>RMS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The redifferentiation of nutritive cells in galls induced by Lepidoptera on <italic>Tibouchina pulchra</italic> (Cham.) Cogn. reveals predefined patterns of plant development</article-title>. <source>Protoplasma</source>
<volume>250</volume>:<fpage>1363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1368</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00709-013-0519-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23779213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittich</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Localization of sucrose synthase activity in developing maize kernels by in situ enzyme histochemistry</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1171</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/49.324.1163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PLV086C76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zrenner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salanoubat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnewald</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Evidence of the crucial role of sucrose synthase for sink strength using transgenic potato plants (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1995.07010097.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7894514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>