<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Trichology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Trichology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Trichology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0974-7753</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0974-9241</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Medknow Publications &#x00026; Media Pvt Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6385512</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJT-11-31</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijt.ijt_16_18</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Trigeminal Trophic Syndrome Simulating Pityriasis Amiantacea</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bandeira</surname><given-names>Luisa Groba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luce</surname><given-names>Maria Cl&#x000e1;udia Alves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>Bruno De Castro E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kakizaki</surname><given-names>Priscila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>Neusa Yuriko Sakai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Dermatology, Hospital of the State Public Servant of S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Luisa Groba Bandeira, Department of Dermatology, Hospital of the State Public Servant of S&#x000e3;o Paulo. Rua Borges Lagoa 1755. Vila Clementino 04038-034, S&#x000e3;o Paulo &#x02013; SP, Brazil. E-mail: <email xlink:href="luisagroba@gmail.com">luisagroba@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Feb</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 International Journal of Trichology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We report a case of trigeminal trophic syndrome (TTS) on the scalp of a 69-year-old woman. Initially, the diagnosis of pityriasis amiantacea was considered. The review of pathological antecedents and knowledge of TTS were fundamental for the diagnosis of this illness. We performed a brief review on TTS and differential diagnoses.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Herpes zoster</kwd><kwd>pityriasis amiantacea</kwd><kwd>trigeminal nerve</kwd><kwd>trigeminal trophic syndrome</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Trigeminal trophic syndrome (TTS) was first described in 1901 by Adolf Wallenberg.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] He also described Wallenberg's medullary lateral syndrome by occlusion of the inferior posterior cerebellar artery, one of the causes of TTS.[<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</p><p>It is a rare condition resulting from manipulation of the skin after peripheral or central injury of the trigeminal nerve. In the classic clinical picture, there is trigeminal anesthesia, facial paresthesia, and unilateral ulcerations on the face.[<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] It is a differential diagnosis of unilateral ulcerations, such as carcinoma, syphilis, and deep mycoses, among others.</p><p>Among the main causes of TTS are iatrogenic in the treatments of trigeminal neuralgia; Wallenberg's lateral medullary syndrome; infectious diseases such as shingles, tertiary syphilis, leprosy, and leishmaniasis; traumas; craniotomy; tumors; and systemic diseases, such as Wegener's granulomatosis.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p><p>The trigeminal nerve is a mixed, sensory, and motor nerve. Its name comes from its three divisions: ophthalmic (V1), maxillary (V2), and mandibular (V3). V1 is responsible for the sensitivity of the forehead to the apex of the scalp, upper eyelid, eyes, anterior region of the nose, and upper nasal cavity. V2 and V3 innervate the middle and lower regions of the face.[<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</p><p>In TTS, V2 is the most commonly affected branch. In this way, the classic clinical picture is of a small crust in the nasal wing, which can evolve with increasing ulceration and extend to the malar region and upper lip. The nasal tip is usually spared, as it is innervated by the ethmoidal branch of V1.[<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</p><p>Pityriasis amytaceae is known as a clinical syndrome that affects the scalp. It is presented with shiny, silvery scales similar to mica, which adhere to each other and surround tufts of hair. Among the possible etiologies are seborrheic dermatitis as the most frequent, followed by psoriasis and local infections.[<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases" id="sec1-2"><title>CASE REPORT</title><p>A 69-year-old female patient presented to the dermatology clinic for a scalp injury she had for a year. She reported intense pruritus on the spot and sore pangs. On physical examination, there were yellowish, coarse crusts attached to the apex of the scalp associated with fine, diffuse scaling on the scalp [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>] and seborrheic areas on the face. The main diagnostic hypothesis was pityriasis amiantacea, and we started treatment for seborrheic dermatitis with ketoconazole shampoo, antibiotics associated with topical corticosteroids, and mineral oil to remove the crusts.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Yellow, greasy, coarse, clinging crusts at the apex of the scalp on physical examination</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJT-11-31-g001"/></fig><p>The patient returned in several consultations, for a year, without improvement of the lesion and with the appearance of a new plate surmounted by a crust next to the old one [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>]. During the consultation, the crust was removed with mineral oil, exposing a clean, erythematous ulcer, with bloody discharge [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>], that was intensely painful. The patient revealed that she had herpes zoster on her scalp 2 years before, at the same site, during treatment with chemotherapy for Hodgkin's lymphoma.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A new lesion arised near the first one</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJT-11-31-g002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The crust was removed with mineral oil, exposing a clean erythematous ulcer with bloody discharge</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="IJT-11-31-g003"/></fig><p>Based on the location and history of herpes zoster, a diagnosis of TTS with V1 involvement was made. She was instructed not to manipulate the lesion, although the patient denied this fact, and we introduced gabapentin 600 mg/day.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Although TTS characteristically affects the ipsilateral nasal wing, the malar region, and the upper lip, which corresponds to the dermatomes V2 and V3, it can affect any territory of V3, with formation of lesions on the scalp. TTS after herpes zoster on the scalp is uncommon.</p><p>The reported case resulted in a differential diagnosis of lesions on the scalp, such as pityriasis amiantacea, which, however, do not evolve with ulceration. Removal of the crust, review of the patient's pathological history, and knowledge of TTS were essential for the final diagnosis of the case.</p><p>A retrospective study of 14 clinical cases of TTS and a literature review conducted in 2008 showed that most patients handled the site of ulcer formation. Our patient denied manipulation. Consequently, TTS cannot be excluded if the patient denies this action.[<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]</p><p>In our case, pityriasis amiantacea was excluded due to a diagnosis of TTS that was made based on the past medical history of herpes zoster on the scalp and the presence of painful ulcers on the region that started to heal with gabapentin treatment.</p><p>In this syndrome, if there is a clear relationship with peripheral or central neural damage, the histopathology is not necessary, as in our case. Histopathology would show only chronic ulcer with minimal infiltrate. It can be performed to exclude malignancies, granulomas, and vascular lesions.[<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</p><p>An important aspect of the treatment is to discourage self-mutilation, and devices may be used to protect the injured area. Pharmacotherapy with gabapentin, benzodiazepines, amitriptyline, carbamazepine, and chlorpromazine has been used with variable results.[<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Declaration of patient consent</title><p>The authors certify that they have obtained all appropriate patient consent forms. In the form the patient(s) has/have given his/her/their consent for his/her/their images and other clinical information to be reported in the journal. The patients understand that their names and initials will not be published and due efforts will be made to conceal their identity, but anonymity cannot be guaranteed.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khachemoune</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminal trophic syndrome</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17567297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeidman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adolf wallenberg: Giant in neurology and refugee from Nazi Europe</article-title><source>J Hist Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24256512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garza</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trigeminal trophic syndrome: An unusual cause of face pain, dysaesthesias, anaesthesia and skin/soft tissue lesions</article-title><source>Cephalalgia</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18557978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Papay</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidimos</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminal trophic syndrome &#x02013; Report of four cases and review of the literature</article-title><source>Dermatol Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15099331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolohanty</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Markman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercurio</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminal trophic syndrome with histopathologic correlation</article-title><source>Cutis</source><year>2015</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>E22</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amorim</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pityriasis amiantacea: A study of seven cases</article-title><source>An Bras Dermatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27828657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monrad</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronoff</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The trigeminal trophic syndrome: An unusual cause of nasal ulceration</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2004</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15153901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trigeminal trophic syndrome</article-title><source>Int J Dermatol</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16863529</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>