<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6882</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5101707</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27825341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1401</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1401-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Essential oils: in vitro activity against <italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic>, cytotoxicity and chemical composition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>Milene Aparecida</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>Cl&#x000ea;nia dos Santos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>Fl&#x000e1;via Nader</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>Maria Luc&#x000ed;lia dos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>Camila Lasse</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>Jaime Martins de</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>Izabela M. D.</given-names></name><address><phone>+556131073051</phone><email>dourado@unb.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Pathogen-Host Interface Laboratory, Department of Cell Biology, The University of Bras&#x000ed;lia, Campus Darcy Ribeiro, Bloco I, Bras&#x000ed;lia, DF CEP 70910-900 Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Ceil&#x000e2;ndia, The University of Bras&#x000ed;lia, Bras&#x000ed;lia, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Institute of Chemistry, The University of Brasilia, Bras&#x000ed;lia, Brazil </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>444</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The current chemotherapy for cutaneous leishmaniosis (CL) has a series of drug limitations such as toxic side effects, long duration, high costs and drug resistance, which requires the development of new drugs or effective alternatives to the CL treatment. Essential oils (EOs) are complex mixtures of secondary metabolites from various plants. It has been shown that several EOs, or their constituents, have inhibitory activity against protozoa. Thus, this study aims to evaluate the biological activity of different essential oils (EOs) on <italic>Leishmania</italic> (<italic>L</italic>.) <italic>amazonensis</italic> promastigotes forms, as well as their cytotoxicity on mammalian cells and chemical composition.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Sixteen EOs were evaluated by mean of IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h and cytotoxicity against L6 cells (CC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h) using Resazurin assay. Only those EOs that presented better results for IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h were submitted to GC&#x02013;MS analysis to determine their chemical constitution.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The EO from <italic>Cinnamodendron dinisii</italic>, <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>, <italic>Myroxylon peruiferum</italic>, <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic>, <italic>Bulnesia sarmientoi</italic>, <italic>Ferula galbaniflua</italic>, <italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic> and <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> were the most active against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> with IC50/24&#x000a0;h ranging from 54.05 to 162.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. Analysis of EOs by GC&#x02013;MS showed mainly the presence of &#x003b2;-farnesene (52.73&#x000a0;%) and bisabolol oxide (12.09&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. chamomilla</italic>; &#x003b1;-copaene (13.41&#x000a0;%), safrole (8.35&#x000a0;%) and &#x003b4;-cadinene (7.08&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. peruiferum</italic>; linalool (28.80&#x000a0;%) and linalyl acetate (60.08&#x000a0;%) for <italic>S. sclarea</italic>; guaiol (48.29&#x000a0;%) and 2-undecanone (19.49&#x000a0;%) for <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic>; ethyl phthalate (13.09&#x000a0;%) and methyl-8-pimaren-18-oate (41.82&#x000a0;%) for <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic>; and neral (37.18&#x000a0;%) and citral (5.02&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. officinalis</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The EO from <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> showed to be effective against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> promastigotes forms and presented low cytotoxic activity against L6 cells. Thus, it represents a strong candidate for future studies aiming its molecular activity on these pathogenic parasites.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Secondary metabolites</kwd><kwd>Anti-<italic>Leishmania</italic></kwd><kwd>Natural products</kwd><kwd><italic>Ferula galbaniflua</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Capes</institution></funding-source><award-id>23038.005298/2011-83</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>Jaime Martins de</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CNPq</institution></funding-source><award-id>79/2013</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>Jaime Martins de</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>FAP/DF</institution></funding-source><award-id>193.001.076/2015</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>Izabela M. D.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>PGCTS-FCE/UnB</institution></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>FINEP</institution></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>DPP/UnB</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>Leishmaniasis, the third most important vector-borne diseases, is caused by a protozoan parasite of the genus <italic>Leishmania</italic>, which is transmitted to human by the bite of sand flies. Leishmaniasis represents a complex disease with diverse clinical manifestations and poses a public health problem since it is a neglected tropical disease with current high worldwide incidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Globally, more than 12 million individuals are infected, with another 350 million at risk of infection, and nearly 2 million new cases are reported annually worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The disease is prevalent in 16 developed and 72 developing countries; nevertheless 90&#x000a0;% of cases are reported in three regions: Sudan/Ethiopia/Kenya, India/Bangladesh/Nepal and Brazil with as many as 0.02 to 0.04 million deaths every year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p>Leishmaniasis can be divided into three forms, varying in severity from self-healing cutaneous lesions, dermatological ulcers in cutaneous leishmaniasis (CL), destructive form of mucocutaneous leishmaniasis, to deadly form of visceral leishmaniasis (VL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. CL is characterized by ulcers on the skin that are often formed at the site of the insect vector bite. Those ulcers can undergo metastasis of the nasopharyngeal mucosa developing to tissue destruction, depending on the species of <italic>Leishmania</italic> involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. <italic>Leishmania (Viannia) braziliensis</italic> and <italic>Leishmania (V.) panamensis</italic> are responsible for cases of mucocutaneous leishmaniasis in the Americas, although <italic>L. (V.) guyanensis</italic> and <italic>L. (L.) amazonensis</italic> have been identified, especially, in immuno-compromised hosts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>The first-line drugs for systemic treatment of leishmaniasis are parenterally administered antimonials such as the sodium stibogluconate (Pentostam&#x000ae;) and the N-methyl glucamine antimoniate (Glucantime&#x000ae;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] generally required for the treatment of CL in the New World due to the risk of mucosal involvement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This current chemotherapy presents several issues such as high cost, difficult administration and elevated toxicity, associated with serious side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], for instance musculoskeletal pain, gastrointestinal disturbances, mild to moderate headache, electrocardiographic QTs interval prolongation and mild to moderate increase of liver and pancreatic enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Second-line drug Pentamidine and amphotericin B are not widely used due to their high toxicity and cost. Miltefosine, the first oral anti-leishmanial drug, is the treatment of choice for diffuse cutaneous leishmaniasis and New World cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by <italic>Leishmania braziliensis</italic> but increasing resistance to this drug has been notified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p>All antileishmanial drugs except miltefosine have to be administrated parenterally. Most of these drugs are toxic, requires prolonged hospitalization and close monitoring, which makes the treatment costly and beyond the reach of most patients. Consequently, the development of alternative therapies is a priority for the treatment of leishmaniasis. As a strategy, the investigation of extracts and compounds, with biological activity, isolated from plants and used in traditional medicine is a promising in the research field for compounds with potential action for the prophylaxis and chemotherapy of CL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p>Essential oils (EOs) are complex mixtures of secondary metabolites isolated from plants. In these mixtures, there are 10&#x02013;60 constituents at different concentrations, but usually only 2&#x02013;3 major constituents determine the biological properties of the EO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Those compounds and their constituents present a broad pharmacological spectrum, and they are used as analgesics, sedatives, anti-inflammatory, and anti-spasmodic drugs, as well as antimicrobials, antiprotozoals and antihelmintics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. It has been shown that several EOs or their constituents have inhibitory activity on protozoa, especially <italic>Leishmania</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. For instance, Santos and colleagues demonstrated that copaiba oil from <italic>Copaifera martii</italic> is a safer, shorter, less-expansive, and more easily administered antileishmanial drug [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Therefore, the purpose of this present work was to analyze the effect of sixteen EOs biological potential on <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> promastigotes forms and L6 cells and chemical constitution, by GC-MS, of those EOs that showed better leishmanicidal results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Essential oils</title><p>EOs of <italic>Litsea cubeba</italic> fruits; <italic>Lavandula officinalis</italic>, <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> and <italic>Cananga odorata</italic> flowers; <italic>Elettaria cardamomum</italic> seeds; <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>, <italic>Myroxylon peruiferum</italic> and <italic>Bulnesia sarmientoi</italic> barks; <italic>Ferula galbaniflua</italic> resin; <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic>, <italic>Foeniculum officinalis</italic>, <italic>Cordia verbenaceae</italic>, and <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> leaves; <italic>Pelargonium graveolens</italic> leaves and stems were purchased from QUINARI Cosmetic and Fragrances Inc. (Maring&#x000e1;-PR, Brazil) with lot number 0717/05209/F. EOs of <italic>Cinnamodendron dinisii</italic> and <italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic> leaves were obtained as described by Andrade et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p>Firstly, EOs and Amphotericin B 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA) were diluted in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) at 100&#x000a0;mg/mL and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. For use, the stock was diluted 5:100 in either Schneider (Sigma-Aldrich) or RPMI-1640 (Sigma-Aldrich) media (sub stock). DMSO final concentration in the experiments never exceeded 0.5&#x000a0;%, a concentration that is not harmful to parasites and L6 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Stocks were stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the dark, to avoid degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The sub stock was freshly prepared before use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chemical composition of EOs</title><p>Gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC&#x02013;MS) analysis was performed using a Shimadzu GC-2010 gas chromatograph coupled with GCMS-QP2010 Plus equipped with auto sampler (model AOC-20i, Shimadzu, Columbia, MD, USA) and GC&#x02013;MS Solution software. Investigation was performed with a Rtx-5MS capillary column (30&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m) at programmed temperature ranging from 60 to 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at 3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min. Analysis conditions were: injector temperature 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, ion source interface temperature 300&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, analysis of masses between 40&#x02013;350&#x000a0;m/z, electron impact at 70&#x000a0;eV, column head pressure at constant pressure of 59 kPa, column flow 1.02&#x000a0;mL/min, gas linear velocity: 36.8&#x000a0;cm/s, carrier gas: helium, injected volume 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L (1:1000 in hexane) in splitless. Constituents of EOs were identified by comparing their mass spectral pattern and retention indexes (RI) relative to a standard n-alkane series (C<sub>9</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>24</sub>) with those known in the literature and the Wiley W9N08 database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Parasites and culture conditions</title><p>The promastigotes forms of <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> (strain MHOM/BR/77/LTB0016) were maintained at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in Schneider medium supplemented with 10&#x000a0;% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL gentamicin, with weekly passages. For the screening of EOs biological potential, promastigotes were collected from cultures at the mid-log phase of growth (3-day-old culture). The parasite strain was obtained from Fiocruz-COLPROT (Cole&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Protozo&#x000e1;rios da Fiocruz).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Antileishmanial activity of essential oils <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>EOs serial dilutions, from 500 to 31.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, were prepared on a 96-well cell culture plate. Afterwards, 1.35 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> parasite/mL culture resuspended in 150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L were added to the plates and incubated for 24&#x000a0;h at 28&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. After this period, 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of Resazurin solution were added to a 2&#x000a0;mM final concentration in all wells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The plates were incubated for further 4&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C followed by the fluorescence measurement under 570 nm<sub>ex</sub>/595 nm<sub>em</sub> in the microplate reader SpectraMax M5 (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA).</p><p>
<italic>In vitro</italic> experiment was performed in triplicate and repeated twice independently. DMSO was used as control in the same final concentration found in each dilution. Amphotericin B was used as positive control at final concentration ranging from 312.5 to 19.56&#x000a0;ng/mL.</p><p>The percentage of viable promastigotes cells was determined by the equation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{P}=\left(100\times \mathrm{F}\mathrm{a}\right)/\mathrm{F}\mathrm{c} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2016_1401_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where %P: percentage of viable promastigotes cells; Fc: control fluorescence units; Fa: fluorescence units emitted by the analyzed samples (with inhibitor).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cytotoxic activity of essential oils <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>Uninfected L6 cell monolayers were washed with Phosphate Buffered Saline (PBS) for 5&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, washed with RPMI medium pH&#x000a0;7.4&#x02009;+&#x02009;2.5&#x000a0;% FBS, centrifuged at 200&#x02009;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, resuspended in the same medium and, finally, seeded into 96-well plates (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> cells/well). Plates were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h, then the medium was removed and cells were washed with PBS. Diluted EOs were added to overnight-adhered L6 cells and incubated for more 24&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Cell viability was assessed by 2&#x000a0;mM Resazurin as described above.</p><p>The percentage of viable cells was determined by the equation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{V}=\left(100\times \mathrm{F}\mathrm{a}\right)/\mathrm{F}\mathrm{c} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">%</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2016_1401_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where %V is the percentage of viable cells, Fc: control fluorescence units; Fa: fluorescence units emitted by the analyzed samples (with inhibitor). The selectivity index (SI) was calculated by dividing CC<sub>50</sub> for the IC<sub>50</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For both <italic>in vitro</italic> EOs biological potential, a randomized complete block design (RBD) test was used, with 5 concentrations, 3 repetitions and 2 experiments (blocks) for each sample. The statistical program used was SISVAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Data were submitted to analysis of variance and the averages compared by Scott-Knott test and regression, both 5&#x000a0;% probability. The adjusted equations were used to calculate the concentration needed to cripple 50&#x000a0;% of L6 cells (CC<sub>50</sub>) or 50&#x000a0;% of the parasites (IC<sub>50</sub>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Antileishmanial and cytotoxic activity of essential oils <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>Growth inhibitory activity by the selected EOs was performed on <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> promastigotes forms at concentrations ranging from 30 to 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. In the test, the EOs of <italic>L. cubeba</italic>, <italic>E. cardamomum</italic>, <italic>L. officinalis</italic>, <italic>C. camphora</italic> and <italic>C. odorata</italic> did not show activity at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Lower concentrations of the remaining EOs were then evaluated to estimate the IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The most effective EO was of the one from <italic>S. guianensis</italic> (48.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.64&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), followed by <italic>C. dinisii</italic> (54.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.88&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>M. chamomilla</italic> (60.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.24&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>C. verbenaceae (</italic>64.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.04&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic> (85.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.38&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL)<italic>, F. galbaniflua</italic> (95.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.82&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (132.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.14&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL)<italic>, M. peruiferum</italic> (162.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.57&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL)<italic>, S. sclarea (</italic>325.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.58&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>F. officinalis (</italic>328, 28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6,80&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and <italic>P. graveolens</italic> (363.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.77&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). The IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h of Amphotericin B was 0.83&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>EOs biological potential and selectivity indexes (SI) for <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h) promastigotes and L6 cells (CC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Essential oils</th><th>
<italic>L. amazonensis</italic>
</th><th>L6 cells</th><th rowspan="2">SI<sup>g</sup>
</th></tr><tr><th>IC<sub>50</sub>
<sup>a</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;DP (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th><th>CC<sub>50</sub>
<sup>f</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;DP (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Litsea cubeba</italic>
</td><td>NI<sup>e</sup>
</td><td>180.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.37</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</td><td>60.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.24</td><td>173.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.24</td><td>2.87</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Elettaria cardamomum</italic>
</td><td>&#x0003e;500.00<sup>b</sup>
</td><td>439.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.27</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Lavandula officinalis</italic>
</td><td>&#x0003e;500.00</td><td>377.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.91</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>
</td><td>&#x0003e;500.00</td><td>&#x0003e;500.00</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Myroxylon peruiferum</italic>
</td><td>162.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.57</td><td>160.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62</td><td>0.99</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Salvia sclarea</italic>
</td><td>325.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.58</td><td>375.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.62</td><td>1.15</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Bulnesia sarmientoi</italic>
</td><td>85.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.38</td><td>163.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.77</td><td>1.91</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Ferula galbaniflua</italic>
</td><td>95.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.82</td><td>377.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.71</td><td>3.94</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Pelargonium graveolens</italic>
</td><td>363.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.77</td><td>368.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.90</td><td>1.01</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cananga odorata</italic>
</td><td>NI</td><td>142.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.76</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Foeniculum officinalis</italic>
</td><td>328. 28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.80</td><td>368.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.81</td><td>1.12</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cordia verbenaceae</italic>
</td><td>64.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.04</td><td>130.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.08</td><td>2.01</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Melissa officinalis</italic>
</td><td>132.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.14</td><td>297.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.32</td><td>2.25</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic>
</td><td>48.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.64</td><td>78.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19</td><td>1.60</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Cinnamodendron dinisii</italic>
</td><td>54.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.88</td><td>106.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.23</td><td>1.97</td></tr><tr><td>Anfotericina B<sup>c</sup>
</td><td>(0.083&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL)</td><td>NI</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>DMSO<sup>d</sup>
</td><td>NI</td><td>NI</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a)</sup> IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;DP: the concentration able to cripple 50&#x000a0;% of the parasites&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation</p><p>
<sup>b)</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;500.00: IC<sub>50</sub> greater than the highest concentration tested</p><p>
<sup>c)</sup> Amphotericin B - positive control</p><p>
<sup>d)</sup> DMSO - negative control</p><p>
<sup>e)</sup> NI: no inhibition</p><p>
<sup>f)</sup> CC<sub>50</sub>: the concentration able to cripple 50&#x000a0;% of cells after 24&#x000a0;h of treatment&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation</p><p>
<sup>g)</sup> Selectivity index - SI&#x02009;=&#x02009;CC<sub>50</sub> L6 / IC<sub>50</sub> promastigotes</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The cytotoxicity against L6 cells and <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> were compared using the selectivity index (SI) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Higher values of SI means more promising compounds for developing antileishmanial drugs. The SI measures the compound&#x02019;s level of selectivity towards <italic>L. amazonensis</italic>. Evaluation of cytotoxicity showed that the least cytotoxic EO was that of <italic>C. camphora</italic> (CC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x002c3;500.00&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), followed by <italic>E. cardamomum</italic> (439.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.27&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>L. officinalis</italic> (377.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.91&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> (377.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.71&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>S. sclarea</italic> (375.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.62&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>P. graveolens</italic> (368.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.90&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>F. officinalis</italic> (368.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.81&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (297.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.32&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>L. cubeba</italic> (180.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.37&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>M. chamomilla</italic> (173.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.24&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic> (163.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.77&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>M. peruiferum</italic> (160.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.62&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>C. odorata</italic> (142.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.76&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>C. verbenaceae</italic> (130.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.08 1.77&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>C. dinisii</italic> (106.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.23&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and the most cytotoxic EO was of the one from <italic>S. guianensis</italic> (78.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>EOs with higher selectivity indexes were those from <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> (3.94), <italic>M. chamomilla</italic> (2.87) and <italic>M. officinalis</italic> (2.25), but all were more cytotoxic and less selective than Amphotericin B, because the reference drug did not show CC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h value.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Chemical composition</title><p>The GC-MS analyses were performed for EOs that showed the lower values of IC<sub>50</sub> and/or the higher SI values (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The analysis identified the main constituents as &#x003b2;-farnesene (52.73&#x000a0;%), bisabolol oxide (12.09&#x000a0;%), &#x003b1;-farnesene (10.34&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. chamomilla</italic>; &#x003b1;-copaene (13.41&#x000a0;%), guaiol (9.35&#x000a0;%), safrole (8.35&#x000a0;%) and &#x003b4;-cadinene (7.08&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. peruiferum</italic>; linalool (28.80&#x000a0;%) and linalyl acetate (60.08&#x000a0;%) for <italic>S. sclarea</italic>; guaiol (48.29&#x000a0;%) and 2-undecanone (19.49&#x000a0;%) for <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic>; ethyl phthalate (13.09&#x000a0;%) and methyl-8-pimaren-18-oate (41.82&#x000a0;%) for <italic>F. galbaniflua;</italic> and neral (37.18&#x000a0;%) and geranial (5.02&#x000a0;%) for <italic>M. officinalis</italic>. According to Andrade et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], EO from <italic>C. dinisii</italic> fresh leaves is composed mainly by &#x003b1;-pinene (35.41&#x000a0;%), &#x003b2;-pinene (17.81&#x000a0;%), sabinene (12.01&#x000a0;%) and bicyclogermacrene (7.59&#x000a0;%). EO from <italic>S. guianensis</italic> fresh leaves contains &#x003b2;-myrcene (13.14&#x000a0;%), germacrene-D (8.68&#x000a0;%) and bicyclogermacrene (16.71&#x000a0;%).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of selected essential oils</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="11">Content (%)</th></tr><tr><th>IRc</th><th>IRl</th><th>Component</th><th>
<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Myroxylon peruiferum</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Salvia sclarea</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Bulnesia sarmientoi</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Ferula galbaniflua</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Melissa officinalis</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th><th>
<italic>Cinnamodendron dinisiia</italic>
<sup>a</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>930</td><td>932</td><td>&#x003b1;-pinene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.83</td><td>35.41</td></tr><tr><td>958</td><td>963</td><td>sabinene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12.01</td></tr><tr><td>961</td><td>970</td><td>&#x003b2;-pinene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17.34</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17.81</td></tr><tr><td>969</td><td>971</td><td>6-metil-5-hepten-2-one</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.88</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>975</td><td>0980</td><td>&#x003b2;-myrcene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.23</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13.14</td><td>1.46</td></tr><tr><td>1018</td><td>1024</td><td>1,8-cineole</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8.71</td><td>3.71</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.37</td></tr><tr><td>1086</td><td>1092</td><td>linalool</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>28.80</td><td>2.67</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1135</td><td>1130</td><td>&#x003b1;-terpineol</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.14</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1231</td><td>1235</td><td>neral</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>37.18</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1247</td><td>1252</td><td>linalyl acetate</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>60.08</td><td>2.64</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1263</td><td>1264</td><td>geranial</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>52.02</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1282</td><td>1285</td><td>safrole</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8.35</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1287</td><td>1293</td><td>2-undecanone</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>19.49</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.69</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1374</td><td>1374</td><td>&#x003b1;-copaene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13.41</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1428</td><td>1432</td><td>trans-&#x003b1;-bergamotene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.48</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1443</td><td>1439</td><td>(+)-aromadendrene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.27</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.26</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1451</td><td>1455</td><td>(E)-&#x003b2;-farnesene</td><td>52.73</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1455</td><td>1458</td><td>allo-aromandrendene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.24</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1470</td><td>1474</td><td>y-gurjunene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.29</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1476</td><td>1482</td><td>germancrene-D</td><td>3.42</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8.68</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1478</td><td>1479</td><td>ar-curcumene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.05</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1481</td><td>1487</td><td>&#x003b2;-selinene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.27</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1488</td><td>1497</td><td>bicyclogermancrene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>16.71</td><td>7.59</td></tr><tr><td>1504</td><td>1505</td><td>(E,E)-a-farnesene</td><td>10.34</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1504</td><td>1507</td><td>&#x003b2;-bisabolene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.09</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1510</td><td>1511</td><td>&#x003b4;-amorfene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>6.59</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1520</td><td>1522</td><td>&#x003b4;-cadinene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7.08</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.04</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>1576</td><td>1577</td><td>(&#x02212;)-spathulenol</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.79</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.16</td><td>1.88</td></tr><tr><td>1594</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>diethyl phthalate</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13.09</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1601</td><td>1600</td><td>Guaiol</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9.35</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>48.29</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1630</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>(&#x02212;)-sinularene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.81</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1652</td><td>1649</td><td>&#x003b2;-eudesmol</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1656</td><td>1656</td><td>bisabolol oxide B</td><td>12.09</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1657</td><td>1658</td><td>t-cadinol</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1,35</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.14</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1685</td><td>1685</td><td>&#x003b1;-bisabolol</td><td>9.83</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3.35</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>1732</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>camazulene</td><td>2.30</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>elixene</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5.87</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>methyl 8 (14)-pimaren-18- oate</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>41.82</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>NI</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9.39</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Total identified (%)</td><td>90.72</td><td>79.38</td><td>94.05</td><td>88.85</td><td>81.83</td><td>93.08</td><td>55.25</td><td>80.67</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IRl literature retention rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], IRc retention ratio calculated by Kovats&#x02019; equation. a) Described by Andrade et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>According to the classification of cytotoxicity and antileishmanial activity for extracts and fractions derived from plants and natural products defined by Study Program and Disease Control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], the evaluated EOs are classified as moderately toxic (100&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;CC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), except the EO from <italic>S. guainensis</italic>, which was classified as toxic (10&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;CC<sub>50 &#x02264;</sub> 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). Regarding the antileishmanial activity only EOs from <italic>S. guianensis</italic>, <italic>C. dinisii</italic>, <italic>M. chamomilla</italic>, <italic>C. verbenaceae</italic>, <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic>, <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> and <italic>M. officinalis</italic> are considered moderately active (50&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;150&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). The others are considered not active.</p><p>Considering the chemical composition of the EO from <italic>M. chamomilla</italic>, (E)-&#x003b2;-farnesene and (E,E)-&#x003b1;-farnesene were found as the major compound group representing 73.07&#x000a0;% of the total composition. These results corroborate with those reported by Machado et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] that found farnesene derivatives as the most representative constituents (22&#x000a0;%) and their bioassays using EO from <italic>Lantana camara</italic> revealed a significant leishmanicidal activity against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>/72&#x000a0;h&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), except for the cytotoxic activity, in which the authors obtained high values on Brine shrimp (CC<sub>50</sub> 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). Subsequently, Gawde <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] observed that the chemical composition of <italic>M. chamomilla</italic> was similar to the one found in our study (&#x003b2;-farnesene, &#x003b1;-bisabolol oxide B, chamazulene) but no leishmanicidal activity on <italic>L. donavani</italic> was observed.</p><p>Studies on the chemical composition and biological activity of <italic>M. peruiferum</italic> EO are scarce. The literature reports (E) and (Z)-nerolidol, &#x003b1;-bisabolol and (E, E)-farnesol as its major components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] but those compounds were not identified in the present study. Santos <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] reported high levels of &#x003b1;-copaene in EO from <italic>Copaifera reticulata</italic> as well as for EO from <italic>M. peruiferum</italic>. The last one showed growth inhibitory activity for <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> with IC<sub>50</sub>/72&#x000a0;h values of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for promastigotes and low cytotoxicity on J774G8 macrophages.</p><p>Ghannadi and Amree [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] have already described the EO composition obtained from the fresh oleogum resin and latex of Iranian <italic>F. galbaniflua (synonym F. gummosa)</italic> and the main constituents of this monoterpene rich oil were &#x003b2;-pinene (58.8&#x000a0;%). Other studies also indicate &#x003b2;-pinene as the major compound from the fresh oleogum resin and latex of this same specie [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], which corroborates our results. The presence of methyl 8-(14)-pimaren-18-ate, a diterpene esters hydrocarbons, has been reported on rosin, a solid form of resin obtained from pines and some other plants; and also in the Cretaceous resins from India and Myanmar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. To our knowledge, there is no antileishmanial activity reports related to this EO to date.</p><p>Rodilla et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] determined the chemical composition of EO from <italic>B. sarmientoi</italic>. In accordance with our work, they identified guaiol as its major component. Studies with EO from <italic>Endlicheria bracteolata</italic>, which has 72.12&#x000a0;% of guaiol in its composition, showed IC<sub>50</sub> of 7.93&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> and presented a CC<sub>50</sub> of 15.14&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for J774.G8 macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The antileishmanial activity may be attributed to the presence of a hydroxyl group of alcohol characteristics in the guaiol, especially in the exocyclic portion of the molecule [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p>The presence of linalyl acetate and linalool as the major compounds in <italic>S. sclarea</italic> EO (total of 88.88&#x000a0;%) corroborate to the results presented by Pitarokili et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] that evaluated the EO composition of <italic>S. sclarea</italic> originated from two localities in Greece, and by Ku&#x0017a;ma et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] that evaluated the EO composition from <italic>S. sclarea</italic> plants generated <italic>in vitro</italic>. On the other hand, antileishmanial activity of linalool-rich EO from leaves of <italic>Croton cajucara</italic> against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> was previously evaluated by Rosa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], they were able to demonstrate morphological changes in <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> promastigotes when treated with 15&#x000a0;ng/mL of that EO. In this study the cell lysis was observed within 1&#x000a0;h, indicating that the antileishmanial activity observed is directly related to the presence of linalool, due to the existence of a hydroxyl group in the organic alcohol function.</p><p>As in our study, the presence of the isomers of citral, neral and geranial are constantly reported in the chemical composition of the EO from <italic>M. officinalis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Regarding the antileishmanial activity, Mikus et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] reported an IC<sub>50</sub>/72&#x000a0;h of 7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for <italic>L. major</italic>, a CC<sub>50</sub>/72&#x000a0;h of 25.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL in HL-60 cells and SI of 3.6, higher than those observed in our study. Another study has already showed that citral presents activity against <italic>T. cruzi</italic>, possibly by inducing cell membrane lysis with leakage of cytoplasm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p>The EO from <italic>C. dinisii</italic> and <italic>S. guianensis</italic> showed weak inhibitory effect on the protozoan <italic>T. cruzi</italic> with values of IC<sub>50</sub>/24&#x000a0;h&#x02009;=&#x02009;209.30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL and 282.93&#x000a0;mg/mL, respectively. These values are higher when compared to those obtained in the study for <italic>L. amazonensis</italic>, 54.05 and 48.55&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p>The mechanism of action by which EOs inhibits parasite growth is still not well known, but previous studies have suggested that structural and morphological changes are caused by drugs that inhibit ergosterol synthesis, or interact with the membrane ergosterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Other studies indicated that the activity of essential oils on parasites is mainly due to terpene composition. Terpenes are responsible for the hydrophobic characteristic of EOs, thus allowing their diffusion through the parasite cell membrane, affecting intracellular metabolic pathways and organelles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>
<italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> EO is effective against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> promastigotes forms and has low cytotoxic activity. Thus, it represents a strong candidate for future studies in order to comprehend its biological activity agaisnt <italic>L. amazonensis</italic>.</p><p>The promising results of this study offer prospects for further research, as the evaluation of the antileishmanial potential of the major compounds and the elucidation of their molecules may, in the future, contribute to the discovery of effective drugs derived from plants for the treatment of parasitic diseases.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The autors are indebted with Central Anal&#x000ed;tica do Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica da Universidade de Bras&#x000ed;lia (CAIQ/UnB) for GC-MS analysis.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES): Programa Nacional de Incentivo a Pesquisa em Parasitologia B&#x000e1;sica (CAPES grant no: 23038.005298/2011-83); Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (CNPq Chamada 79/2013-MCTI/CNPq/FNDCT); Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Distrito Federal (FAP-DF- 193.001.076/2015); PGCTS-FCE/UNB; Financiadora de Estudos e Projetos (FINEP); Decanato de Pesquisa e P&#x000f3;s-gradua&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o/UnB (DPP/UnB).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>IMDB and JMS conceived the research idea. MAA, CSA and CLS conducted the experiment, analyzed and interpreted the data as well as prepared the first draft. MLS supported the conduct of the analysis and interpreted the data of CG-MS. IMDB, JMS, FNM, and CSA critically read and revised the paper. All authors have read and approved the paper before its final submission.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Homsi Y, Makdisi G. Leishmaniasis: a forgotten disease among neglected people. Internet J Health. 2009;11:1&#x02013;5. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ispub.com/IJH/11/2/9151">http://ispub.com/IJH/11/2/9151</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reedijk</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Schallig</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis: recente developments in diagnosis and management</article-title><source>Am J Clin Dermatol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40257-015-0114-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25687688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25687688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. World Health Organization. Investing to overcome the global impact of neglected tropical diseases: 3rd WHO report on neglected diseases. 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/152781/1/9789241564861_eng.pdf">http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/152781/1/9789241564861_eng.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e9;lez</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Bern</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Desjeux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leishmaniasis worldwide and global estimates of its incidence</article-title><source>PloS One.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e35671</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035671</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22693548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22693548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ejaz A, Raza N, Iftikhar N. Recurrent cutaneous leishmaniasis presenting as sporotrichoid abscesses: a rare presentation near Afghanistan border<bold>.</bold> Dermatol Online J. 2007; 13:15. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17498434">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17498434</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. World Health Organization. Technical Report Series 949&#x02014;control of leishmaniases. Report of a meeting of the WHO Expert Committee on the Control of Leishmaniases, Geneva, 22&#x02013;26 March 2010. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://whqlibdoc.who.int/trs/WHO_TRS_949_eng.pdf">http://whqlibdoc.who.int/trs/WHO_TRS_949_eng.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Name</surname><given-names>RQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>LSC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>JHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauil</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>RNR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical, epidemiological and therapeuthic study of 402 patients with american cutaneous leishmaniasis attended at University Hospital of Brasilia, DF, Brazil</article-title><source>Ann Bras Dermatol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0365-05962005000300004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gonz&#x000e1;lez U, Pinart M, Rengifo-Pardo M, Macaya A, Alvar J, Tweed JA. Interventions for American cutaneous and mucocutaneous leishmaniasis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009;2:1&#x02013;175. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19370612">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19370612</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minodier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis treatment</article-title><source>Travel Med Infect Dis.</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2006.09.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17448941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reithinger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dujardin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Louzir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirmez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutaneous leishmaniasis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis.</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(07)70209-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17714672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17714672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben Salah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Messaoud</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaatour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Alaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettaieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Topical paromomycin with or without gentamicin for cutaneous leishmaniasis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1202657</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23388004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23388004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Utaile</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassahun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility of clinical isolates of <italic>Leishmania aethiopica</italic> to miltefosine, paromomycin, amphotericin B and sodium stibogluconate using amastigote-macrophage <italic>in vitro</italic> model</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2013.01.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23434530?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23434530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azeredo</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>BHLNS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> biological evaluation of eight different essential oils against <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>, with emphasis on <italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>BMC Complementary Altern Med.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-14-309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakkali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Idaomar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of essential oils - A review</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2007.09.106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17996351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampasona</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalan</surname><given-names>CAN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of chemical, antioxidant and antimicrobial studies of cinnamon leaf and bark volatile oils, oleoresins and their constituents</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2007.02.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17408833?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17408833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Victoria</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenard&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Savegnago</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascente</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil of the leaves of <italic>Eugenia uniflora</italic> L.: antioxidant and antimicrobial properties</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>2668</fpage><lpage>2674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2012.05.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22583648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22583648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueda-Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendon&#x000e7;a-Filho</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgado-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maza</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado Dias Filho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>DAD</given-names></name><name><surname>Alviano</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Alviano</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antileishmanial activity of eugenol-rich essential oil from <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol Int</source><year>2006</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parint.2005.10.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16343984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16343984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda-Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias Filho</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Veiga Junior</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Brazilian copaiba oils on <italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic></article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2008.08.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18775772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>MGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cit&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>AMGL</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>JAD</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>RCBQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antileishmanial activity and cytotoxicity of essential oil from <italic>Lippia sidoides</italic> Cham</article-title><source>Parasitol Int.</source><year>2011</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parint.2011.03.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21421075?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21421075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Resende</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>ACS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical Composition and Antioxidant Activity of Essential Oils from <italic>Cinnamodendron dinisii</italic> Schwacke and <italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic> Aublet</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox2040384</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26784471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26784471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>LGL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacaroni</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influ&#x000ea;ncia da luz e da temperatura sobre a oxida&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o do &#x000f3;leo essencial de capim-lim&#x000e3;o (<italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (D.C.) STAPF)</article-title><source>Quim Nova</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1476</fpage><lpage>1480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0100-40422008000600037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Identification of Essential oil Components by Gas Chromatography/ Mass Spectroscopy</source><year>2007</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>IL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Allured Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Orton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pognan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the Alamar Blue (resazurin) fluorescent dye for the assessment of mammalian cell cytotoxicity</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>5421</fpage><lpage>5426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-1327.2000.01606.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10951200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10951200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Iten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grether-Buhler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Alamar Blue assay to determine drug sensitivity of African trypanosomes (<italic>T. b. rhodesiense</italic> and <italic>T. b. gambiense</italic>) <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><year>1997</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0001-706X(97)00079-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9386789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9386789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeredo</surname><given-names>CMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>LMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>ACS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological Activity of the Essential Oils from <italic>Cinnamodendron dinisii</italic> and <italic>Siparuna guianensis</italic></article-title><source>Braz J Microbiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838246120130683</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26221107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26221107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferreira DF. SISVAR: A computer statistical analysis system. Cienc Agrotec. 2008;6:36&#x02013;41. doi:10.1590/S1413-70542011000600001. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rios YK, Otero AC, Mu&#x000f1;oz DL, Echeverry M, Robledo SM, Yepes MA. Actividad citot&#x000f3;xica y leishmanicida <italic>in vitro</italic> del aceite de manzanilla (<italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>). Rev Colomb Cienc Qu&#x000ed;m Farm. 2008;37:200&#x02013;11. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.revistas.unal.edu.co/index.php/rccquifa/article/view/15254/16051">http://www.revistas.unal.edu.co/index.php/rccquifa/article/view/15254/16051</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>RRP</given-names></name><name><surname>Valente J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coimbra</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential oil from leaves of <italic>Lantana camara</italic>: a potential source of medicine against leishmaniasis</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacogn.</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-695X2012005000057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gawde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheljazkov</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Astatkie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steam distillation extraction kinetics regression models to predict essential oil yield, composition, and bioactivity of chamomile oil</article-title><source>Ind Crops Prod.</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2014.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wanner J, Schmidt E, Bail S, Jirovetz L, Buchbauer G, Gochev V, et al. Chemical composition and antibacterial activity of selected essential oils and some of their main compounds. Nat Prod Commun. 2010;5:1359&#x02013;64. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20922991">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20922991</ext-link>. Accessed 04 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghannadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amree</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile oil constituents of <italic>Ferula gummosa</italic> Boiss. from Kashan, Iran</article-title><source>J Essent Oil Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10412905.2002.9699908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouyakhi</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Naghavi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alayhs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of the essential oil variation of <italic>Ferula gummosa</italic> samples from Iran</article-title><source>Chem Nat Compounds.</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10600-008-0038-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahebkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iranshahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile Constituents of the Genus <italic>Ferula</italic> (Apiaceae): A Review</article-title><source>J Essent Oil-Bear Plants.</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0972060X.2011.10643969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chang T, Mead TE, Zlnkel DF. Mass Spectra of Diterpene Resin Acid Methyl. J Am Oil Chem Soc.1presented in part at the Meeting of the American Chemical Society, Chicago. 1970. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02544660">http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02544660</ext-link>. Accessed 05 Apr 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoid composition and botanical affinity of Cretaceous resins from India and Myanmar</article-title><source>Int J Coal Geol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coal.2010.09.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodilla</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davyt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Coloma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zrostl&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;f</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellacassa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in the identification and agrochemical importance of sesquiterpenoids from <italic>Bulnesia sarmientoi</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>Ind Crops Prod</source><year>2011</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2010.10.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rottini</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>ACF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JLP</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JRA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniwaki</surname></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>CSF</given-names></name><name><surname>d'Escoffier</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida-Souza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardoim</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>SCG</given-names></name><name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of (&#x02212;) &#x003b1;-bisabolol as a promising agent against <italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic></article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>2015</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2014.10.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25448354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25448354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitarokili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Couladis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petsikos-Panayotarou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzakou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition and antifungal activity on soil-borne pathogens of the essential oil of <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic> from Greece</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem.</source><year>2002</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>6688</fpage><lpage>6691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf020422n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12405762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12405762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ku&#x0017a;ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalemba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f3;&#x0017c;alski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f3;&#x0017c;alska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wi&#x00119;ckowska-Szakiel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krajewska</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wysoki&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and biological activities of essential oil from <italic>Salvia sclarea</italic> plants regenerated <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Molecules.</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1438</fpage><lpage>1447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules14041438</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19384275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19384275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>MSS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendon&#x000e7;a-Filho</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bizzo</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>RMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Souto-Padr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alviano</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>AHCS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antileishmanial activity of a linalool-rich essential oil from <italic>Croton cajucara</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1895</fpage><lpage>1901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.6.1895-1901.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12760864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadraei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghannadib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malekshahia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relaxant effect of essential oil of <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> and citral on rat ileum contractions</article-title><source>Fitoterapia.</source><year>2003</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0367-326X(03)00109-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12837359?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mimica-Dukic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and Antioxidant activities of <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> L. (Lamiaceae) essential oil</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>2485</fpage><lpage>2489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf030698a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15113145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>CLS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Esquibel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> L. <italic>in vitro</italic> produced under the influence of growth regulators</article-title><source>J Braz Chem Soc</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1387</fpage><lpage>1390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-50532005000800014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harkenthal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steverding</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> effect of essential oils and isolated mono- and sesquiterpenes on <italic>Leishmania major</italic> and <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><year>2000</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2000-8548</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10865458?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10865458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Santoro GF, Cardoso MG, Guimar&#x000e3;es LGL, Freire JM, Soares MJ. Antiproliferative effect of the essential oil of <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC) Stapf (lemongrass) on intracelular amastigotes, bloodstream trypomastigotes and culture epimastigotes of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (Protozoa: Kinetoplastida). Parasitology. 2007;13:1649&#x02013;56. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17686189">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17686189</ext-link>. Accessed 05 Apr 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenzan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>BPD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda-Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>DAG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antileishmanial activity of crude extract and coumarin from <italic>Calophyllum brasiliense</italic> leaves against <italic>Leishmania amazonensis</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-007-0542-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17483964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aires</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Higino</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trypanocidal and cytotoxic activities of essential oils from medicinal plants of Northeast of Brazil</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2012.06.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22771867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771867</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>