<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Pharmacol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1663-9812</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6232252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.01175</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Pharmacology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human Adipose Tissue-Derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells Attenuate Atopic Dermatitis by Regulating the Expression of MIP-2, miR-122a-SOCS1 Axis, and Th1/Th2 Responses</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Misun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sung-Hoon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/591465/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Youngmi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/202316/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Yoojung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Yeongseo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Hong-Ki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Hyun Suk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/495500/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeoung</surname><given-names>Dooil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/180398/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Biochemistry, Kangwon National University</institution>, <addr-line>Chunchon</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Biotechnology Institute, EHL-BIO Co., Ltd.</institution>, <addr-line>Uiwang</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Patrizia Ballerini, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi &#x0201c;G. d&#x02019;Annunzio&#x0201d; Chieti - Pescara, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Eldi Schonfeld-Dado, Stanford University, United States; Dan Hu, Wuhan University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Dooil Jeoung, <email>jeoungd@kangwon.ac.kr</email></corresp><corresp id="fn002"><sup>&#x02020;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>This article was submitted to Inflammation Pharmacology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Pharmacology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1175</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Kim, Lee, Kim, Kwon, Park, Lee, Jung and Jeoung.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kim, Lee, Kim, Kwon, Park, Lee, Jung and Jeoung</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The objective of this study was to investigate the effect of human adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal stem cells (AdMSCs) on atopic dermatitis (AD) in the BALB/c mouse model. The AdMSCs attenuated clinical symptoms associated with AD, decreased numbers of degranulated mast cells (MCs), IgE level, amount of histamine released, and prostaglandin E2 level. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of cytokines/chemokines, such as interleukin-5 (IL-5), macrophage inflammatory protein-1&#x000df; (MIP-1&#x000df;), MIP-2, chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 5 (CCL5), and IL-17, in BALB/c mouse. The AdMSCs showed decreased expression levels of these cytokines in the mouse model of AD. <italic>In vivo</italic> downregulation of MIP-2 attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of hallmarks of allergic inflammation, induced interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2; with histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3) and Lyn, increased &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity, increased serum IgE level, and increased the amount of histamine released in an MIP-2-dependent manner. Downregulation of MIP-2 increased the levels of several miRNAs, including miR-122a-5p. Mouse miR-122a-5p mimic inhibited AD, while suppressor of cytokine signaling 1 (SOCS1), a predicted downstream target of miR-122a-5p, was required for AD. The downregulation of SOCS1 decreased the expression levels of MIP-2 and chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 13 (CXCL13) in the mouse model of AD. The downregulation of CXCL13 attenuated AD and allergic inflammation such as passive cutaneous anaphylaxis. The role of T cell transcription factors in AD was also investigated. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of T-bet and GATA-3 [transcription factors of T-helper 1 (Th1) and T-helper 2 (Th2) cells, respectively] but decreased the expression of Foxp3, a transcription factor of regulatory T (Treg) cells, in an SOCS1-dependent manner. In addition to this, miR-122a-5p mimic also prevented AD from regulating the expression of T-bet, GATA-3, and Foxp3. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression of cluster of differentiation 163 (CD163), a marker of M2 macrophages, but decreased the expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS), a marker of M1 macrophages. Additionally, SOCS1 and miR-122a-5p mimic regulated the expression of CD163 and iNOS in the mouse model of AD. Experiments employing conditioned medium showed interactions between MCs and macrophages in AD. The conditioned medium of AdMSCs, but not the conditioned medium of human dermal fibroblasts, negatively inhibited the features of allergic inflammation. In summary, we investigated the anti-atopic effects of AdMSCs, identified targets of AdMSCs, and determined the underlying mechanism for the anti-atopic effects of AdMSCs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>adipose tissue-derived stem cells</kwd><kwd>atopic dermatitis</kwd><kwd>targets of stem cells</kwd><kwd>cellular interactions</kwd><kwd>MIP-2</kwd><kwd>miR-122a-5p</kwd><kwd>SOCS1</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="15"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="58"/><page-count count="19"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) are multipotent stem cells that can be isolated from various tissues, including bone marrow, umbilical cord and adipose tissue. They interact with both innate and adaptive immune systems, resulting in a suppressive effect on the activation of immune cells, including T cells, B cells, dendritic cells, and natural killer (NK) cells (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Asari et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Prigione et al., 2009</xref>). Mesenchymal stem cells can ameliorate allergic diseases such as asthma, rhinitis, and dermatitis (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Nemeth et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Kavanagh and Mahon, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Kapoor et al., 2012</xref>), and MSCs suppress chronic asthmatic changes in male rats (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmadi et al., 2016</xref>). Intratracheally administered MSCs can attenuate inflammation and promote tissue homeostasis in the course of allergic asthma (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Urbanek et al., 2016</xref>). In addition, MSCs can change microRNA (miRNA) expression profile in airway allergic inflammation (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2016</xref>), suppress lung inflammation and airway remodeling via PI3K/Akt signaling pathway in rat asthma model (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2015</xref>), and ameliorate allergic airway inflammation by blunting the amplification of epithelial-derived inflammatory cytokines (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Duong et al., 2015</xref>). The overexpression of C-X-C motif chemokine receptor 5 (CXCR5) is known to intensify the immunomodulatory effects of MSCs, and it decreases allergic contact dermatitis (ACD) (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Human umbilical cord blood-derived MSCs (hUC-MSCs) are known to exhibit protective effects against AD and suppress infiltration and degranulation of mast cells (MCs) (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2015</xref>). Transforming growth factor (TGF-&#x003b2;1) production from hUC-MSCs in response to interleukin-4 (IL-4) contributes to the attenuation of MC degranulation by downregulating Fc&#x1d700;RI expression in MCs (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2015</xref>). Adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal stem cells (AdMSCs) contribute to the self-limiting course of ACD by decreasing the expression of interferon-&#x003b3; (IFN-&#x003b3;) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kikuchi et al., 2017</xref>). They can reduce gross and histological signatures of AD induced by <italic>Dermatophagoides farinae</italic>, decrease serum IgE level, and suppress MC degranulation (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Shin et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p>Although previous reports have suggested the roles of AdMSCs in treating allergic diseases, their efficacy and mechanisms in treating AD have not been extensively investigated yet. In this study, we showed the anti-atopic effect of AdMSCs and identified macrophage inflammatory protein-2 (MIP-2) as a target of AdMSCs in a mouse model of AD. Macrophage inflammatory protein-2 acted as a negative regulator of miR-122a-5p. Underlying mechanisms of the anti-atopic effect of AdMSCs were also identified by determining the effects of MIP-2, miR-122a-5p-suppressor of cytokine signaling 1 (SOCS1) negative feedback loop on the clinical symptoms, expression levels of hallmarks, immune responses, and cellular interactions accompanied by AD. A conditioned medium of AdMSCs was employed to investigate the mechanism of the anti-atopic effect of AdMSCs in relation with cellular interactions during AD. Our study may offer a valuable strategy for the development of anti-atopic therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals and Materials</title><p>Female BALB/c mice that were five weeks old were purchased from Nara Biotech (Seoul, South Korea) and were group housed under specific pathogen-free conditions in the animal facility of the Kangwon National University. All animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of the Kangwon National University (KIACUC-160329-2). Acetone and 2, 4-dinitrochlorobenzene (DNCB) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, United States). All other chemicals used in this study were also purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, United States). The following antibodies were obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, United States): MIP-2, histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3), transglutaminase II (TGaseII), cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2), monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 (MCP1), Lyn, SOCS1, Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2;, and actin. Anti-mouse and anti-rabbit IgG horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated antibodies were purchased from Thermo Pierce (Rockford, IL, United States). The jetPRIME transfection reagent was purchased from Polyplus (NY, United States). The miRNA mimic and siRNAs were purchased from Bioneer Company (Daejeon, South Korea). The MIP-2 siRNA [5&#x02032;-GAGUUGGGAACUAGCUACA-3&#x02032; (sense) and 5&#x02032;-UGUAGCUAGUUCCCAACUC-3&#x02032; (antisense)] and scrambled siRNA [5&#x02032;-GGTACGTCTCGAAGATAGA-3&#x02032; (sense) and 5&#x02032;- GCTATCGCCCATTGCTAAT-3&#x02032; (antisense)]; SOCS1 siRNA [5&#x02032;-GUGACUACCUGAGUUCCUU-3&#x02032; (sense) and 5&#x02032;-AAGGAACUCAGGUAGUCAC-3&#x02032; (antisense)]; and CXCL13 siRNA [5&#x02032;-GAGGAAUGAAAAACCUACA-3&#x02032; (sense) and 5&#x02032;-UGUAGGUUUUUCAUUCCUC-3&#x02032; (antisense)] were used. Primers used in this study were commercially synthesized by Bioneer Company (Daejeon, South Korea).</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation and Culture of Human Adipose Tissue-Derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells</title><p>The AdMSCs were isolated from human fat tissue obtained by liposuction (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Shin et al., 2017</xref>). Fat tissue was washed with &#x003b1;-minimum essential medium (&#x003b1;-MEM; Gibco, Grand Island, NY, United States) and was digested with an 0.1% collagenase (type I, Gibco, Grand Island, NY, United States) solution at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min. Cell pellet obtained by centrifugation at 2,000 rpm for 10 min was suspended in &#x003b1;-MEM containing 8% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Mulgrave Victoria, Australia) and filtrated with 100 &#x003bc;m nylon mesh. Cell suspension was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24 h, and unbound cells were removed by washing. Cells were passaged five times by the TrypLE<sup>TM</sup> (Gibco Grand Island, NY, United States) method, and surface cluster of differentiation (CD) markers of AdMSCs were analyzed by FACS (FACSVerse, BD). All AdMSC banking was conducted in accordance with guidelines approved by the Korea National Institute for Bioethics Policy&#x02019;s IRB (IRB No. P01-201511-31-004).</p></sec><sec><title>Culture of Human Dermal Fibroblasts</title><p>Human primary dermal fibroblasts were purchased (HDFa lot #1780051, Gibco, Grand Island, NY, United States) and expanded in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified eagle medium (DMEM; Gibco, Grand Island, NY, United States) containing 8% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Mulgrave Victoria, Australia) at 37&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Induction of Atopic Dermatitis in BALB/c Mice</title><p>Symptoms of atopic dermatitis (AD) were induced by using DNCB, as previously described (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2010</xref>), with minor modifications. Briefly, the upper backs of the mice were shaved with a clipper. After 24 h, 150 &#x003bc;l of 1% DNCB in acetone: olive oil mixture (4:1 vol/vol) was topically applied on days 1 through 5. Later, the same dose of 0.2% DNCB was applied three times a week for 4 weeks. Human AdMSCs [1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells in 100 &#x003bc;l phosphate buffered saline (PBS)] were injected intravenously on days 12 and 23 of the timeline (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The cell control group was injected with human dermal fibroblast (HDF). Dermatitis scores of 0 (none), 1 (mild), 2 (moderate), and 3 (severe) were given for each of the four symptoms: dryness, excoriation, erosion, and erythema and edema. The sum of the individual scores was used as the clinical severity. After sacrifice on day 26, serum and skin samples were collected and stored at -80&#x000b0;C to detect the concentration of total IgE, prostaglandin E2 (PGE2), and the amount of histamine released or to evaluate histopathological lesions. The experimental design is described in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>. To examine the effect of MIP-2 on AD, mice were intravenously injected with MIP-2 siRNA (100 nM) or scrambled siRNA (100 nM) for a total of seven times as described in the timeline (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). To examine the effect of SOCS1 on AD, mice were intravenously injected with SOCS1 siRNA (100 nM) or scrambled siRNA (100 nM) for a total of five times as described in the timeline (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). To examine the effect of miR-122a-5p on AD, mice were intravenously injected with control mimic (100 nM) or miR-122a-5p mimic (100 nM) for a total of six times as described in the timeline (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Human adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal stem cells (AdMSCs) attenuate the clinical symptoms associated with atopic dermatitis (AD). <bold>(A)</bold> 2, 4-dinitro chlorobenzene (DNCB) was employed to induce AD in BALB/c mice. Human dermal fibroblasts (HDFs) or AdMSCs were intravenously injected once a week. <bold>(B)</bold> At the indicated day (day 36) after the induction of AD, clinical scores of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were determined. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. N.C., negative control; N.S., not significant. <bold>(C)</bold> Sera of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were employed for the determination of prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) level, IgE level, and the amount of histamine released. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Histological Examination</title><p>To evaluate skin thickening and cellular infiltration, skin samples were collected, fixed with 10% neutral buffered formalin, and embedded in paraffin. Sections (5 &#x003bc;m thickness) were prepared and stained with haemotoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) or toluidine blue for leukocyte infiltration or MC infiltration and degranulation, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>The Levels of IgE, PGE2, and Histamine Release</title><p>The levels of IgE, PGE2, and the amount of histamine released were measured according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instruction using the commercially available ELISA kit (Abcam, United Kingdom). Reaction product was measured calorimetrically with a microplate reader. Histamine release assays employing sera of BALB/c mice were performed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instruction (Enzo, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Cytokine Array</title><p>Expression levels of cytokine/chemokines were determined by using a Proteom ProfilerTM Mouse Cytokine Array Kit (R&#x00026;D Systems, MN, United States) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Blood serum collected from the BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was incubated with an array containing 40 mouse cytokine and chemokine specific antibodies. Relative cytokine intensities were normalized in comparison with control spots on the same membrane.</p></sec><sec><title>miRNA Array</title><p>The miRNA expression analysis in AdMSCs was performed by using miRNA Array III (Signosis, CA, United States) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Briefly, 5 mg of total miRNA was annealed to an oligonucleotide primer mix and hybridized to 132 miRNA oligonucleotide probes. Streptavidin-HRP chemiluminescence was used for the detection of miRNA expression.</p></sec><sec><title>miRNA Extraction and Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p>Total miRNA was isolated with the miRNeasy Micro Kit (Qiagen, CA, United States) following the standard protocol from the manufacturer. The extracted miRNA was reverse transcribed using a miScript II RT Kit (Qiagen, CA, United States) with universal RT primer. The expression level of miR-122a-5p was quantified with SYBR Green Master Mix (Qiagen, CA, United States) using a miRNA-specific forward primer and universal reverse primer. Relative expression of miRNA was calculated using the 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method (&#x00394;CT = CT<sub>miR</sub> -CT<sub>reference</sub>). The U6 small nuclear RNA was used as an endogenous control for data normalization. The expression levels of MIP-2, SOCS1, and T-helper 1 (Th1)/ T-helper 2 (Th2) cytokines were also quantified by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>miRNA Target Analysis</title><p>Genes that contain the miR-binding site(s) in the untranslated region (UTR) were obtained using the TargetScan<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn03">3</xref></sup> program.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture</title><p>Isolation of macrophages was performed according to the standard procedures with slight modifications (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Eom et al., 2014a</xref>). Isolation of MCs was performed according to the standard procedures with slight modifications (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Eom et al., 2014b</xref>). Rat basophilic leukemia (RBL2H3) cells were obtained from the Korea Cell Line Bank (Seoul, South Korea). Cells were grown in DMEM containing heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 U/ml penicillin, and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml streptomycin (Invitrogen). Cultures were maintained in 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Western Blot and Immunoprecipitation Analysis</title><p>Western blot and immunoprecipitation analyses were performed according to the standard procedures (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Eom et al., 2014a</xref>). Tissue homogenates obtained from frozen samples were lysed in a radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 1 mM NaF, 1 mM Na3VO4, 1 mM leupeptin, 20 &#x003bc;g/ml aprotinin, and 1% Nonidet P-40. Protein content of the supernatant was quantified using the Bio-Rad protein assay reagent. Equal amounts of proteins were separated on 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gels, transferred to PVDF membrane, and then exposed to the appropriate antibodies. For immunoprecipitation, 100 &#x003bc;g of protein was incubated with anti-Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2; antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml), and immunocomplexes were precipitated using protein A/G Sepharose and analyzed by western blot.</p></sec><sec><title>&#x003b2;-Hexosaminidase Activity Assays</title><p>&#x003b2;-hexosaminidase activity assays were performed according to standard procedures as described previously (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Noh et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunohistochemical Staining</title><p>Immunohistochemical staining of tissues was performed using an established avidin-biotin detection method (Vectastain ABC kit, Vector Laboratories Inc., Burlingame, CA, United States). 4&#x02013;6 &#x003bc;m-thick sections of the paraffin-embedded tissue blocks were cut, mounted on positively charged glass slides, and dried in an oven at 56&#x000b0;C for 30 min. The sections were deparaffinized in xylene and then rehydrated in graded ethanol and water. Endogenous peroxidase was blocked by incubation in 3% (v/v) hydrogen peroxide for 15 min. Antigen retrieval was accomplished by pretreatment of the sections with citrate buffer at pH 6.0 for 20 min at 56&#x000b0;C in a microwave oven, and then the sections were allowed to cool for 30 min. Nonspecific endogenous protein binding was blocked using 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA). The sections were then incubated with primary antibodies overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The following primary antibodies were used: anti-SOCS1 (1:100, Santa Cruz Biotechnology); anti-MIP-2 (1:100, Invitrogen); anti-CXCL13 (1:250, R&#x00026;D Systems); anti-CD163 (1: 700, Abchem); and anti-inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) (1: 500, Santa Cruz Biotechnology). After washing, biotinylated secondary antibodies were applied at 1:100 or 1:200 dilutions for 1 h. Color was developed with diaminobenzidine (Vector Laboratories, Inc.). Sections were counterstained with Mayer&#x02019;s hematoxylin. The sections incubated without primary antibody served as controls. To visualize tissue MCs, the sections were stained with 0.1% toluidine blue (Sigma) in 0.1 N HCl for 15 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Passive Cutaneous Anaphylaxis (PCA)</title><p>The BALB/c mice were sensitized with an intradermal injection of 2, 4-dinitrophenol (DNP)-specific IgE (0.5 &#x003bc;g/kg). After 24 h, the mice were challenged with an intravenous injection of DNP-human serum albumin (HSA) (250 &#x003bc;g/kg) and 2% (v/v) Evans blue solution. After 30 min of DNP-HSA challenge, the mice were euthanized, and the 2% (v/v) Evans blue dye was extracted from each dissected ear in 700 &#x003bc;l of acetone/water (7:3) overnight. The absorbance of Evans blue in these extracts was measured with a spectrophotometer at 620 nm. To determine the effect of CXCL13 on the PCA, BALB/c mice were given an intradermal injection of IgE (0.5 &#x003bc;g/kg) and intravenous injection of the indicated siRNA (each at 100 nM). The next day, BALB/c mice were given an intravenous injection of PBS or DNP-HSA (250 &#x003bc;g/kg) along with 2% (v/v) Evans blue solution for determining the extent of vascular permeability accompanied by PCA. Later, 1 h after the injection of Evans blue solution, the dye was eluted from the ear in 700 &#x003bc;l of formamide at 63&#x000b0;C. The absorbance was measured at 620 nm. To determine the effect of the conditioned medium on PCA, BALB/c mice were given an intradermal injection of DNP-specific IgE (0.5 &#x003bc;g/kg) and an intravenous injection of the conditioned medium of AdMSCs or HDFs (each at 200 &#x003bc;l/mouse). The following day, BALB/c mice were administered an intravenous injection of PBS or DNP-HSA (250 &#x003bc;g/kg) along with 2% (v/v) Evans blue solution for determining the extent of vascular permeability accompanied by PCA.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed and graphed using the GraphPad Prism statistics program (GraphPad Prism software). Results are presented as means &#x000b1; SE. Statistical analysis was performed using <italic>t</italic>-tests with differences between means considered significant when <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Human Adipose Tissue-Derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells Inhibit Features of Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>Several reports have shown the anti-allergic effects of MSCs (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Nemeth et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Kavanagh and Mahon, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Kapoor et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmadi et al., 2016</xref>). This led us to hypothesize that MSCs might be able to regulate AD. We examined the effect of human AdMSCs on AD. For this, AD in BALB/c mouse was induced by DNCB. The BALB/c mice were treated with 1% (v/v) DNCB on days 1 through 5 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). These mice were treated again with 0.2% (v/v) DNCB on days 9 through 11. To examine the effect of AdMSCs on AD, AdMSCs (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells) were injected intravenously at day 12 when AD was fully induced. The AdMSCs were injected intravenously once a week after the induction of AD. The HDFs were used as negative controls. The AdMSCs attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B,C</xref>). The HDFs failed to affect the clinical symptoms associated with AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Additionally, AdMSCs prevented DNCB from increasing the levels of PGE2, IgE, and the amount of histamine released in the sera of BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). Staining with H&#x00026;E showed that epidermal hyperplasia and lymphocyte infiltration induced by AD were attenuated by AdMSCs, but not by HDFs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Toluidine blue staining showed that AdMSCs, but not HDFs, decreased the number of degranulated MCs in the mouse model of AD (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B,C</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that AdMSCs can attenuate the clinical symptoms associated with AD. However, the mechanism for the anti-atopic effects of AdMSCs remains unknown.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>AdMSCs inhibit features of AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were isolated at the time of sacrifice and were subjected to hematoxylin &#x00026; eosin (H&#x00026;E) staining. <bold>(B,C)</bold> Same as <bold>(A)</bold> except that toluidine blue staining was performed to determine the number of degranulated mast cells. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. Scale bars represent 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>AdMSCs Exert Negative Effect on Increased Expression of Cytokines in Mouse Model of Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>Previous reports have suggested the roles of cytokines in anti-allergic effects of MSCs (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Duong et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). We hypothesized that AdMSCs could target cytokines to exert anti-atopic effects. For this, mouse model of AD was used (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), and serum obtained from the BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was subjected to cytokine array analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of IL-5, IL-17, chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 5 (CCL5), MIP-1&#x000df;, and MIP-2 in the serum of BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). The AdMSCs, but not HDFs, prevented DNCB from increasing the expression of these cytokines (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). Macrophage inflammatory protein-2 is necessary for AD induced by 1-Fluoro-2, 4-dinitrofluorobenzene in an Nc/Nga mouse model (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2010</xref>). Acute AD lesion shows a significant upregulation of Th2 promoting chemokines, such as CCL5 and CCL17 (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Olivry et al., 2016</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that AdMSCs may exert an anti-atopic effect by regulating the expression of inflammatory cytokines/chemokines such as MIP-2.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Identification of cytokines subjected to opposite regulations by AD and AdMSCs. <bold>(A)</bold> Shows the experimental time line to determine cytokines that mediate AD and serve as targets of AdMSCs. <bold>(B)</bold> Serum of BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was subjected to cytokine array analysis. Serum was obtained at the time of sacrifice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>MIP-2 Is Necessary for DNCB-Induced Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>The level of MIP-2 was decreased by AdMSCs in the mouse model of AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). The role of MIP-2 in AD has not been studied extensively when compared with cytokines such as IL-5, IL-17, CCL5, or MIP-1&#x000df;. Therefore, we examined the role of MIP-2 in AD. Downregulation of MIP-2 attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD induced by DNCB in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the serum IgE level, the amount of histamine released, and &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity in an MIP-2-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of SOCS1, TGaseII, COX-2, histone deacetylase 3 (HDAC3), and MCP1 in BALB/c mouse in an MIP-2-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). Roles of TGaseII (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Eom et al., 2014a</xref>), SOCS1 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Noh et al., 2017</xref>), COX-2 (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al., 2015</xref>), and HDAC3 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Eom et al., 2014b</xref>) in allergic inflammation, such as anaphylaxis, have been previously reported. Also, SOCS1 can suppress the immune modulatory function of MSCs by inhibiting the production of NO (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>). Downregulation of MIP-2 prevented DNCB from inducing interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2; with HDAC3, Lyn, and SOCS1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). Therefore, AD and anaphylaxis display common molecular features. Atopic dermatitis induced epidermal hyperplasia and lymphocyte infiltration. It also increased the numbers of degranulated MCs in an MIP-2-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed increased expression of MIP-2 by AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Therefore, MIP-2 might mediate the atopic effect induced by DNCB.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Macrophage inflammatory proten-2 (MIP-2) is necessary for AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Shows the experimental time line to determine the effect of MIP-2 on AD. Lower figure shows the effect of MIP-2 on clinical symptoms associated with AD. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(B)</bold> Skin tissue lysates were subjected to &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assay and qRT-PCR analysis. Serum IgE level and the amount of histamine released were also determined. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(C)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to western blot analysis and immunoprecipitation by employing the indicated antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml). Tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse injected with scrambled (scr.) following the induction of AD by DNCB were also immunoprecipitated with isotype-matched IgG antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>Induction of the features of AD occurs in an MIP-2-dependent manner. Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were isolated at the time of sacrifice and were subjected to immunohistochemical staining by employing anti-MIP-2 antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml) and H&#x00026;E staining. Toluidine blue staining was also performed to determine the number of degranulated mast cells. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SOCS1, a Potential Target of MIP2-Regulated miR-122a-5p, Is Necessary for DNCB-Induced Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>The roles of miRNAs in allergic inflammation have been reported as 18, 21. We hypothesized that MIP-2 would mediate AD by regulating miRNAs. For this, a miRNA array analysis was performed using skin tissue lysates of BALB/c mice. Additionally, miRNAs, such as miR-19a, miR-122a-5p, miR-182, miR-24, miR-30b, miR-188, and miR-199a, were downregulated by AD but upregulated by the downregulation of MIP-2 in BALB/c mouse under AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). TargetScan analysis predicted that the binding of miR-122a-5p to the 3&#x02032; UTR of SOCS1 and miR-122a-5p would decrease luciferase activity associated with 3&#x02032; UTR of SOCS1 in rat basophilic leukemia (RBL2H3) cells (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Noh et al., 2017</xref>). Since miR-122a-5p, downregulated by AD, was predicted to target SOCS1 in AD, we hypothesized that SOCS1 would be necessary for AD. The downregulation of SOCS1 attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of MIP-2, COX-2, HDAC3, and MCP1 in BALB/c mice in a SOCS1-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>). Expression of COX-2 is known to be increased by house dust mite extract in Nc/Nga mouse model of AD (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Karuppagounder et al., 2015</xref>). The downregulation of SOCS1 prevented AD from inducing interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2; with HDAC3, Lyn, and SOCS1 in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>). It also prevented AD from increasing &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity, serum IgE level, and the amount of histamine released in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed increased expression levels of SOCS1 and MIP-2 by AD in BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). The downregulation of SOCS1 prevented AD from inducing epidermal hyperplasia and lymphocytes infiltration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). It also increased the expression of miR-122a-5p in qRT-PCR analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). Therefore, miR-122a-5p and SOCS1 might form a negative feedback loop. The downregulation of SOCS1 prevented AD from increasing the number of degranulated MCs (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A,B</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that SOCS1 might mediate AD.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>FIGURE 6</label><caption><p>Suppressor of cytokine signaling 1 (SOCS1) is necessary for DNCB-induced AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Skin tissue lysates of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were subjected to miRNA array analysis. <bold>(B)</bold> Shows the experimental time line to determine the effect of MIP-2 on AD (lower). Upper figure shows the effect of SOCS1 on clinical symptoms associated with AD. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(C)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to western blot or immunoprecipitation by employing the indicated antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml). Tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse injected with scr. following the induction of AD was also immunoprecipitated with isotype-matched IgG antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml). <bold>(D)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assays (left). Sera of BALB/c mice were employed for the determination of the amount of histamine released (middle) and IgE level (right). <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>FIGURE 7</label><caption><p>SOCS1 regulates the expression of miR-122a-5p and MIP-2. <bold>(A)</bold> Immunohistochemical staining by employing the indicated antibody was performed. Scale bar represents 10 &#x003bc;m. Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were isolated at the time of sacrifice and were also subjected to H&#x00026;E staining. Toluidine blue staining was performed to determine the number of degranulated mast cells. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. <bold>(B)</bold> Tissue lysates from mouse of each experimental group were subjected to qRT-PCR analysis. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. The number of degranulated mast cells was also determined. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. Scale bars represent 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g007"/></fig></sec><sec><title>miR-122a-5p Mimic Attenuates Atopic Dermatitis by Regulating the Expression of Hallmarks of Allergic Inflammation Such as SOCS1</title><p>Since the downregulation of SOCS1 increased the expression of miR-122a-5p (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>), the effect of miR-122a-5p, a potential regulator of SOCS1, on AD was examined. The miR-122a-5p mimic attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>). It also prevented DNCB from increasing &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity, serum IgE level, and the amount of histamine released in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from increasing the expression of SOCS1 at the transcriptional level (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). It also prevented DNCB from increasing the expression levels of SOCS1, MIP-2, COX-2, HDAC3, MCP1 in skin tissue (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>, upper left), and MCs isolated from the skin tissue of BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>, upper right). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from inducing interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x003b2; with HDAC3, Lyn, and SOCS1 in the skin tissue of BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>, lower). Immunohistochemical staining showed that miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from increasing the expression levels of SOCS1 and MIP-2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from inducing epidermal hyperplasia and lymphocytes infiltration (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). It also prevented DNCB from increasing the number of degranulated MCs in BALB/c mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that miR-122a-5p can attenuate AD by regulating the expression of hallmarks of allergic inflammation such as SOCS1.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>FIGURE 8</label><caption><p>miR-122a-5p mimic inhibits DNCB-induced AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Shows the experimental time line to determine the effect of miR-122a-5p mimic on AD (upper). Lower figure shows the effect of miR-122a-5p mimic on clinical symptoms associated with AD. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(B)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assays (left). Sera of BALB/c mice were employed for the determination of histamine release (middle) and IgE level (right). <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(C)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to qRT-PCR analysis. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(D)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to western blot analysis (upper) or immunoprecipitation (lower) by employing the indicated antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml). Mast cell lysates from the skin tissue of the mice of each experimental group were also subjected to western blot analysis (upper right). Tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse injected with control (ctrl.) mimic following the induction of AD by DNCB were immunoprecipitated with isotype-matched IgG antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>FIGURE 9</label><caption><p>miR-122a-5p mimic negatively regulates the expression of SOCS1, MIP-2, and the number of degranulated mast cells. <bold>(A)</bold> Immunohistochemical staining by employing the indicated antibody was performed. Scale bar represents 100 &#x003bc;m. H&#x00026;E staining was also performed. <bold>(B)</bold> Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were isolated at the time of sacrifice and were subjected to toluidine blue staining to determine the number of degranulated mast cells. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. Scale bar represents 100 &#x003bc;m. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g009"/></fig></sec><sec><title>CXCL13 Is Necessary for DNCB-Induced Atopic Dermatitis and Anaphylaxis</title><p>Since SOCS1 mediated AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>), we attempted to identify cytokines/chemokines regulated by SOCS1. For this, cytokine array analysis was performed by employing the sera of BALB/c mice under AD without or with siSOCS1 injection. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression of CXCL13 in the sera of BALB/c mice in a SOCS1-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>). We next examined the effect of CXCL13 on AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B</xref>). The downregulation of CXCL13 attenuated the clinical symptoms associated with AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10C</xref>), prevented DNCB from increasing &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10D</xref>), and prevented DNCB from increasing serum PGE2 level, serum IgE level, and the amount of histamine released in BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10E</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of CD163, SOCS1, MIP-2, COX-2, HDAC3, COX-2, and MCP1 but decreased the expression of iNOS in a CXCL13-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10F</xref>). The downregulation of CXCL13 prevented DNCB from inducing interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x000df; with HDAC3, Lyn, and SOCS1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10F</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed that AD increased the expression of CD163 while decreasing the expression of iNOS in a CXCL13-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A</xref>). Atopic dermatitis increased the number of degranulated MCs in a CXCL13-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11B</xref>). Inducible nitric oxide synthase and CD163 are markers of M2 and M1 macrophages, respectively. It is probable that AD is accompanied by the activation of M2 macrophages. Since AD displayed molecular features of anaphylaxis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>), the effect of CXCL13 on PCA was also examined. The downregulation of CXCL13 prevented the antigen (DNP-HSA) from increasing vascular permeability (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12A</xref>) and &#x000df;&#x02013;hexosaminidase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12B</xref>) in a mouse model of PCA. The downregulation of CXCL13 prevented the antigen from increasing the expression of hallmarks of allergic inflammation and interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x000df; with HDAC3, Lyn, and SOCS1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12C</xref>). Taken together, these results suggest that CXCL13 may mediate AD and anaphylaxis by regulating the activation of MCs along with macrophages.</p><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>FIGURE 10</label><caption><p>Chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 13 (CXCL13) is necessary for DNCB-induced AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Serum of BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was subjected to cytokine array analyses. Serum was obtained at the time of sacrifice. <bold>(B)</bold> Shows the experimental time line to determine the effect of CXCL13 on AD. (<bold>C</bold>) At the indicated day after the induction of AD, clinical scores of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were determined. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(D)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assays. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(E)</bold> Sera of mice of each experimental group were employed for the determination of PGE2 level, IgE level, and the amount of histamine released. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. <bold>(F)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to western blot analysis and immunoprecipitation by employing the indicated antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>FIGURE 11</label><caption><p>DNCB-induced AD regulates the expression of markers of activated macrophages. <bold>(A)</bold> Immunohistochemical staining by employing the indicated antibody was performed. Scale bar represents 100 &#x003bc;m. Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were isolated at the time of sacrifice and were also subjected to H&#x00026;E staining. <bold>(B)</bold> Toluidine blue staining was performed to determine the number of degranulated mast cells. Closed triangle represents degranulated mast cells. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="float"><label>FIGURE 12</label><caption><p>CXCL13 mediates passive cutaneous anaphylaxis. <bold>(A)</bold> Passive cutaneous anaphylaxis was performed as described. After 1 h of Evans blue solution injection, the dye was eluted from the ear in 700 &#x003bc;l of formamide at 63&#x000b0;C. The absorbance was measured at 620 nm. Representative images from four animals of each experimental group are shown. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(B)</bold> Ear tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse of each experimental group were subjected to &#x003b2;-hexosaminidase activity assay. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(C)</bold> Same as <bold>(B)</bold> except that western blot and immunoprecipitation were performed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g012"/></fig></sec><sec><title>miR-122a-5p&#x02013;SOCS1 Axis Regulates Th1/Th2 and Treg Response During Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>The hUC-MSCs can reduce ovalbumin (OVA)-induced allergic inflammation. This effect might be mediated by regulatory T (Treg) cells (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al., 2017</xref>). Human mesenchymal stem cells (HUMSCs) can reduce neutrophil airway inflammation by downregulating neutrophil chemokine production and by modulating T-cell responses (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Hong et al., 2017</xref>). The AdMSCs are known to activate Treg cells. The activation of Treg cells involves secretion of PGE2 and TGF-&#x000df; by AdMSCs (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Cho et al., 2014</xref>). The HUMSCs can also increase Treg cells via heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2013</xref>). Also, GATA-3 and ROR&#x003b3;t (transcription factors for Th2 and Th17 cell differentiation, respectively) determine the phenotype of asthmatic airway inflammation (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ano et al., 2013</xref>). It has been reported that OVA-exposed ROR&#x003b3;t-overexpressing mice display higher expression of MIP-2 than wild type mice (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ano et al., 2013</xref>). These reports led us to hypothesize that AdMSCs might attenuate AD by regulating T cell responses. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of T-bet and GATA-3 but decreased the expression of Foxp3 in BALB/c mouse, in an SOCS1-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented AD from regulating the expression of T-bet, GATA-3, and Foxp3 in BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13D</xref>). Also, T-bet and GATA-3 are transcriptional factors of Th1 cells and Th2 cells, respectively. The protein Foxp3 is a specific transcriptional factor of Treg cells. Tumor necrosis factor-&#x003b1; and IFN&#x003b3; are Th1 cytokines. The interleukins IL-4, IL-5, IL-6, and IL-13 are Th2 cytokines. In addition to this, IL-17 represents Th17 cells. Atopic dermatitis increased the expression levels of IL-4, IL-13, IL-6, IL-17, IFN&#x003b3;, and TNF&#x003b1; but decreased the expression of IL-10 in BALB/c mouse, in an SOCS1-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13B</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from increasing the expression of IL-4, IL-13, IL-6, IL-17, IFN&#x003b3;, and TNF&#x003b1; (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13E</xref>). Since AD increased the expression of IL-17, it would be necessary to examine the effect of AD on the expression of ROR&#x003b3;T, a specific transcription factor of Th17 cells. Atopic dermatitis decreased the expression of IL-10 in BALB/c mouse in an SOCS1-dependent manner (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13B</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented DNCB from decreasing the expression of IL-10 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13E</xref>). Anti-IL-10 can block the expansion of Treg cells by myeloid-derived suppressor cells, and IL-10 induces Treg response and attenuates rheumatoid inflammation (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2018</xref>). Atopic dermatitis, in an SOCS1-dependent manner, decreased the expression of iNOS while increasing the expression of CD163 in BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed that SOCS1 was necessary for the expression regulation of CD163 and iNOS in mouse model of AD (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13C</xref>). The miR-122a-5p mimic prevented AD from regulating the expression of iNOS and CD163 in BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13D</xref>). It is probable that IL-10 might regulate the expression of CD163 and iNOS in BALB/c mice. Taken together, these results suggest that AD can induce Th1 and Th2 response while suppressing the Treg response in a SOCS1-dependent manner.</p><fig id="F13" position="float"><label>FIGURE 13</label><caption><p>miR-122a-5p-SOCS1 negative feedback loop regulates TH1/TH2 and regulatory T (Treg) response during AD. <bold>(A,D)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to western blot analysis. <bold>(C)</bold> Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were subjected to immunohistochemical staining. Scale bar represents 100 &#x003bc;m. <bold>(B,E)</bold> Tissue lysates from the mice of each experimental group were subjected to qRT-PCR analysis.<sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g013"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Mast Cell Activation of Macrophages Occurs in Atopic Dermatitis</title><p>Since AD was accompanied by the activation of macrophages (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13A,C</xref>), we examined the possibility of cellular interactions between MCs and macrophages in AD. We hypothesized that soluble factors of MCs might activate macrophages. When the conditioned medium of MCs isolated from an AD-induced BALB/c mouse was added to macrophages isolated from a BALB/c mouse, it increased the expression levels of CD163 and hallmarks of allergic inflammation while decreasing the expression of iNOS in macrophages (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>). The conditioned medium of MCs isolated from an AD-induced BALB/c mouse showed higher levels of PGE2 and histamine released than the conditioned medium of MCs isolated from a BALB/c mouse or MCs isolated from an AD-induced BALB/c mouse injected with miR-122a-5p mimic (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>, right). When the conditioned medium of MCs isolated from an AD-induced BALB/c mouse was added to RBL2H3 cells, it increased the expression levels of hallmarks of allergic inflammation, induced interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x000df; with HDAC3, SOCS1, and Lyn (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14B</xref>), and increased &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14C</xref>). However, miR-122a-5p mimic prevented the conditioned medium of AD-activated MCs from activating macrophages and inducing features of AD (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A&#x02013;C</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining showed that miR-122a-5p mimic prevented AD from regulating the expression of CD163 and iNOS in a BALB/c mouse (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14D</xref>).</p><fig id="F14" position="float"><label>FIGURE 14</label><caption><p>Mast cell activation of macrophages occurs in AD. <bold>(A)</bold> Skin mast cells were isolated from BALB/c mice of each experimental group as described. The conditioned medium of mast cells isolated from BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was added to lung macrophages for 8 h, followed by western blot analysis (left). The conditioned medium of mast cells isolated from BALB/c mouse of each experimental group was subjected to PGE2 level assays and histamine release assays (right). <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005. C.M., conditioned medium. <bold>(B)</bold> Same as <bold>(A)</bold> except that rat basophilic leukemia cells, equivalent of mouse mast cells, were employed. Western blot and immunoprecipitation were performed. Tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse injected with ctrl. mimic following the induction of AD by DNCB were immunoprecipitated with isotype-matched IgG antibody (2 &#x003bc;g/ml). <bold>(C)</bold> Same as <bold>(B)</bold> except that &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assays were performed. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(D)</bold> Skin tissues of BALB/c mice of each experimental group were subjected to immunohistochemical staining. Scale bar represents 100 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g014"/></fig><p>These results indicate that there are cellular interactions during AD. Further study is needed to identify cytokines/chemokines that mediate cellular interactions involving MCs and macrophages.</p></sec><sec><title>Conditioned Medium of AdMSCs Inhibits Features of Allergic Inflammation</title><p>Coculture experiments have shown that AdMSCs can attenuate AD by regulating MC degranulation and B cell function (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Shin et al., 2017</xref>). This led us to hypothesize that soluble factors in AdMSCs might attenuate AD. The conditioned medium of AdMSCs, but not that of HDFs, prevented the antigen from increasing &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity in RBL2H3 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15A</xref>). It also prevented the antigen from increasing the PGE2 level and the amount of histamine in the conditioned medium of RBL2H3 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15B</xref>). The conditioned medium of AdMSCs, but not that of HDFs, prevented the antigen from increasing the expression levels of hallmarks of allergic inflammation. It also prevented the antigen from inducing interactions of Fc&#x1d700;RI&#x000df; with HDAC3, SOCS1, and Lyn in RBL2H3 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15C</xref>). The conditioned medium of AdMSCs, but not that of HDFs, prevented the antigen from increasing vascular permeability and &#x000df;&#x02013;hexosaminidase activity (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15D</xref>). It also prevented the antigen from increasing the expression of hallmarks of allergic inflammation and CD163 while preventing the antigen from decreasing the expression of iNOS in a mouse model of PCA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">15E</xref>). The conditioned medium of AdMSCs displayed higher expression levels of various cytokines, such as MCP1, CCL5, IL-6, and IL-8 than those seen in the conditioned medium of HDFs (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1A</xref>). The conditioned medium of AdMSCs, but not the conditioned medium of HDFs, prevented the antigen from increasing the expression of cytokines such as IL-7, MCP1, CXCL12, IL-27, and macrophage colony stimulating factor (M-CSF) in IgE-sensitized RBL2H3 cells (Supplementary Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1B</xref>). Thus, secreted cytokines/chemokines in the conditioned medium of AdMSCs might have acted as negative regulators of AD.</p><fig id="F15" position="float"><label>FIGURE 15</label><caption><p>The conditioned medium of AdMSCs inhibits the features of allergic inflammation. <bold>(A)</bold> The IgE (100 ng/ml)-sensitized RBL2H3 cells were treated without or with the conditioned medium of HDFs or AdMSCs for 48 h, followed by stimulation with DNP-HSA (100 ng/ml) for 1 h. The &#x000df;-hexosaminidase activity assays were performed. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(B)</bold> Same as <bold>(A)</bold> except that PGE2 level and the amount of histamine released were determined by using the conditioned medium of RBL2H3 cells. <sup>&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005. <bold>(C)</bold> The IgE (100 ng/ml)-sensitized RBL2H3 cells were treated without or with the conditioned medium of HDFs or AdMSCs for the indicated time, followed by stimulation with DNP-HSA (100 ng/ml) for 1 h. Western blot was performed. For immunoprecipitation, lysates from RBL2H3 cells treated without or with conditioned medium for 48 h were employed. <bold>(D)</bold> BALB/c mice were given an intradermal injection of IgE (0.5 &#x003bc;g/kg) and intravenous injection of the conditioned medium of HDFs or AdMSCs (each at 200 &#x003bc;l/mouse). Representative images from four animals of each experimental group are shown. Ear tissue lysates from BALB/c mouse of each experimental group were subjected to &#x003b2;-hexosaminidase activity assays. <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005; <sup>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005. <bold>(E)</bold> Ear tissue lysates were subjected to western blot analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fphar-09-01175-g015"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results showed that AdMSCs prevented AD from increasing the serum PGE2 level. The prostaglandin PGE2 can induce IL-22 from T cells through its receptors such as the prostanoid receptors EP2 and EP4 (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Robb et al., 2018</xref>). Selective deletion of EP4 in T cells limits atopic-like skin inflammation (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Robb et al., 2018</xref>). The interleukin IL-22 plays important pathogenic roles in the initiation and development of AD, in part through the induction of keratinocyte production of type 2 cytokines and activation of the gastrin-releasing peptide (GRP)/GRPR pathway (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Lou et al., 2017</xref>). However, the effect of AdMSCs on AD and the mechanism of anti-atopic effect by AdMSCs have not been investigated extensively.</p><p>Mast cell activation involves increased expression of CCL5 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Oskeritzian et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2016</xref>). The Asian AD phenotype presents increased hyperplasia, parakeratosis, higher TH17 activation, and a strong TH2 component (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Noda et al., 2015</xref>). Allergic response to grass pollen involves increased expression of MIP-1&#x003b2; (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Leaker et al., 2017</xref>). The interleukins IL-17 and IL-5 are known to contribute to pathologic changes in skin structure and barrier functions as well as immune dysregulation in AD (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Purushothaman et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, IL-17 and IL-5 represent TH17 cytokine and TH2 cytokine, respectively. The high molecular weight form of hyaluronic acid (HA) can reduce skin lesions in Nc/Nga mice treated with DNFB and decrease the expression levels of MIP-2, Sprr-2a, and serum IgE (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2008</xref>). We showed that expression levels of cytokines, such as IL-5, IL-17, CCL5, MIP-1&#x000df; (CCL4), and MIP-2, were increased by DNCB and downregulated by AdMSCs, but not by HDFs, in a mouse model of AD. In comparison with cytokines, such as IL-5, IL-17, CCL5, and MIP-1&#x000df;, the functional role of MIP-2 in AD has not been studied extensively yet.</p><p>The miRNA precursor miR-146a can inhibit chronic skin inflammation by decreasing the expression levels of IFN-&#x003b3;, CCL5, and CCL8 in the skin (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Rebane et al., 2014</xref>). Keratinocytes of patients with AD show increased IFN-&#x003b3;-induced apoptosis compared to keratinocytes from healthy subjects. They also show higher expression levels of CCL5 and CCL8 than healthy subjects (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Rebane et al., 2012</xref>). Also, miR-143 can suppress IL-13 activity and inflammation by targeting IL-13R&#x003b1;1 in epidermal keratinocytes (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2016</xref>). In addition to this, miR-155 is over-expressed in patients with AD. It might be involved in AD pathogenesis by modulating differentiation and function of Th17 cells (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The miRNA miR-122a-5p that is negatively regulated by MIP-2 in a mouse model of AD is known to form a negative feedback loop with SOCS1, and it regulates allergic inflammation such as anaphylaxis (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Noh et al., 2017</xref>). Allergen-induced airway inflammation is regulated by the upregulation of SOCS1 (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Dharajiya et al., 2009</xref>). Numbers of circulating CD4 <sup>+</sup>CXCR5 <sup>+</sup>ICOS <sup>+</sup>PD-1 <sup>+</sup> T<sub>FH</sub>-like cells are significantly increased in children with AD when compared with healthy controls (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Szab&#x000f3; et al., 2017</xref>). Chemokine (C-X-C motif) receptor 5 (CXCR5) is a receptor for CXCL13. The stimulation of Fc&#x1d700;RI increases the numbers of macrophages expressing histamine receptor 1 (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Novak et al., 2013</xref>). The numbers of CD163 (+) cells in lesional skin of AD patients are larger than those seen in normal skin (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2015</xref>). These reports suggest the involvement of activated macrophages in AD. Our results showed that AD increased the expression of CD163 while decreasing the expression of iNOS in a SOCS1-dependent manner. We showed that CXCL13, an SOCS1-regulated cytokine, was necessary for the expression regulation of CD163 and iNOS.</p><p>The inhibition of allergic reactions is accompanied by increased numbers of CD4 (+) Foxp3 (+) T cells (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2015</xref>). This suggests that Treg cells play an inhibitory role in AD. Our results showed that AD decreased the expression of Foxp3 in a SOCS1-dependent manner. Murine AdMSCs reduce allergic airway responsiveness, expression levels of lgE and IL-17F (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), as well as increase the serum levels of Foxp3, and the percentage of CD4 (+) CD25 (+) Foxp3 (+) Treg cells in the spleen (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al., 2018</xref>). It will be necessary to examine the effects of AdMSCs on the activation of Treg responses in a mouse model of AD.</p><p>Stem cell therapy has shown therapeutic benefits in immune modulation and tissue remodeling (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">van den Akker et al., 2013</xref>). However, the survival time of implanted cells is short. This greatly impairs the therapeutic effect of MSCs (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chimenti et al., 2010</xref>). In addition, transplantation of MSCs into normal tissues may cause tumor formation (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Sell, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Recent reports have suggested that therapeutic effects of stem cells are due to factors such as cytokines, microRNAs, and exosomes, which are secreted by stem cells (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kay et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Palomares et al., 2018</xref>). The AdMSCs expressing inducible protein-10 (IP-10) reduce melanoma tumor growth and lung metastasis (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mirzaei et al., 2018</xref>). The conditioned medium of AdMSCs can promote endometrial cancer growth and invasion (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2018</xref>). These reports suggest that the conditioned medium of AdMSCs may attenuate AD by regulating cellular interactions. Our results showed that the conditioned medium of AdMSCs inhibited features of allergic inflammations.</p><p>Exosomes of AdMSCs can regulate intercellular communication in pathological processes of the skin (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). The AdMSCs-exosomes can significantly decrease the expression levels of various inflammatory cytokines such as IL-4, IL-23, IL-31, and TNF-&#x003b1; in AD skin lesions of Nc/Nga mice (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Cho et al., 2018</xref>). Further studies are needed to examine the effect of GW4869, an inhibitor of exosomes formation, on anti-allergic effects by the conditioned medium of AdMSCs.</p><p>In summary, AdMSCs can attenuate AD by targeting MIP-2, which in turn regulates the expression of miR-122a-5p, a negative regulator of SOCS1. In addition to this, SOCS1 regulates the expression of CXCL13. Also, SOCS1 and CXCL13 are necessary for the activation of macrophages and regulation of T cells responses during AD. Experiments employing the conditioned medium demonstrate that there are cellular interactions during AD and the role of soluble factors of AdMSCs in regulating allergic inflammation. Thus, employing targets of AdMSCs such as MIP-2 might offer a valuable strategy to develop anti-atopic therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MK, S-HL, and DJ designed the study. MK, YKw, YP, YKi, and S-HL performed the experiments and analyzed the data. HJ, H-KL, and DJ planned the projects and supervised the experiments. DJ wrote the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>S-HL and H-KL were employed by EHL-BIO company. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by National Research Foundation Grants (2017R1A2A2A05001029 and 2017M3A9G7072417), a grant from the BK21 plus program. This research was supported by &#x0201c;The Project of Conversion by the Past R&#x00026;D Results&#x0201d; through the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy (MOTIE) (N0002477, 2017). This work was also supported by a grant from the Kangwon National University (520170495).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org/">http://www.targetscan.org/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn02"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pictar.mdc-berlin.de/">http://pictar.mdc-berlin.de/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="fn03"><label>3</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mirdb.org/">http://mirdb.org/</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2018.01175/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fphar.2018.01175/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>(A) Cytokine array analysis employing the conditioned medium of AdMSCs and HDFs was performed. <bold>(B)</bold> The IgE (100 ng/ml)-sensitized RBL2H3 cells were treated without or with the conditioned medium of HDFs or AdMSCs for 48 h, followed by stimulation with DNP-HSA (100 ng/ml) for 1 h. The conditioned medium of IgE-sensitized RBL2H3 cells without antigen stimulation (DNP-HSA) was also subjected to cytokine array analysis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image_1.jpeg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahbarghazi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslani</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyhanmanesh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Contributory anti-inflammatory effects of mesenchymal stem cells, not conditioned media, on ovalbumin-induced asthmatic changes in male rats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Inflammation</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>1960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1971</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10753-016-0431-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27590236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27590236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morishima</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yageta</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Transcription factors GATA-3 and ROR&#x003b3;t are important for determining the phenotype of allergic airway inflammation in a murine model of asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>190</volume>
<fpage>1056</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1065</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1202386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23293351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Itakura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreri</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandeel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells suppress B-cell terminal differentiation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Hematol.</italic></source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2009.01.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19375651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19375651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chimenti</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstenblith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacomello</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Relative roles of direct regeneration versus paracrine effects of human cardiosphere-derived cells transplanted into infarcted mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Circ. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>980</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.109.210682</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20110532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>Y. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Exosomes derived from human adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal stem cells alleviate atopic dermatitis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>187</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13287-018-0939-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29996938?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29996938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Adipose-derived stem cells ameliorate allergic airway inflammation by inducing regulatory T cells in a mouse model of asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mediators Inflamm.</italic></source>
<volume>2014</volume>:<issue>436476</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/436476</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25246732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25246732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>STAT3 activation by IL-6 from adipose-derived stem cells promotes endometrial carcinoma proliferation and metastasis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>500</volume>
<fpage>626</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>631</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2018.04.121</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29684351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29684351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Intratracheal administration of adipose derived mesenchymal stem cells alleviates chronic asthma in a mouse model.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Pulm. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>18</volume>:<issue>131</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12890-018-0701-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30089474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30089474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dharajiya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luxon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldogh</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Allergen challenge induces Ifng dependent GTPases in the lungs as part of a Th1 transcriptome response in a murine model of allergic asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>e8172</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008172.45</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20027288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20027288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Virtucio</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemska</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltazar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Treatment of skin inflammation with benzoxaborole phosphodiesterase inhibitors: selectivity, cellular activity, and effect on cytokines associated with skin inflammation and skin architecture changes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther.</italic></source>
<volume>358</volume>
<fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.116.232819</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27353073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27353073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The expression and regulation of interleukin-33 in human epidermal keratinocytes: a new mediator of AD and its possible signaling pathway.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Interferon Cytokine Res.</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>562</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jir.2015.0159</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27348082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duong</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arikkatt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Immunomodulation of airway epithelium cell activation by mesenchymal stromal cells ameliorates house dust mite-induced airway inflammation in mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Respir. Cell Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>624</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1165/rcmb.2014-0431OC</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25789608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25789608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014a</year>). <article-title>Transglutaminase II/microRNA-218/-181a loop regulates positive feedback relationship between allergic inflammation and tumor metastasis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>289</volume>
<fpage>29483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29505</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.603480</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25202021?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014b</year>). <article-title>Histone deacetylase-3 mediates positive feedback relationship between anaphylaxis and tumor metastasis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>289</volume>
<fpage>12126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.521245</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24619412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24619412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Docosahexaenoic acid alleviates atopic dermatitis by generating tregs and IL-10/TGF-&#x003b2;-modified macrophages via a TGF-&#x003b2;-dependent mechanism.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Invest. Dermatol.</italic></source>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>1556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1564</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2014.488</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25405323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25405323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>hMSCs suppress neutrophil-dominant airway inflammation in a murine model of asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Mol. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>:<issue>e288</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emm.2016.135</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28127050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Immunologic regulatory effects of human umbilical cord blood-derived mesenchymal stem cells in a murine ovalbumin asthma model.</article-title>
<source><italic>Clin. Exp. Allergy</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>945</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cea.12920</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28294434?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28294434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capitle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rameshwar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Tolerance-like mediated suppression by mesenchymal stem cells in patients with dust mite allergy-induced asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>1094</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2011.10.048</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22196773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22196773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karuppagounder</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thandavarayan</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitchaimani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreedhar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Afrin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Modulation of HMGB1 translocation and RAGE/NF&#x003ba;B cascade by quercetin treatment mitigates AD in NC/Nga transgenic mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Exp. Dermatol.</italic></source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/exd.12685</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25739980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25739980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahon</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells prevent allergic airway inflammation by inducing murine regulatory T cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>Allergy</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1398-9995.2010.02509.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21091718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadfoot</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccinini</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cell-conditioned medium reduces disease severity and immune responses in inflammatory arthritis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>18019</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-18144-w</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29269885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29269885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanaba</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobeyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiso</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Suppressive effects of mesenchymal stem cells in adipose tissue on allergic contact dermatitis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Dermatol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>399</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5021/ad.2017.29.4.391</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28761285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28761285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Human umbilical cord blood mesenchymal stem cell-derived PGE2 and TGF-&#x003b2;1 alleviate AD by reducing mast cell degranulation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Stem Cells</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>1254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1913</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25522163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25522163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Transglutaminase II interacts with rac1, regulates production of reactive oxygen species, expression of snail, secretion of Th2 cytokines and mediates in vitro and in vivo allergic inflammation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>1010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1022</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2009.11.017</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20004474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20004474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Histone deacetylase 3 mediates allergic skin inflammation by regulating expression of MCP1 protein.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>287</volume>
<fpage>25844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25859</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.348284</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22679019?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22679019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Hyaluronic acid targets CD44 and inhibits fcepsilonRI signaling involving PKCdelta, Rac1, ROS, and MAPK to exert anti-allergic effect.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>2537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2547</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2008.01.008</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18289679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18289679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>So</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Generation of regulatory dendritic cells and CD4 + Foxp3 + T cells by probiotics administration suppresses immune disorders.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>2159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2164</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0904055107</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20080669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>MicroRNA-26a/-26b-COX-2-MIP-2 loop regulates allergic inflammation and allergic inflammation-promoted enhanced tumorigenic and metastatic potential of cancer Cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>290</volume>
<fpage>14245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14266</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.645580</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25907560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25907560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leaker</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malkov</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogg</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruddy</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The nasal mucosal late allergic reaction to grass pollen involves type 2 inflammation (IL-5 and IL-13), the inflammasome (IL-1&#x003b2;), and complement.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mucosal Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mi.2016.74</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27677865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27677865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuan-sun</surname><given-names>Y. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Human mesenchymal stem cells elevate CD4 + CD25 + CD127low/- regulatory T cells of asthmatic patients via heme oxygenase-1.</article-title>
<source><italic>Iran. J. Allergy Asthma Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 23893806?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23893806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaeloudes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiegman</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells alleviate oxidative stress-induced mitochondrial dysfunction in the airways.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>141</volume>
<fpage>1634.e5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1645.e5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.017</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28911970?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28911970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Mesenchymal stem cells suppress lung inflammation and airway remodeling in chronic asthma rat model via PI3K/Akt signaling pathway.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Clin. Exp. Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>8958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8967</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 26464637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26464637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Exosomes as a novel pathway for regulating development and diseases of the skin.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biomed. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/br.2018.1054</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29599975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29599975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barmettler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Expression of IL-22 in the skin causes Th2-biased immunity, epidermal barrier dysfunction, and pruritus via stimulating epithelial Th2 cytokines and the GRP pathway.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>198</volume>
<fpage>2543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1600126</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28228560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28228560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>H. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>MicroRNA-155 may be involved in the pathogenesis of AD by modulating the differentiation and function of T helper type 17 (Th17) cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>Clin. Exp. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>181</volume>
<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cei.12624</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25761610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25761610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oskuee</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The therapeutic potential of human adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells producing CXCL10 in a mouse melanoma lung metastasis model.</article-title>
<source><italic>Cancer Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>419</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2018.01.029</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29331419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29331419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane-Myers</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorham</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundoc</surname><given-names>V. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Bone marrow stromal cells use TGF-beta to suppress allergic responses in a mouse model of ragweed-induced asthma.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>5652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5657</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0910720107</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20231466?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez-Fari&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ungar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Guzman Strong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The asian AD phenotype combines features of AD and psoriasis with increased TH17 polarization.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>1254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1264</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2015.08.015</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26428954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26428954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>miR-122-SOCS1-JAK2 axis regulates allergic inflammation and allergic inflammation-promoted cellular interactions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oncotarget</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>63155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.19149</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28968979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28968979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieber</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Fc&#x1d700;RI stimulation promotes the differentiation of histamine receptor 1-expressing inflammatory macrophages.</article-title>
<source><italic>Allergy</italic></source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>461</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.12109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23414213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23414213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivry</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paps</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peredo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajpal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Early activation of Th2/Th22 inflammatory and pruritogenic pathways in acute canine AD skin lesions.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Invest. Dermatol.</italic></source>
<volume>136</volume>
<fpage>1961</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1969</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jid.2016.05.117</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27342734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27342734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oskeritzian</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hait</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chumanevich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolawole</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The sphingosine-1-phosphate/sphingosine-1-phosphate receptor 2 axis regulates early airway T-cell infiltration in murine mast cell-dependent acute allergic responses.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>1008.e1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1018.e1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2014.10.044</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25512083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25512083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruzos-Cidon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrecilla</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugedo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso-Varona</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The neuroprotective effect of conditioned medium from human adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells is impaired by N-acetyl cysteine supplementation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Neurobiol.</italic></source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12035-017-0714-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28812231?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28812231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Interleukin-10 produced by myeloid-derived suppressor cells is critical for the induction of tregs and attenuation of rheumatoid inflammation in mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>3753</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-21856-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29491381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29491381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prigione</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benvenuto</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Battistini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uccelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Reciprocal interactions between human mesenchymal stem cells and gammadelta T cells or invariant natural killer T cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>Stem cells</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/stemcells.2008-0687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19096038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purushothaman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A novel catecholopyrimidine based small molecule PDE4B inhibitor suppresses inflammatory cytokines in atopic mice.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Pharmacol.</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>485</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00485</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29867490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Runnel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aab</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maslovskaja</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;ckert</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>MicroRNA-146a alleviates chronic skin inflammation in AD through suppression of innate immune responses in keratinocytes.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>836.e11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>847.e11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2014.05.022</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24996260?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24996260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aab</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baurecht</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koreck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karelson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mechanisms of IFN-&#x003b3;-induced apoptosis of human skin keratinocytes in patients with AD.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>1297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1306</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2012.02.020</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22445417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22445417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robb</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>McSorley</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Prostaglandin E2 stimulates adaptive IL-22 production and promotes allergic contact dermatitis.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</italic></source>
<volume>141</volume>
<fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.04.045</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28583370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28583370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>On the stem cell origin of cancer.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>176</volume>
<fpage>2584</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2594</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2010.091064</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20431026?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Human adipose tissue-derived mesenchymal stem cells alleviate AD via regulation of B lymphocyte maturation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oncotarget</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.13473</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27888809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27888809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szab&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e1;sp&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dajnoki</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e1;bos</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szegedi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Expansion of circulating follicular T helper cells associates with disease severity in childhood AD.</article-title>
<source><italic>Immunol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>189</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imlet.2017.04.010</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28431963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28431963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S. Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>MicroRNAs involved in asthma after mesenchymal stem cells treatment.</article-title>
<source><italic>Stem Cells Dev.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>896</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/scd.2015.0339</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27106170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27106170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbanek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaziano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piegari</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matteis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappetta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Intratracheal administration of mesenchymal stem cells modulates tachykinin system, suppresses airway remodeling and reduces airway hyperresponsiveness in an animal model.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>e0158746</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158746</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27434719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27434719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Akker</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deddens</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doevendans</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluijter</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Cardiac stem cell therapy to modulate inflammation upon myocardial infarction.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</italic></source>
<volume>1830</volume>
<fpage>2449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2458</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2012.08.026</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22975401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22975401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H. Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>MicroRNA-143 inhibits IL-13-induced dysregulation of the epidermal barrier-related proteins in skin keratinocytes via targeting to IL-13R&#x003b1;1.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Cell. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>416</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-016-2696-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27048505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27048505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>SOCS1 regulates the immune modulatory properties of mesenchymal stem cells by inhibiting nitric oxide production.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>9</volume>:<issue>e97256</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097256</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24826993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24826993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>CXCR5-overexpressing mesenchymal stromal cells exhibit enhanced homing and can decrease contact hypersensitivity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Ther.</italic></source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1447</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymthe.2017.04.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28454789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28454789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>