<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Afr J Tradit Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Afr J Tradit Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJTCAM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>African Journal of Traditional, Complementary, and Alternative Medicines</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0189-6016</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2505-0044</issn><publisher><publisher-name>African Traditional Herbal Medicine Supporters Initiative (ATHMSI)</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Nigeria</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5566141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AJTCAM-13-166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21010/ajtcam.v13i4.22</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>ETHNOBIOLOGICAL SURVEY OF PLANTS AND ANIMALS USED FOR THE TREATMENT OF ACUTE RESPIRATORY INFECTIONS IN CHILDREN OF A TRADITIONAL COMMUNITY IN THE MUNICIPALITY OF BARBALHA, CEAR&#x000c1;, BRAZIL</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>Izabel Cristina Santiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Delmondes</surname><given-names>Gyllyandeson de Ara&#x000fa;jo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>Ana Deyva Ferreira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>Enaide Soares</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Dayanne Rakelly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Figueiredo</surname><given-names>Patr&#x000ed;cia Rosane Leite</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>Dailon de Ara&#x000fa;jo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>Roseli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Menezes</surname><given-names>Irwin Rose Alencar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>Henrique Douglas Melo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kerntopf</surname><given-names>Marta Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>George Pimentel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological Chemistry, Laboratory of Molecular Chemistry and Pharmacology, Regional University of Cariri, Crato, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Public Health, State University of Cear&#x000e1;, Fortaleza, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Department of Biological Chemistry, Laboratory of Microbiology and Molecular Biology, Regional University of Cariri, Crato, Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author :</bold> Regional University of Cariri &#x02013; URCA, Crato-CE, Brazil. Cel. Antonio Luis Street, 1161, 63105-000.. <bold>E-mail:</bold><email xlink:href="pimentelprof@outlook.com">pimentelprof@outlook.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2016 Afr. J. Traditional Complementary and Alternative Medicines</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/CC-BY/4.0"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>The use of natural resources for the treatment of acute respiratory infections in children is a widespread practice within traditional communities, especially by women by being the primary caregivers. This study aimed to perform ethnobiological survey of plants and animals used for the treatment of acute respiratory infections in children of a traditional community in the municipality of Barbalha, Cear&#x000e1;, Brazil.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Methods:</title><p>It is a descriptive exploratory study with a quantitative approach, developed in Sitio Santo Antonio, in the municipality of Barbalha, Cear&#x000e1;, Brazil. As a tool for data collection, was applied a questionnaire and a semi-structured interview. Data analysis used descriptive statistics (simple and percentage rate) and the Relative Frequency of Citation.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Results:</title><p>The research included a total of 54 informants. In total, there were 38 species cited. According to the Relative Frequency of Citation the following species were the most cited: <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. (0.59), <italic>Eucalyptus globulus Labili</italic> (0.59), <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) Spreng (0.42), <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit. (0.24), <italic>Allium aescalonicum</italic> L. (0.22) and <italic>Mentha arvensis</italic> L. (0.18). Among the symptoms mentioned by the research subjects to treat the acute respiratory infections in childhood, there were: fever; cough; coughing with secretions; sore throat; hoarseness; tiredness; nasal congestion.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>It is important the knowledge about the usefulness of natural resources as alternative practices in diseases treatment, seeking to rescue popular knowledge used in the traditional community and fomenting the need to consider cultural aspects in the full practice to children&#x02019;s health care.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ethnobotany</kwd><kwd>Ethnomedicine</kwd><kwd>Acute respiratory infections</kwd><kwd>Natural products</kwd><kwd>Children&#x02019;s Health</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Acute respiratory infection (ARI) is a clinical syndrome with respiratory viruses as the most common infectious agents such as the respiratory syncytial virus or <italic>Streptococcus pneumonia</italic> and <italic>Haemophilus influenza</italic> bacterias (Rigat et al., 2013).</p><p>It is estimated that about 4 million people die from ARI annually, and the lower respiratory tract infections are responsible for 98% of these deaths, mainly affecting infants, children and the elderly population (WHO, 2014).</p><p>Thus, the ARI is a problem of contemporary public health and Brazil is one of the 15 countries with the highest number of clinical pneumonia cases in children under five years old. (Cardoso, 2010).</p><p>In the risk factors associated with higher frequencies of ARI episodes in childhood, there are low birth weight, malnutrition, poor or no breastfeeding, neglect of immunization, family of low income, and use of inappropriate clothing for the climate and the presence of smokers in the house. This highlighting that the ARI in Brazil is in the group of childhood illness (Fornazari et al., 2003; Mello et al., 2009).</p><p>Based on the epidemiological relevance of respiratory tract infections in childhood, especially in developing countries, and with prevalence and risk factors mainly related to socioeconomic variables, it is important to understand how the care process is established by mothers and/or responsible for the treatment and ARI management.</p><p>It is relevant to focus especially on traditional knowledge been reproduced and perpetuated in caring for children; the use of unconventional medicine and how these cultural medical practices are configured in the reality of contemporary traditional communities and their contributions to conventional medical practices (Raymundo, 2013).</p><p>Some studies published in the country have considered about the traditional knowledge and the influence of this culturally learned knowledge on childcare, especially addressing the mother&#x02019;s perspective in this process (Alves et al., 2003; Ichisato et al., 2001; Iserhard et al., 2009; Zanatta et al., 2007).</p><p>From the information above, it is observed that it is important to develop research that seeks to rescue established traditional knowledge by assessing the level of influence that determine health care employees in a particular community. This will enable alternatives to pharmacological treatment of high cost and foster the need to consider cultural aspects in the integral practice of health care.</p><p>In this context, this study aimed to survey the species of plants and animals used by mothers or caregivers for the treatment of acute respiratory infections (ARI) in a traditional community and to identify ways to use these flora and fauna resources.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>It is a descriptive, exploratory study with a quantitative approach developed in the Santo Antonio community, located in Arajara District, in the municipality of Barbalha (CE) in the period from May 2013 to September 2014.</p><p>Barbalha is 553 km from the state capital, Fortaleza, located specifically at latitude 7&#x000b0; 18&#x02019; 18&#x0201d; S and longitude 39&#x000b0; 18&#x02019; 7&#x0201d; W, adjacent to the Chapada do Araripe having an area of a territorial unit of 569.508 Km<sup>2</sup>. In 2013, the estimated population of the municipality of Barbalha was 57,818 inhabitants, with a population density of 97.14 (hab/km) (IBGE, 2010).</p><p>Its climate is characterized as semi-arid tropical hot, <italic>Caatinga</italic> is the predominant vegetation, although it shows areas of <italic>Cerrad&#x000e4;o</italic> and <italic>Cerrado</italic>. It is noteworthy the presence of the Araripe Geopark in the municipality of Barbalha (also found in Santana do Cariri, Nova Olinda, Crato, Juazeiro do Norte and Miss&#x000e4;o Velha).</p><p>The Geopark was established in 2006, located in the Chapada Araripe and the region of Araripe Sedimentary Complex, being the only national representative in the Global Geoparks Network (Brito et al., 2012).</p><p>In the municipality of Barbalha different communities are possible to find, the Sitio Santo Antonio community among them. The reason Santo Antonio community was chosen for data collection is because it is a traditional community, in accordance with the requirements given by the Ministry of the Environment (Brasil, 2014).</p><p>Thus, Santo Antonio community highlights with the following characteristics: it occupies, permanently or temporarily, traditional territories; it uses natural resources, conditioning it as a tool for cultural, social, religious, ancestral and economic community reproduction and it has mainly knowledge and practices originated by oral tradition (Haverroth, 2013).</p><p>The study population consisted of residents in the community, aged between 12 and 90 years old having knowledge regarding the use and management of medicinal plants and animals for the treatment of acute respiratory infections in children. The inclusion of adolescents in the sample was given by high pregnancy rates in adolescence expressed in Cear&#x000e1; state (Martins et al., 2011).</p><p>For data collection, strategies were used as the &#x0201c;rapport&#x0201d; and the composition of the sample was through the &#x0201c;snowball&#x0201d; technique (Albuquerque et al., 2010).</p><p>The instrument for data collection was the closed questionnaire for socioeconomic characterization of the research subjects. Soon after, a semi-structured interview applied, as it allows greater flexibility and is an effective tool to collect descriptive data on the individual&#x02019;s language.</p><p>To finish the composition of the sample, the criterion of saturation of answers was applied. For this study, the saturation was established where more than 50% of a group of informants did not mention different species names - compared to other respondents groups (Fontanella et al., 2011).</p><p>Descriptive statistics was used for data analysis (simple and percentage rate) and the Relative Frequency of Citation (RFC), widely used in ethnobotanical surveys (Bano et al., 2014) and obtained from the ratio: FC/N, where FC is the number of informants who mentioned species use and N is the total number of informants in the study.</p><p>It is noteworthy that during the development of the research, all the requirements of the Guidelines and Standards of Research Involving Human Beings were met, regulated by Resolution 466/12 of the National Health Council (CNS).</p><p>Therefore, in line with the ethical aspects, the research was submitted to the Research Ethics Committee of the Regional University of Cariri - URCA, located in the municipality of Crato - CE / Brazil, to its contemplation and analysis. It was approved by the CEP under number 705.497.</p></sec><sec id="sec1-3"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Characterization of the Respondents</title><p>The research included a total of 54 informants randomly divided into seven different groups, according to the order of the interviews. Groups 1 to 6 were composed of 8 respondents each, and the group 7 had 6 participants.</p><p>In the total, 44.44% of the respondents were male, and 55.56% were female. The age group with the largest representation was between 30 to 45 years old (27.78%), followed by the group of young adults (22-29 years old), representing 20.37%, and the group aged from 46 to 59 years old (20.37%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap orientation="portrait" id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Profile of informants of S&#x000ed;tio Sto. Ant&#x000f4;nio (Barbalha) &#x02013; CE.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipality</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barbalha-CE</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S&#x000ed;tio Sto. Ant&#x000f4;nio</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.56</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age Group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-21</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22-29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46-59</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60-75</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76-96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.25</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time of residence in the area</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 5 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 5 &#x0003c; 10 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 10 &#x0003c; 20 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 20 &#x0003c; 30 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 30 &#x0003c; 40 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 40 &#x0003c; 50 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 50 &#x0003c; 60 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-educated</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incomplete Elementary School</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete Elementary School</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incomplete High School</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complete High School</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community health agent</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Farmer</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retired</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-employed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commercial employee</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Manicure</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Masson</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teacher</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seller</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widow/widower</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Divorced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Regarding the residence time, it is noteworthy that most of the sample (22.22%) reported living in the area to a higher or the same period of 20 years and below 30 years, followed by those living in the area to a higher or equal period of 40 years and less than 50 years (20.37%).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Species mentioned for the treatment of symptoms and/or pathologies related to Acute Respiratory Infections (ARI) in children</title><p>Through data analysis, some plants used in Santo Antonio community for the treatment of ARI were possible to identify. It is noteworthy that although cited less of ten, some animal species have also been mentioned (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap orientation="portrait" id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>List of species used by the community for the treatment of symptoms of ARI in children.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">POPULAR NAME</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCIENTIFIC NAME</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SYMPTOM TREATED/ PATHOLOGY</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PARTS USED</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAYS OF TRADITIONAL USE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alca&#x000e7;uz</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Sore Throat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alecrim</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pectis brevipedunculata</italic> Sch. Bip.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Flu; Sinusitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Bath; Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alfavaca</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Flu; Bronchitis; Sore Throat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); mouthwash; Gargle</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alfavac&#x000e4;o</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flu; Fever; Nasal congestion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Bath in the Head</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Algod&#x000e4;o</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pneumonia; Flu; Coughing with secretions; Fever</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed; Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Juice</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Alho</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flu; Fever; Throat infection</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth (bulbils); Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Juice;Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Anador</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternanthera brasiliana</italic> (L.) Kuntze</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat; Fever</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Andu</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bronchitis; colds; Sore throat; Fever; Cough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction); Tea (infusion);Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Arruda</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Respiratory infection in general</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Bananeira</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Musa paradis&#x000ed;aca</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Inflammation of the throat; Bronchitis; Flu</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Latex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambedor; Juice</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Camar&#x000e1;</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lantana Camaia</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Flu</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Capim-santo</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cymbopogon citratus (DC.) Stapf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Carrapicho-de-Agulha</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Achyrocline satureioides</italic> (Lam.) DC.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat; Fever.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cebolinha Branca</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Allium aescalonicum</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore Throat; Coughing with secretions; Cough; Hoarseness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bulb; Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cidreira/ Erva-Cidreira</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lippia alba</italic> (M.) N.E. Br.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flu; Fever; Coughing with Secretion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Contra-Erva</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dorstenia cayapia</italic> Vell</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Bronchitis; Sore throat; Respiratory Infection in General</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Roots</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction).</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Eucalipto</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flu; Nasal congestion; Sinusitis; Fever; Cough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Inhalation</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Galinha Caipira</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gallus gallus domesticus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Flu; Nasal congestion; Cough; Sore throat; Hoarseness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lard (fat)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topic; Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gengibre</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat; Cough; Fever; Flu</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juice; Macerated;</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hortel&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mentha arvensis</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Cough; Nasal congestion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Bath; Inhalation</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Imburana/ Umburana (Mart.)J.B. Gillett</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Commiphora leptophloeos</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bronchitis; Flu; Cough; Sore throat; Hoarseness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bark</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction); Tea (infusion); Lambedor; Macerated</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Janda&#x000ed;ra</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Melipona subnitida</italic> D.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Hoarseness; Sore throat; Coughing with secretions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Honey</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Juazeiro</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ziziphos joazeiro</italic> Mart.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flu; Cough; Fever; Bronchitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Stem Bark</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Macerated</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lim&#x000e4;o</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Burm. f.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Flu; Cough; Sore Throat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Fruit; Bark (fruit)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juice; Tea (infusion); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Maca&#x000fa;ba</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acrocomia aculeata</italic> (J.) Lodd.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Flu; Coughing with secretions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Bark</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juice; Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Malva do Reino</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) Spreng</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough; Sore throat; Bronchitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Juice; Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mam&#x000e4;o/ Mamoeiro</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tiredness; Fever</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nectar; Flower; Sprout</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambedor; Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mandacaru</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cereus jamacaru</italic> DC.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Cough; Bronchitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bark; Root; Branches</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Tea (decoction); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mangueira</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coughing with secretions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Juice; Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mastruz</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Cough; Coughing with secretions; Pneumonia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pequi</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Caryocar coriaceum</italic> Wittm.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat; Bronchitis; Coughing with secretions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambedor; Oil (Ingestion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Piracuru</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bryophyllumpinnatum</italic> (L.) Oken</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (infusion); Lambedor; Juice</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Quina-Quina</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Coutarea hexandra</italic> (J.) K. Schum.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; The flu; Cough; Sinusitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bark</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction); Lambedor</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Retirante</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acanthospermum hispidum</italic> DC.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Coughing with secretions; Bronchitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf; Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction); Tea (infusion)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Rom&#x000e4;</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit (Bark)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouthwash; Gargle</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Tejua&#x000e7;u/ Tei&#x000fa;/ Teju</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tupinambis merianae</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sore throat; Cough with secretion; Flu; Hoarseness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lard(fat)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Friction (Topic)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Urucu</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bixa orellana</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Tiredness; Flu; Bronchitis; Pharyngitis; Coughing with secretion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed; Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lambedor; Macerated; Tea (decoction)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Vassourinha</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever; Cough; Bronchitis; Sore throat</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chanana</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Turnera subulata</italic> Sm.</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root; Leaf</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tea (decoction); Tea (infusion); Lambedor</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The most common form of traditional use were teas, mentioned 32 times, with two preparation methods: by decoction and infusion. Lambedores (home-made syrups) were also noteworthy associated with the use of plant species by 20 times.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Most frequently cited species by the respondents according to the Relative Frequency Citation (RFC) for ARI treatment</title><p>A significant number of respondents mentioned more than one species by an injury. The species with the highest RFC were all plants species.</p><p>The following species have the highest number of citations: <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. (0.59); <italic>Eucalyptus globulus Labill</italic> (0.59); <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) <italic>Spreng</italic> (0.42); <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit. (0.24); <italic>Allium aescalonicum</italic> L. (0.22); <italic>Mentha arvensis</italic> L. (0.18), all mentioned 32, 32, 23, 13, 12 and 10 times, respectively.</p><p>Also, the species <italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp. (0.16); <italic>Punica granatum</italic> L. (0.16) and <italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L. (0.14) were mentioned 9, 9 and 8 times, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap orientation="portrait" id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Relative frequency of citation - RFC of mentioned species by the community for the treatment of ARI in children.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RFC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pectis brevipedunculata</italic> Sch. Bip.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Ocimum basilicum</bold></italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.59</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Hyptis suaveolens</bold></italic> (L.) Poit.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.24</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Allium sativum</bold></italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.03</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternanthera brasiliana</italic> (L.) Kuntze</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Millsp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Musa paradis&#x000ed;aca</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lantana Camaia</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC.) Stapf</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Achyrocline satureioides</italic> (Lam.) DC.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Allium aescalonicum</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lippia alba</italic> (M.) N.E. Br.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dorstenia cayapia</italic> Vell</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Eucalyptus globulus Labili</bold></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.59</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Gallus gallus domesticus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Mentha arvensis</bold></italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.18</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Commiphora leptophloeos</italic> (Mart.) J.B. Gillett</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Melipona subnitida</italic> D.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ziziphos joazeiro</italic> Mart.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Burm. f.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acrocomia aculeata</italic> (J.) Lodd.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic><bold>Plectranthus amboinicus</bold></italic><bold>(L.) Spreng</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.42</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cereus jamacaru</italic> DC.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">003</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Caryocar coriaceum</italic> Wittm.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic> (L.) Oken</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Coutarea hexandra</italic> (J.) K. Schum.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acanthospermum hispidum</italic> DC.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tupinambis merianae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bixa orellana</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Turnera subulata</italic> Sm.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Considering the RFC, the <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. and <italic>Eucalyptus globulus Labill</italic> were the plant species most frequently cited by respondents for the treatment of ARI, as well as some isolated symptoms. We initially considered the species <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L, or as is commonly known &#x0201c;basil&#x0201d;.</p><p>In the case of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L., it is a plant belonging to the Lamiaceae family and is widely used by traditional medicine, mainly due to its essential oils, with methyl chavicol, linalool, geranial and estragol as the major constituents (Veloso et al., 2014).</p><p>Research participants indicate that the <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. was effective for cough, flu in general, bronchitis and sore throat. This information is in line with other research, such as Albertasse et al. (2010).</p><p>In the ethnobotanical study of Ribeiro et al. (2014) the species was mentioned as effective for the treatment of &#x0201c;flu&#x0201d;, in Vendr&#x000fa;sculo et al. (2006) research, the plant is cited by respondents as useful for a &#x0201c;sore throat&#x0201d;.</p><p>Residents of Santo Antonio community reported that <italic>Eucalyptus globulus Labill</italic> is the plant used for the treatment and management of flu; nasal congestion; sinusitis; fever and cough.</p><p>According to Lorenzi et al. (2008), eucalyptus is a large tree, with opposite leathery leaves and operculate fruits. The composition of the essential oil of eucalyptus has a-Pinene; &#x003b2;-myrcene; a-phellandrene; &#x003b1;-terpinene; Limonene; 1,8-Cineole &#x003b2;-Ocimene; &#x003a5; -Terpinene; p-Cymene; Epoxy linalool, Linalool oxide, linalool Menthol, among others.</p><p>Its medicinal properties are often mentioned in to in biopanning studies and ethnobiological surveys, particularly for disorders related to human respiratory tract been indicated as an alternative to antibiotic treatment (Pereira, 2014).</p><p>The most used parts of the plant species were leaves, mentioned 27 times, followed by the roots cited seven times, while for animal species of commonly used parts for acute respiratory infections in children were fat (lard) mentioned twice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Parts of plants commonly used by the community for the treatment of acute respiratory infections in children.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="AJTCAM-13-166-g001"/></fig><p>In this context, the findings of Teklay et al. (2013) highlights in a study developed in Kilte district Awulaelo, Ethiopia, Eucalyptus globulus Labill as the species with higher citations for medicinal use of practical applications, with the antitussive as the actions brought by the research.</p><p>The second most cited species for this research was <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) <italic>Spreng</italic>, or <italic>malva-do-reino</italic>. The species of Plectranthus (Lamiaceae) have wide use in traditional medicine in Africa, America, Oceania, and Asia (Carneiro et al., 2010)</p><p>In this sense, the <italic>malva-do-reino</italic> is characterized by being &#x0201c;a perennial, erect, very aromatic herb [&#x02026;] with deltoid-ovate leaves, with truncated base and jagged, brittle margins, and prominent veins on the back&#x0201d; (Lorenzi et al., 2008)</p><p>Essential oils of <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) Spreng are composed by Copaene; &#x003b2;-Bourboneno; trans-caryophyllene; Humulene; Germacrene-D; Valencene; &#x003b2;-Bisabolene &#x00394;-Cadinene and Caryophyllene oxide (Bandeira et al., 2011).</p><p>In the study by Torres et al. (2005) the author states that the species is used to combat bronchitis and its use is consistent for the treatment of diseases related to the respiratory system, since in its essential oil there is thymol and carvacrol antimicrobial properties.</p><p>In Rodrigues et al. (2014) <italic>malva-do-reino</italic> is also among the most cited species, with ethnopharmacological signs for the medical treatment of a cough, phlegm in the chest, bronchitis and flu.</p><p>The third more cited species for this research was the <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit., characterized by being an annual subshrub, erect, branched, strongly aromatic, with foursquare stalks. It has opposite leaves, membranous, pubescent glands [&#x02026;] and used in home-made medicine&#x0201d; (Lorenzi et al., 2008).</p><p>Regarding the essential oils of the species <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit, the following components are highlighted: Sabinene, limonene, bicyclogermacrene, &#x003b2;-phellandrene and 1.8-cineol as the main constituents, although its composition depends on the geographic region where the species was collected (Azevedo et al., 2001).</p><p>In this context, Jesus et al. (2009) mentions that <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit has antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity, highlighting also its antimicrobial activity, according to pharmacological tests (Nantitanon et al., 2007).</p><p>This plant species, popularly known as basil, has a broad application in rustic medicine and according to Morais et al. (2005). &#x0201c;The presence of high cineole content in the essential oil of the leaves allows its use for flu&#x0201d;.</p><p>This information is consistent with the respondents&#x02019; statements, mentioning the use of the species to treat symptoms in children such as flu, fever, and nasal congestion.</p><p>The findings of the ethnobotanical survey conducted by Roque et al. (2010) of plants with medicinal properties of the <italic>caatinga</italic> showed that the use of <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit is associated with the treatment of flu and runny nose/nasal congestion.</p><p>Other studies, such as Kala et al. (2005) where data collection occurred in the Himalayas, India region, the species was indicated to treat colds in general and coughs. Other studies published internationally also list it as the species most commonly used for therapeutic purposes (Cavalcanti et al., 2013; Kabir et al., 2014).</p><p>Within the Brazilian public health, specifically considering the Unified Health System, the National Policy on Integrative and Complementary Practices (PNPIC), collaborates with encouragement for the inclusion and the rational use of natural resources in the treatment of various diseases (Brasil, 2006).</p><p>Thus, encouraging the use of these natural resources, including a symptomatic approach to the ARI has shown rapid growth in the last two decades (Barros, 2006).</p><p>With the gradual implementation of the National Policy on Integrative and Complementary Practices (PNPCI) and the publication of ethnobotanical surveys, as well as bioprospecting research, it is believed that the tendency is that these cultural aspects come to be more valued, especially in primary care, featuring a more rational use of natural resources with medicinal properties, including for the treatment of ARI.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec1-4"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study showed that 38 species were cited for the treatment of Acute Respiratory Infections (ARI) in children. Their effects were under a range of symptoms - such as fever, cough, cough with secretion, sore throat, hoarseness, fatigue and nasal congestion - and they would act effectively on the specific respiratory diseases such as pharyngitis; bronchitis and pneumonia.</p><p>Considering a significant number of respondents mentioning more than one kind of problem, the Relative Frequency of Citation (RFC) was calculated. For the treatment of ARI in children, the most cited species were all vegetables: <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. (0.59); <italic>Eucalyptus globulus Labill</italic> (0.59); <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (L.) Spreng (0.42); <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit. (0.24); <italic>Allium aescalonicum</italic> L. (0.22) and <italic>Mentha arvensis</italic> L. (0.18).</p><p>It is noteworthy that the results obtained are an important contribution to traditional medicine since they reaffirm the natural resource used by different generations of the community, registering and allowing the reproduction of legitimate knowledge. Also, they are the interests of future studies in the area of bioprospecting, resulting in the discovery of new bioactive compounds to be used for treating various childhood illnesses.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>To the community of Sitio Sto. Antonio (Barbalha - CE/ Brasil).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albertasse</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomaz</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Plantas medicinais e seus usos na comunidade da Barra do Jucu, Vila Velha, ES</article-title><source>Rev. bras. plantas med</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>RFP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>LVF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><source>M&#x000e9;todos e T&#x000e9;cnicas na pesquisa Etnobiol&#x000f3;gica e Etnoecol&#x000f3;gica</source><publisher-loc>Recife</publisher-loc><publisher-name>NUPEEA</publisher-name><volume>2010</volume><fpage>559</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MJP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>O uso da fitoterapia no cuidado de crian&#x000e7;as com at&#x000e9;cinco anos em &#x000e1;rea central e perif&#x000e9;rica dacidade de S&#x000e4;o Paulo</article-title><source>Rev. esc. enferm. USP</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14727448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Portes</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Seraphin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Chemical variability in the essential oil of <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> Phytochemistry</article-title><volume>57</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>736</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandeira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>LMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>ICS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacarin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J&#x000c1;</given-names></name><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>EJB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Composi&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o do &#x000f3;leo essencial de quatro esp&#x000e9;cies do g&#x000e9;nero <italic>Plectranthus</italic> Rev. bras</article-title><source>plantas med</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>164</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadda</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Saboor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Quantitative ethnomedicinal study of plants used in the skardu valley at high altitude of Karakoram-Himalayan range, Pakistan</article-title><source>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>43</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><source>A Constru&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o da Medicina Integrativa: um desafio para o campo da sa&#x000fa;de</source><publisher-loc>S&#x000e4;o Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Hucitec</publisher-name><fpage>311</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brasil</surname><given-names>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Secretaria de Aten&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o &#x000e0;Sa&#x000fa;de. Departamento de Aten&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o B&#x000e1;sica. Pol&#x000ed;tica Nacional de Pr&#x000e1;ticas Integrativas e Complementares no SUS (PNPIC)</article-title><source>Brasilia</source></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Brasil, Minist&#x000e9;rio do Meio Ambiente - MMA</collab><source>Desenvolvimento Rural - Povos e Comunidades Tradicionais</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>LSM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perinotto</surname><given-names>ARC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Difus&#x000e4;o da ci&#x000e9;ncia no Geopark Araripe, Cear&#x000e1;, Brasil</article-title><source>Anu. Inst. Geocienc</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>A persist&#x000e9;ncia das infec&#x000e7;&#x000f6;es respirat&#x000f3;rias agudas como problema de Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica</article-title><source>Cad. Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>1270</fpage><lpage>1271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>FB. D. I</given-names><suffix>J&#x000fa;nior</suffix></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>PQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac&#x000e9;do</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Varia&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o da quantidade de &#x003b2;-cariofileno em &#x000f3;leo essencial de <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (Lour.) Spreng, Lamiaceae, sob diferentes condi&#x000e7;&#x000f6;es de cultivo</article-title><source>Rev. bras. farmacogn</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x0201c;Hidden Diversity&#x0201d; of Medicinal Plants in Northeastern Brazil: Diagnosis and Prospects for Conservation and Biological Prospecting</article-title><source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source><year>2013</year><fpage>29</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>BJB</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchesi</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidel</surname><given-names>MGB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turato</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Amostragem em pesquisas qualitativas: proposta de procedimentos para constatar satura&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o te&#x000f3;rica</article-title><source>Cad. Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21359475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornazari</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Doen&#x000e7;as respirat&#x000f3;rias e seguimento de crian&#x000e7;as menores de cinco anos de idade: revis&#x000e4;o da literatura</article-title><source>Rev. bras. enferm</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15320619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haverroth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><source>Etnobiologia e Sa&#x000fa;de de Povos Ind&#x000ed;genas</source><publisher-loc>Recife</publisher-loc><publisher-name>NUPEEA</publisher-name><volume>2013</volume><fpage>275</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ichisato</surname><given-names>SMT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimo</surname><given-names>AKK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Aleitamento materno e as cren&#x000e7;as alimentares</article-title><source>Rev. Latino-Am. Enfermagem</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatistica - IBG</collab><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Censo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><comment>2010</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iserhard</surname><given-names>ARM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bud&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>MLD</given-names></name><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Badke</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Pr&#x000e1;ticas culturais de cuidados de mulheres m&#x000e4;es de rec&#x000e9;m-nascidos de risco do sul do Brasil</article-title><source>Esc. Anna Nery</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jesus</surname><given-names>NZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>JCS</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>DTO</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Levantamento etnobot&#x000e2;nico de plantas popularmente utilizadas como anti&#x000fa;lceras e antiinflamat&#x000f3;rias pela comunidade de Pirizal, Nossa Senhora do Livramento-MT, Brasil</article-title><source>Rev. bras. Farmacogn</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhuiyan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmatullah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>A survey of medicinal plants used by the Deb barma clan of the Tripura tribe of Moulvibazar district, Bangladesh</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24502444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Ethnomedicinal botany of the Apatani in the Eastern Himalayan region of India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenzi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>FJA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><source>Plantas medicinais no Brasil: nativas e ex&#x000f3;ticas</source><publisher-loc>Nova Odessa, SP</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Instituto Plantarum</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>GHN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JEFB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim&#x000f6;es</surname><given-names>VMF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Associa&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o de gravidez na adolesc&#x000e9;ncia e prematuridade</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Ginecol. Obstet</source><volume>33</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22267114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Furtado</surname><given-names>MCC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Seguimento de enfermagem: monitorando indicadores infantis na sa&#x000fa;de da familia</article-title><source>Acta paul. enferm</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>754</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dantas</surname><given-names>JDP</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>ARA</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e4;es</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Plantas medicinais usadas pelos indios Tapebas do Cear&#x000e1;</article-title><source>Rev. bras. Farmacogn</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nantitanon</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowwanapoonpohn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okonogi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Antioxidant and Antimicrobial Activities of <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> Essential Oil</article-title><source>Scientia Pharmaceutica</source><volume>75</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>VPR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><source>Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o da Actividade Antimicrobiana de Extractos e &#x000d3;leos Essenciais de Eucalipto <italic>(Eucalyptus globulus)</italic> em Isolados do tracto Respirat&#x000f3;rio Humano</source><publisher-loc>Vila Real</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universidade de Tr&#x000e1;s-os-Montes e Alto Douro 2014</publisher-name><comment>65f. Disserta&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o (Mestrado)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymundo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Interculturalidade e a conjun&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o de saberes que congregam a aten&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o em sa&#x000fa;de</article-title><source>Rev. Bio&#x000e9;t</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac&#x000e9;do</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>LGS</given-names></name><name><surname>Saraiva</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>I.R.A</given-names></name>
. (</person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Potencial terap&#x000e9;utico e uso de plantas medicinais em uma &#x000e1;rea de Caatinga no estado do Cear&#x000e1;, nordeste do Brasil</article-title><source>Rev. bras. plantas med</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>930</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Igl&#x000e9;sias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnatje</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Traditional and alternative natural therapeutic products used in the treatment of respiratory tract infectious diseases in the eastern Catalan Pyrenees (Iberian Peninsula)</article-title><source>Journal of Ethnopharmacology</source><volume>148</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23612419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>LHC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Levantamento etnobot&#x000e2;nico das plantas medicinais utilizadas pela comunidade de Inham&#x000e4;, Pernambuco, Nordeste do Brasil</article-title><source>Rev. bras. plantas med</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>730</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Loiola</surname><given-names>MIB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Uso e diversidade de plantas medicinais da Caatinga na comunidade rural de Laginhas, municipio de Caic&#x000f3;, Rio Grande do Norte (nordeste do Brasil)</article-title><source>Rev. bras. plantas med</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teklay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abera</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>An ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used in Kilte Awulaelo District, Tigray Region of Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>65</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24011232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>MFFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Estudo sobre o uso de plantas medicinais em crian&#x000e7;as hospitalizadas da cidade de Jo&#x000e4;o Pessoa: riscos e beneficios</article-title><source>Rev. bras. farmacogn</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>380</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veloso</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>LCA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>AF</given-names><suffix>J&#x000fa;nior</suffix></name><name><surname>Scheidt</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Teor e composi&#x000e7;&#x000e2;o do &#x000f3;leo essencial de quatro acessos e duas cultivares de manjeric&#x000e4;o <italic>(Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Rev. bras. plantas med</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>371</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vendruscolo</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mentz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Estudo da concord&#x000e2;ncia das cita&#x000e7;&#x000f6;es de uso e import&#x000e2;ncia das esp&#x000e9;cies e familias utilizadas como medicinais pela comunidade do bairro Ponta Grossa, Porto Alegre, RS, Brasil</article-title><source>Acta Bot. Bras</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>World Health Organization &#x02013; WHO</collab><year>2014</year><source>Infection prevention and control of epidemic- and pandemicprone acute respiratory infections in health care settings</source></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanatta</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Corso</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Saberes e pr&#x000e1;ticas de m&#x000e4;es no cuidado &#x000e0;crian&#x000e7;a de zero a seis meses</article-title><source>Rev Ga&#x000fa;ch Enferm</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>563</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>