<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Exp Mol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Exp. Mol. Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Experimental &#x00026; Molecular Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1226-3613</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2092-6413</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6001487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29899324</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-018-0104-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions are suppressed in <italic>fat-1</italic> transgenic mice through the inhibition of inflammasomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Hyun-Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>Jeung-Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Sang-Myeong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Byung-Hyun</given-names></name><address><phone>+82-63-270-3139</phone><email>bhpark@jbnu.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0470 4320</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411545.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry, </institution><institution>Chonbuk National University Medical School, </institution></institution-wrap>Jeonju, Jeonbuk 54896 Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0470 4320</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411545.0</institution-id><institution>Division of Biotechnology, College of Environmental and Bioresource Sciences, </institution><institution>Chonbuk National University, </institution></institution-wrap>Iksan, Jeonbuk 54596 Republic of Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>50</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>73</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, and provide a link to the Creative Commons license. You do not have permission under this license to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Previous clinical trials have addressed the beneficial effects of fish oil supplementation on atopic dermatitis. Recently, we reported that <italic>fat-1</italic> mice, which can convert n-6 to n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), are protected against allergic airway inflammation because their Th2 immune responses are suppressed. Here, we examined the effects of endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs on atopic dermatitis, a representative Th2-dominant allergic inflammatory disease. Mouse models of atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions were prepared by epicutaneous application of 2,4-dinitrochlorobenzene (DNCB) or house dust mite (HDM) extract to the ears. DNCB-treated <italic>fat-1</italic> mice exhibited markedly reduced epidermal thickening, lower mast cell infiltration, and lower serum IgE and histamine compared with wild-type mice. The draining lymph nodes of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice were substantially smaller and contained significantly smaller proportions of activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and IL-4-producing Th2 cells than those of wild-type mice. Consistent with these findings, the mRNA levels of Th2 cytokines were significantly decreased in DNCB-sensitized skin lesions of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. Lastly, inflammasome activation, IL-1&#x003b2; production, and pyroptotic cell injury were suppressed in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. Similar results were observed in HDM-challenged <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. This study confirms the results of previous clinical studies and suggests fish oil supplementation as a therapeutic strategy for atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="LongSummary"><title>Skin disease: Omega-3 fatty acid reduces inflammation</title><p id="Par2">A component of fish oil reduces the severity of atopic dermatitis in mice by dampening the immune response. Omega-3 fatty acids found in fish oil are essential nutrients that humans and other mammals need but cannot produce. Byung-Hyun Park at Chonbuk National University Medical School, Jeonju, South Korea, and colleagues show that genetically engineered mice expressing a gene which enables them to synthesize their own omega-3 fatty acids are protected from atopic dermatitis. Following exposure to a dermatitis-inducing chemical or house dust mite extract these mice developed smaller skin lesions and mounted a weaker inflammatory response than wild-type mice. This study confirms the anti-inflammatory effects of omega-3 fatty acids and highlights the use of fish oil supplements as a useful strategy for the treatment of atopic dermatitis and potentially other chronic inflammatory diseases.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Atopic dermatitis is a multifactorial chronic inflammatory disease that results from complex interactions between genetic and environmental factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Atopic dermatitis is also considered a T-helper 2 (Th2)-mediated allergic disease because interleukin (IL)-4, IL-5, and IL-13 produced by Th2 cells play key roles in its onset and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. These cytokines stimulate B cells, mast cells, and epidermal cells, leading to IgE production and mast cell degranulation as well as the production of various cytokines. Thymic stromal lymphopoietin (TSLP), a cytokine produced mainly by epidermal keratinocytes and mast cells, promotes the differentiation of na&#x00457;ve T cells into Th2 cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. TSLP is highly expressed in skin lesions of atopic dermatitis patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Interestingly, T cell polarization in atopic dermatitis is biphasic: there is a predominantly a Th2 response in the acute phase, while high levels of interferon (IFN)-&#x003b3; and the appearance of Th1 cells have been observed in the chronic phase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. In addition to adaptive immune responses, the innate immune system is activated via evolutionarily conserved pathogen-recognition receptors, such as Toll-like receptors (TLRs) and nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain receptors (NLRs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The most well known of these is NLR family pyrin domain-containing protein 3 (NLRP3), which recruits apoptosis-associated speck-like protein containing a caspase recruitment domain (ASC) and pro-caspase-1. Inflammasome assembly then activates caspase-1 and leads to the release of IL-1&#x003b2; and IL-18<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. These ILs are important in innate immune functions and in the regulation of adaptive immune responses. Indeed, single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in the <italic>Nlrp3</italic> gene are associated with atopic dermatitis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Based on the pathology of atopic dermatitis, immunomodulating strategies have been developed to treat the disease. These strategies include corticosteroids, calcineurin inhibitors, and IgE&#x02013;neutralizing antibodies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. However, prolonged use of these drugs often produces adverse effects in atopic dermatitis patients. Therefore, a safe and long-term therapeutic strategy is required. Several epidemiological studies have shown that dietary fish oil supplementation decreases the prevalence of atopic dermatitis and alleviates the severity of the disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Fish oil is an important source of n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), such as eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA, 20:5) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA, C22:6). The incorporation of n-3 PUFAs into the membranes of immune cells, at the expense of arachidonic acid, is thought to be important for the anti-inflammatory effects of n-3 PUFAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, which gives rise to fewer inflammatory eicosanoids. This shift ultimately affects cytokine production. n-3 PUFAs suppress T-cell activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, monocyte chemotaxis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, macrophage M1 polarization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, and dendritic cell maturation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, resulting in a decrease in local tissue inflammation. However, it is difficult to ascertain the contribution of n-3 PUFAs <italic>per se</italic> without the potential confounding effects of other dietary components, such as the nutrient composition, total caloric intake, duration of feeding, and contamination of trace elements. To address this issue, Kang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. developed <italic>fat-1</italic> mice, which contain the <italic>fat-1</italic> gene from <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> and are able to convert n-6 to n-3 PUFAs in vivo. As a result of the endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs in blood and tissues, these mice exhibit the beneficial effects of n-3 PUFAs in various inflammatory disease models, such as pancreatitis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, allergic airway inflammation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and rheumatoid arthritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. In this study, we investigated whether atopic dermatitis-like symptoms and skin lesions observed in 2,4-dinitrochlorobenzene (DNCB)- or house dust mite (HDM) extract-exposed mice would be alleviated in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. Special attention was paid to the effects exerted by endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs on inflammasome activation in skin tissues.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Animals</title><p id="Par5">Dr. JX Kang of Harvard Medical School (Boston, MA, USA) kindly provided the <italic>fat-1</italic> transgenic mice. Mice were housed in a laminar flow cabinet and maintained on an AIN-76A diet containing 5% corn oil provided ad libitum. All animal experiments were performed in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals, published by the US National Institutes of Health (NIH Publication No. 85-23, revised 2011). The current study protocol was also approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Chonbuk National University (Permit No. CBNU 2017-0085).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Induction of experimental atopic dermatitis</title><p id="Par6">To induce experimental atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions, the surfaces of both ears were very gently stripped five times with surgical tape (Tegaderm; 3&#x02009;M, St Paul, MN, USA). Mice were sensitized by applying 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 1% DNCB (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) or vehicle alone to the ear on Day -7. On Day 0, mice were challenged again by applying 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 0.5% DNCB to the ears every other day for up to 42 days. Changes in ear thickness were measured weekly. The mice were sacrificed on Day 43. In the HDM (<italic>Dermatophagoides farina</italic> extract, Greer Laboratories, Lenoir, NC, USA)-induced atopic dermatitis model, both surfaces of the ear lobes were very gently stripped three times with Tegaderm. After stripping, 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of HDM (10&#x02009;mg/ml) was painted on each ear. The application of HDM was repeated 3 times per week for 8 weeks. Two weeks after the first induction, blood was collected from the tail vein to measure serum IgE.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Histology</title><p id="Par7">Ear tissues were fixed with 10% formalin and embedded in paraffin. Fixed tissues were cut into 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m sections and deparaffinized. Sections were stained with hematoxylin-eosin (H&#x00026;E) or toluidine blue for light-microscopic examinations or mast cell infiltration assays, respectively. The epidermis and dermis thicknesses were measured using the iSolution DT36 software (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany). The inflammation severity was scored as follows:<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> 0, none; 1, minimal; 2, mild; 3, moderate; and 4, marked. Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) staining was performed using a commercial kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). For confocal microscopic analysis, sections were stained with antibodies against caspase-1 (14F468) or ASC (N-15) (both from Santa Cruz Biotechnology). Images were acquired with an LSM510 confocal laser scanning microscope (Carl Zeiss).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)</title><p id="Par8">The levels of IgE, IgG1, IgG2a, IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1;, IFN-&#x003b3; IL-4, IL-13, IL-17 (eBioscience, San Diego, CA, USA), histamine (Enzo Life Sciences), high-mobility group box 1 (HMGB1, Chondrex, Redmond, WA, USA), and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity (Biovision, Milpitas, CA, USA) in mouse serum were measured using commercial ELISA kits.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cell surface staining and intracellular cytokine staining for flow cytometry</title><p id="Par9">Single-cell suspensions prepared from draining lymph nodes (dLNs) were stained with anti-CD4-PerCP/Cy5.5 and anti-CD69-FITC antibodies (eBioscience) for 30&#x02009;min on ice and washed with fluorescence-activated cell sorting buffer (2% FBS in PBS). The cell surface expression of CD69 and percentage of IL-4-producing CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were evaluated by flow cytometry on an Accuri flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA, USA). All of the antibodies used were purchased from eBioscience.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par10">Data are expressed as the means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. Significant differences between groups were determined using Student&#x02019;s unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test followed by Fisher&#x02019;s post-hoc analysis. A value of <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was accepted as an indication of statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Liquid chromatographic analysis shows increased n-3 PUFA content in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice</title><p id="Par11">We first quantified the major n-3 and n-6 PUFAs in skin tissues of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice and their wild-type (WT) littermates. The n-3 PUFA (ALA, EPA, and DHA) content was significantly different between the genotypes, with higher levels in the serum and skin tissues of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Conversely, the n-6 PUFA (AA and LA) contents were lower in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice compared with WT mice. <italic>Fat-1</italic> mice had a skin tissue n-6/n-3 ratio of 5.6 compared to the ratio of 12.5 in WT mice.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><italic>Fat-1</italic> gene overexpression ameliorates the symptoms of atopic dermatitis in mice</title><p id="Par12">To validate the effects of endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs on atopic dermatitis, a DNCB-induced atopic dermatitis model was used (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Following DNCB treatment, the ears of wild-type mice became red and swollen. On day 42, the ears of DNCB-treated wild-type mice showed severe erythema, erosion, and dryness (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). However, these atopic skin lesions were markedly attenuated in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. When ear thickness was measured over time and compared between genotypes, we found that thickness increased as atopic dermatitis developed. Consistent with the photographic images of the skin lesions, ear thickness was significantly reduced beginning on Day 7 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). As IgE production, histamine release, and TSLP expression are markers for the development of atopic dermatitis, we also measured those levels in serum. As expected, <italic>fat-1</italic> mice produced significantly less histamine, IgE, IgG1, IgG2a, and TSLP than wild-type mice at Day 43 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d, e</xref>). These data indicate that endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs effectively ameliorate atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions in mice.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>DNCB-induced atopic dermatitis-like symptoms in mice.</title><p><bold>a</bold> A schematic diagram showing the induction of atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions by DNCB treatment in mice. <bold>b</bold> Representative pictures of mouse ears on Day 42. <bold>c</bold> Ear thickness was measured weekly from day 7 to 42 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4). <bold>d</bold> Serum histamine, IgE, IgG1, and IgG2a in mice were measured by ELISA (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7&#x02013;9). <bold>e</bold> TSLP in ear skin was measured by western blotting with densitometry (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT; <sup>#</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+DNCB</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e546"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Tissue inflammation and immune cell infiltration are diminished in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice</title><p id="Par13">Improvements in the atopic symptoms of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice were also confirmed by microscopic analysis of H&#x00026;E-stained sections from ears removed at the end of the study. Wild-type mice under DNCB treatment exhibited the typical microscopic characteristics of atopic dermatitis, which include hyperkeratosis, parakeratosis, and acanthosis, along with infiltration of inflammatory cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). Toluidine blue staining of ear tissue sections revealed mast cell infiltration into the dermis of wild-type mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>). However, in skin tissues from <italic>fat-1</italic> mice, the epidermal and dermal tissues were significantly thinner and the infiltration of inflammatory cells into the dermis was significantly reduced. Accordingly, the inflammation score and mRNA levels of inflammation-related genes were changed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c, d</xref>). These results suggest that reductions in inflammation and mast cell infiltration in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice might attenuate the symptoms of atopic dermatitis. Since histamine release was markedly downregulated in <italic>fat-1</italic> skin tissues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>), we hypothesized that endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs improved atopic dermatitis-like skin symptoms through downregulation of mast cell function. To test this possibility, we focused on the transcription factors required for mast cell activation. Gene expression analysis showed that <italic>Gata2</italic>, but not <italic>Gata1</italic>, was markedly increased by DNCB treatment in WT mice and significantly downregulated in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). The expression of the GATA2 target genes <italic>Cpa3</italic> and <italic>c-Kit</italic> was altered accordingly.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Histological analysis of ear skin lesions.</title><p>Ears were excised from each group of mice on Day 43, fixed with formalin, embedded in paraffin, and cut into thin sections. The ear sections were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E) and toluidine blue. Bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. <bold>a</bold> Representative photomicrographs of ear sections. The arrow indicates mast cells. <bold>b</bold> Epidermal and dermal thicknesses were measured in H&#x00026;E-stained microphotographs, and mast cells were counted after toluidine blue staining. <bold>c</bold> The inflammation index was determined as described in the Methods (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>d, e</bold> mRNA expression levels of inflammation-related genes (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) and mast cell transcription factors (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) were determined by real-time RT-PCR. Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT; <sup>#</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+DNCB</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e647"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>T cell activation and Th2 cytokine production are suppressed in draining lymph nodes of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice</title><p id="Par14">To investigate whether skin inflammation increased the number of Th2 cells in the dLNs of the ear, submandibular lymph nodes were collected. We first observed that the lymph nodes in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice were substantially smaller than those from wild-type mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Lymph nodes were homogenized, and single cells were prepared and counted. Consistent with the lymph node size, the total cell numbers were significantly decreased in the lymph nodes of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). Next, single cells prepared from lymph nodes were analyzed for T cell activation. Flow-cytometric analysis showed that the percentages of T cells expressing CD25<sup>+</sup> and CD69<sup>+</sup> were significantly lower in the dLNs of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>), indicating that <italic>fat-1</italic> expression suppressed DNCB-induced CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell activation in dLNs. Moreover, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from <italic>fat-1</italic> mice showed lower percentages of Th1, Th2, and Th17 cells after DNCB treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>), but no difference in the percentage of Tregs (data not shown). Real-time RT-PCR analysis of cytokines in dLNs revealed an inhibition of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell differentiation into Th1, Th2, or Th17 in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). ELISA analysis in serum further revealed an inhibition of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell differentiation in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>T cell activation and differentiation in the draining lymph nodes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> At the end of the study, submandibular lymph nodes were collected, and photographs were taken. <bold>b</bold> Single-cell suspensions were prepared from dLNs, and total cells were counted (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>c</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were analyzed for CD25 and CD69 by flow cytometry (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>d</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were stained for IL-4, IL-17, and IFN-&#x003b3; and analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentage of CD4<sup>+</sup> cells expressing each cytokine is shown (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9). <bold>e</bold> dLNs were homogenized, and the mRNA levels of cytokines were analyzed by real-time RT-PCR (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7). <bold>f</bold> Serum cytokines were measured by ELISA (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7). Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT;<sup>#</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+DNCB</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e785"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>n-3 PUFAs alleviate NLRP3 inflammasome-mediated pyroptosis by inhibiting NF-&#x003ba;B activation</title><p id="Par15">Since inflammasomes play important roles in skin inflammation, including atopic dermatitis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, we hypothesized that endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs would ameliorate the symptoms of atopic dermatitis by suppressing inflammasome activation. To test this hypothesis, we compared the protein and mRNA levels of NLRP3, ASC, and caspase-1, which are three key components of inflammasomes, in the skin of ears. NLRP3, procaspase-1, its proteolytic cleavage products p20 and p10, and ASC were markedly increased by DNCB treatment of WT mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>). In agreement with the results of western blotting, immunofluorescence staining showed that p20 caspase-1 and ASC were elevated in DNCB-treated WT skin tissues (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). We further determined the protein levels of IL-1&#x003b2; and HMGB1, hallmarks of inflammasome activation. DNCB treatment increased the expression of IL-1&#x003b2; and HMGB1 in the skin tissues as well as their secretion into the systemic circulation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d, e</xref>). However, all of the aforementioned findings of inflammasome activation were remarkably suppressed in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Inflammasome activation.</title><p><bold>a, b</bold> At the end of the study, inflammasome components in the skin lesions were examined by western blotting and real-time RT-PCR. Protein levels were quantified by densitometry (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). <bold>c</bold> Skin tissues were double-stained for caspase-1 and ASC. Signals are digitally merged in the lower panels. Bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. IL-1&#x003b2; and HMGB1 in skin tissues <bold>(d)</bold> and serum <bold>(e)</bold> were measured by ELISA (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5). Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT; <sup>#</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+DNCB</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e859"/></fig></p><p id="Par16">Activation of inflammasomes culminates in a special type of cell death called pyroptosis, a proinflammatory programmed cell death. Cell death by pyroptosis is characterized by the loss of the plasma membrane integrity and eventual cell lysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. We observed a significant decrease in TUNEL-positive cells in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice compared with WT mice (Fig. S1A). LDH activity was also decreased in both the skin and serum of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice, suggesting maintenance of membrane integrity (Figs. S1B and S1C).</p><p id="Par17">Because NLRP3 expression is under transcriptional control of NF-&#x003ba;B, we next evaluated changes in NF-&#x003ba;B under our experimental conditions. Acetylated p65 (Ac-p65) was markedly increased by DNCB, while no change was observed for total p65 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). DNCB-mediated NF-&#x003ba;B activation was followed by an increase in the mRNA levels of two of the NF-&#x003ba;B-dependent proinflammatory molecules, <italic>Tnfa</italic> and <italic>Il1b</italic> (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). We further confirmed NF-&#x003ba;B activation by these cytokines in HaCaT cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). Endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice and exogenous treatment with DHA in HaCaT cells significantly suppressed DNCB- and cytokine-induced NF-&#x003ba;B activation, respectively (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). However, arachidonic acid, an n-6 PUFA, had no effect on NF-&#x003ba;B activation.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>The Sirt1-NF-&#x003ba;B axis in skin lesions and HaCaT cells.</title><p><bold>a</bold> At the end of the study, p65, acetylated p65, and Sirt1 in the skin lesions were measured by western blotting. <bold>b</bold> mRNA levels of cytokines in the skin lesions were determined by real-time RT-PCR (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5). <bold>c</bold> HaCaT cells were transiently transfected with an <italic>NfkB</italic> luciferase construct and then treated with 10&#x02009;nM TNF-&#x003b1; and 10&#x02009;nM IL-1&#x003b2; in the presence or absence of 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M DHA or 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M arachidonic acid. After 24&#x02009;h, cells were harvested in reporter lysis buffer, and luciferase activity in cell lysates was assayed (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7&#x02013;9). <bold>d</bold> mRNA levels of <italic>Sirt1</italic> in the skin lesions were determined by real-time RT-PCR (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5). <bold>e, f</bold> Protein levels of Sirt1 and HMGB1 and Sirt1 luciferase activity in HaCaT cells. Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>*</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT; <sup>#</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+DNCB or VEH; <sup>$$</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. none+VEH. VEH vehicle, DHA docosahexaenoic acid, AA arachidonic acid</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e968"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">We previously reported that <italic>fat-1</italic> gene overexpression increased Sirt1 expression and decreased p65 acetylation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. We therefore investigated whether Sirt1 expression was linked to the acetylation status of p65 in our experimental conditions. Our results revealed a significant reduction in Sirt1 expression and/or activity in DNCB-treated skin tissues and cytokine-treated HaCaT cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d&#x02013;f</xref>). Again, endogenous and exogenous n-3 PUFAs significantly upregulated the level of Sirt1 mRNA or protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>HDM-induced atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions are suppressed in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice</title><p id="Par19">To explore the relevance of our findings to human disease, we reproduced our experiments using the HDM antigen, one of the most clinically important allergens for atopic dermatitis. HDM exposure induced increases in ear thickness; increases in serum HMGB1, IgE, and histamine; and histological abnormalities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a&#x02013;e</xref>). Similar to the results obtained with the DNCB model, all of these parameters were significantly suppressed in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. The overall atopic symptoms and skin lesions observed in the HDM model were weaker than those in the DNCB model. Collectively, our experiments with HDM confirm our results with the DNCB model of atopic dermatitis.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Allergic inflammation in response to HDM.</title><p>Mice were challenged with HDM as described in the Materials and Methods. <bold>a</bold> Ear thickness and <bold>(b-d)</bold> serum IgE, histamine, and HMGB1were analyzed (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6). <bold>e</bold> Paraffin-embedded skin sections were prepared and stained with H&#x00026;E and toluidine blue. Bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Epidermal and dermal thicknesses were measured in H&#x00026;E-stained microphotographs (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6). Values are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEMs. <sup>**</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT; <sup>##</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 vs. WT+HDM</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12276_2018_104_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1031"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Several human clinical trials have addressed the beneficial effects of n-3 PUFAs on atopic dermatitis. Fish oil supplementation during pregnancy has resulted in improvements in the clinical severity of atopic outcomes for infants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Similarly, infants supplemented with DHA-rich formula during the first year of life had a reduced incidence of atopic dermatitis during early childhood<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Regulation of epidermal barrier function and modulation of the immune system have been suggested as underlying mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Since DHA and EPA are not major constituents of the epidermis because of insufficient dietary consumption or increased cellular utilization, the restoration of skin permeability-barrier abnormality is not likely the main mechanism. Instead, substantial attention has been paid to the immune-modulatory function of n-3 PUFAs, especially T cell regulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. However, to our knowledge, a study on the inflammasome, a component of the innate immune system, has not been reported.</p><p id="Par21">An <italic>Nlrp3</italic> gene polymorphism has been associated with increased risk of atopic dermatitis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, and activation of inflammasomes triggers the allergic inflammatory response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Consequently, targeting the inhibition of NLRP3 inflammasomes is an attractive strategy for treating allergic diseases, including atopic dermatitis. Although there is growing evidence that nutrition is an effective modulator of the inflammasome, few attempts have been made to inhibit the NLRP3 inflammasome through diet. Interestingly, saturated fatty acids activate the NLRP3 inflammasome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, while unsaturated fatty acids prevent its activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Herein, we investigated whether endogenously synthesized n-3 PUFAs are effective in suppressing the NLRP3 inflammasome and mitigating the pathophysiological consequences of inflammation in mouse models of DNCB- and HDM-induced atopic dermatitis-like skin lesions. Our results showed that DNCB treatment resulted in activation of NLRP3 inflammasome signaling pathways, as evidenced by increases in NLRP3 and ASC expression, enhanced maturation of caspase-1 and IL-1&#x003b2;, and induction of pyroptosis. However, <italic>fat-1</italic> gene overexpression increases Sirt1 expression, which allows for deacetylation of NF-&#x003ba;B, resulting in the loss of its transcriptional activity. Given that NF-&#x003ba;B activation is required for the transcription of inflammasome components, including <italic>Nlrp3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, n-3 PUFAs seem to inhibit the priming of the NLRP3 inflammasome based on its ability to suppress NF-&#x003ba;B.</p><p id="Par22">Most of the mechanistic studies on atopic dermatitis point to an imbalance between Th1 and Th2 responses in favor of Th2 responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. The characteristic Th2 responses observed in atopic dermatitis patients include abnormal IgE production, mast cell infiltration, peripheral eosinophilia, and induction of Th2 cells expressing IL-4 and IL-13. Interestingly, sequential biopsies from atopic dermatitis patients after exposure to aeroallergens show a biphasic immunologic response characterized by switching from a Th2 phenotype in the earlier phase to a Th1 phenotype in the later phase of the disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Concordantly, B cells switch their expression of immunoglobulin classes from IgE to IgG2a. Consistent with our previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, <italic>fat-1</italic> gene overexpression decreased IL-4, IL-5, IL-13, and IFN-&#x003b3; as well as IgE, IgG1, and IgG2a, suggesting that n-3 PUFAs inhibit both Th2 and Th1 immune responses. In addition to the Th1/Th2 paradigm, the roles of Th17 and Treg cells in the pathogenesis of atopic dermatitis have also been highlighted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. IL-17 modulates innate immunity via keratinocytes, as IL-17 together with IFN-&#x003b3; amplifies a nonspecific cytotoxic cascade that results in a severe and sustained cutaneous inflammatory reaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. To clarify this point, it was necessary to examine Th17 cell infiltration into skin lesions of <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. In the present study, <italic>fat-1</italic> gene overexpression successfully inhibited Th17 cell infiltration in the skin tissues and IL-17 production by draining lymph nodes, which was related to the decreased production of the inflammatory cytokines IFN-&#x003b3;, TNF-&#x003b1;, and IL-6. Consistent with our previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, the present study strongly suggests that <italic>fat-1</italic> gene overexpression suppresses Th17 cell-mediated cutaneous inflammation in DNCB-treated mice. However, in contrast to the report by Han et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, we did not observe an increase in Treg cells in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice. In their study, DHA upregulated the function of M2 macrophages and promoted the generation of Treg cells. Since we also observed an increase in M2 macrophages in <italic>fat-1</italic> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, differences in the n-3 PUFAs (DHA in their study vs. n-3 PUFAs in our study) might have produced the different outcomes.</p><p id="Par23">In summary, our data demonstrate that DNCB treatment activates the NLRP3 inflammasome pathway, which induces the release of inflammatory cytokines and amplifies the inflammatory response to cause atopic dermatitis symptoms. Modulation of this pathway with n-3 PUFAs has clinical relevance and can be a useful strategy to attenuate atopic dermatitis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec18"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12276_2018_104_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>The authors contributed equally: Hyun-Young Jang, Jeung-Hyun Koo.</p></fn><fn><p>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s12276-018-0104-3.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Basic Science Research Program (grant numbers NRF-2017R1A2B2005730&#x000a0;and 2018R1D1A1B07046553) and by the Medical Research Center Program (grant number NRF-2017R1A5A2015061) through the National Research Foundation (NRF) funded by the Korean government (MSIP). We thank Sang-Hyun Kim (School of Medicine, Kyungpook National University, Korea) for critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par24">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetics and epigenetics of atopic dermatitis-filaggrin and other polymorphisms</article-title><source>Clin. Rev. Allergy Immunol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12016-015-8508-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26385242?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivaprasad</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Th2 cytokines and atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>J. Clin. Cell Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>110</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2155-9899.1000110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21994899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21994899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New concept of the pathogenesis of atopic dermatitis: interplay among the barrier, allergy, and pruritus as a trinity</article-title><source>J. Dermatol. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdermsci.2013.02.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23473856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23473856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00149-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26377142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26377142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TSLP-activated dendritic cells induce an inflammatory T helper type 2 cell response through OX40 ligand</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20051135</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16275760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16275760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soumelis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human epithelial cells trigger dendritic cell mediated allergic inflammation by producing TSLP</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni805</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12055625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Waki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TSLP directly interacts with skin-homing Th2 cells highly expressing its receptor to enhance IL-4 production in atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>J. Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>3017</fpage><lpage>3024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2015.318</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26288354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26288354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grewe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the cytokine pattern expressed in situ in inhalant allergen patch test reactions of atopic dermatitis patients</article-title><source>J. Invest Dermatol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1523-1747.ep12321078</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7665922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7665922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NOD2 and TLR2 ligands trigger the activation of basophils and eosinophils by interacting with dermal fibroblasts in atopic dermatitis-like skin inflammation</article-title><source>Cell Mol. Immunol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cmi.2015.77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26388234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arend</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IL-1, IL-18, and IL-33 families of cytokines</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2008</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2008.00624.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18613828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18613828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macaluso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polymorphisms in NACHT-LRR (NLR) genes in atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>Exp. Dermatol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0625.2007.00589.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17620097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17620097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NLRP3rs35829419 polymorphism is associated with increased susceptibility to multiple diseases in humans</article-title><source>Genet Mol. Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>13968</fpage><lpage>13980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/2015.October.29.17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26535712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26535712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bivik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation in the inflammasome and atopic dermatitis susceptibility</article-title><source>J. Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>2486</fpage><lpage>2489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2013.168</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23563199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23563199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belloni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low-dose anti-IgE therapy in patients with atopic eczema with high serum IgE levels</article-title><source>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>1225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2007.08.060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17936892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17936892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in atopic dermatitis management: comparison of 1990-1997 to 2003-2012</article-title><source>J. Drugs Dermatol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29462220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29462220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonacier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of eczema: corticosteroids and beyond</article-title><source>Clin. Rev. Allergy Immunol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12016-015-8486-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25869743?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25869743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hageman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of dietary long-chain polyunsaturated fatty acids on respiratory illness in infants and children</article-title><source>Curr. Allergy Asthma Rep.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11882-012-0304-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23001718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23001718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Supplementation with a fish oil-enriched, high-protein medical food leads to rapid incorporation of EPA into white blood cells and modulates immune responses within one week in healthy men and women</article-title><source>J. Nutr.</source><year>2011</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.110.132985</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21430245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of n-3 PUFA on the CD4<sup>+</sup> type 2 helper T-cell-mediated immune responses in Fat-1 mice</article-title><source>Mol. Nutr. Food Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201300194</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24019303?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24019303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Omega-3 fatty acids ameliorate atherosclerosis by favorably altering monocyte subsets and limiting monocyte recruitment to aortic lesions</article-title><source>Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2122</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/ATVBAHA.112.253435</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22814747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22814747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced M2 macrophage polarization in high n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid transgenic mice fed a high-fat diet</article-title><source>Mol. Nutr. Food Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2481</fpage><lpage>2492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201600014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27306613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27306613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dendritic cell activation, phagocytosis and CD69 expression on cognate T cells are suppressed by n-3 long-chain polyunsaturated fatty acids</article-title><source>Immunology</source><year>2013</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imm.12088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23373457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23373457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgenic mice: fat-1 mice convert n-6 to n-3 fatty acids</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>504</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/427504a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14765186?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weylandt</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduction of inflammation and chronic tissue damage by omega-3 fatty acids in fat-1 transgenic mice with pancreatitis</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys. Acta</source><year>2008</year><volume>1782</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2008.08.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18832028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18832028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endogenous conversion of n-6 to n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids attenuates K/BxN serum-transfer arthritis in fat-1 mice</article-title><source>J. Nutr. Biochem</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2015.01.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25910895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25910895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The enzyme Cyp26b1 mediates inhibition of mast cell activation by fibroblasts to maintain skin-barrier homeostasis</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2014.01.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24726878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24726878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mite allergen is a danger signal for the skin via activation of inflammasome in keratinocytes</article-title><source>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>14. e1-4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2010.12.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21272927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21272927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammasomes and inflammatory caspases in skin inflammation</article-title><source>Expert Rev. Mol. Diagn.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14737159.8.6.697</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18999922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18999922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Aderem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caspase-1-induced pyroptotic cell death</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2011</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2011.01044.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21884178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21884178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furuhjelm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allergic disease in infants up to 2 years of age in relation to plasma omega-3 fatty acids and maternal fish oil supplementation in pregnancy and lactation</article-title><source>Pediatr. Allergy Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3038.2010.01096.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21332799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21332799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denburg</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fish oil supplementation in pregnancy modifies neonatal progenitors at birth in infants at risk of atopy</article-title><source>Pediatr. Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1203/01.PDR.0000148279.72611.1D</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15585690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15585690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of early nutrition on incidence of allergic manifestations and common respiratory illnesses in children</article-title><source>J. Pediatr.</source><year>2010</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpeds.2010.01.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20227721?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant-Kels</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Healing fats of the skin: the structural and immunologic roles of the omega-6 and omega-3 fatty acids</article-title><source>Clin. Dermatol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clindermatol.2010.03.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20620762?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20620762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Docosahexaenoic acid alleviates atopic dermatitis by generating Tregs and IL-10/TGF-&#x003b2;-modified macrophages via a TGF-&#x003b2;-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>J. Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1556</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2014.488</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25405323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25405323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Omega-3 fatty acids suppress Th2-associated cytokine gene expressions and GATA transcription factors in mast cells</article-title><source>J. Nutr. Biochem</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2012.05.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22902330?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22902330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herberth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endogenous metabolites and inflammasome activity in early childhood and links to respiratory diseases</article-title><source>J. Allergy Clin. Immunol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2015.01.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25754623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25754623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid-induced NLRP3-ASC inflammasome activation interferes with insulin signaling</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21478880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dietary saturated fatty acids prime the NLRP3 inflammasome via TLR4 in dendritic cells-implications for diet-induced insulin resistance</article-title><source>Mol. Nutr. Food Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1212</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201200058</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22700321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22700321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Omega-3 fatty acids prevent inflammation and metabolic disorder through inhibition of NLRP3 inflammasome activation</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2013.05.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23809162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monounsaturated fatty acid-enriched high-fat diets impede adipose NLRP3 inflammasome-mediated IL-1&#x003b2; secretion and insulin resistance despite obesity</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>2015</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>2116</fpage><lpage>2128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/db14-1098</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25626736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25626736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauernfeind</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cutting edge: NF-&#x003ba;B activating pattern recognition and cytokine receptors license NLRP3 inflammasome activation by regulating NLRP3 expression</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0901363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19570822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guttman-Yassky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atopic dermatitis and psoriasis: two different immune diseases or one spectrum?</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Immunol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2017.08.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28869867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28869867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Cesare</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Meglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nestle</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for Th17 cells in the immunopathogenesis of atopic dermatitis?</article-title><source>J. Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>2569</fpage><lpage>2571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2008.283</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18927538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-17 amplifies human contact hypersensitivity by licensing hapten nonspecific Th1 cells to kill autologous keratinocytes</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>4880</fpage><lpage>4888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0901767</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20357258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20357258</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>