<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Insects</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Insects</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">insects</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Insects</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2075-4450</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4553563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects3041056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">insects-03-01056</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Parasitoids of Queensland Fruit Fly <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> in Australia and Prospects for Improved Biological Control</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zamek</surname><given-names>Ashley L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-insects-03-01056">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-insects-03-01056">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spinner</surname><given-names>Jennifer E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-insects-03-01056">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Micallef</surname><given-names>Jessica L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-insects-03-01056">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>Geoff M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-insects-03-01056">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>Olivia L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-insects-03-01056">4</xref><xref rid="c1-insects-03-01056" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-insects-03-01056"><label>1</label>Elizabeth Macarthur Agricultural Institute, NSW Department of Primary Industries, Woodbridge Road, Menangle, NSW 2568, Australia; E-Mails: <email>azamek@phau.com.au</email> (A.L.Z.); <email>jess.smart@dpi.nsw.gov.au</email> (J.L.M)</aff><aff id="af2-insects-03-01056"><label>2</label>EH Graham Centre for Agricultural Innovation, NSW Department of Primary Industries and Charles Sturt University, Locked Bag 588, Wagga Wagga, NSW 2678, Australia; E-Mail: <email>jspinner@csu.edu.au</email></aff><aff id="af3-insects-03-01056"><label>3</label>EH Graham Centre for Agricultural Innovation, NSW Department of Primary Industries and Charles Sturt University, Charles Sturt University, P.O. Box 883, Orange, NSW 2800, Australia; E-Mail: <email>ggurr@csu.edu.au</email></aff><aff id="af4-insects-03-01056"><label>4</label>EH Graham Centre for Agricultural Innovation, NSW Department of Primary Industries and Charles Sturt University, Elizabeth Macarthur Agricultural Institute, Woodbridge Road, Menangle, NSW 2568, Australia </aff><author-notes><fn id="fn1-insects-03-01056"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Present address: Level 1, 1 Phipps Close DEAKIN ACT 2600 Australia. </p></fn><corresp id="c1-insects-03-01056"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>olivia.reynolds@dpi.nsw.gov.au</email>; Tel.: +61-0-2-4640-6426; Fax: +61-0-2-4640-6300.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2012 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This review draws together available information on the biology, methods for study, and culturing of hymenopteran parasitoids of the Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic>, and assesses prospects for improving biological control of this serious pest<italic>. </italic>Augmentative release of the native and naturalised Australian parasitoids, especially the braconid <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic>, may result in better management of <italic>B. tryoni </italic>in some parts of Australia. Mass releases are an especially attractive option for areas of inland eastern Australia around the Fruit Fly Exclusion Zone that produces <italic>B. tryoni</italic>-free fruits for export. <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> has been successful in other locations such as Hawaii for the biological control of other fruit fly species. Biological control could contribute to local eradication of isolated outbreaks and more general suppression and/or eradication of the <italic>B. tryoni</italic> population in endemic areas. Combining biological control with the use of sterile insect technique offers scope for synergy because the former is most effective at high pest densities and the latter most economical when the pest becomes scarce. Recommendations are made on methods for culturing and study of four <italic>B. tryoni</italic> parasitoids present in Australia along with research priorities for optimising augmentative biological control of <italic>B. tryoni</italic>. </p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Braconidae</kwd><kwd>Tephritidae</kwd><kwd><italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Fopius arisanus</italic></kwd><kwd>sterile insect technique</kwd><kwd>integrated pest management</kwd><kwd>mass-rearing</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>The Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> (Froggatt) (Diptera: Tephritidae), is the major fruit fly pest for all of eastern Australia with literature on the species dating back more than 115 years [<xref rid="B1-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is a major economic pest as a consequence of its ability to survive in a wide range of climatic conditions, its polyphagous nature and its destructive damage to most cultivated fruits and fruiting vegetables. The native range of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> is considered to be tropical and subtropical coastal Queensland (Qld) and northern New South Wales (NSW), however, its distribution now extends along much of the eastern seaboard and areas of inland NSW and Victoria [<xref rid="B1-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Within NSW, <italic>B. tryoni</italic> is best suited to the climate of the coastal and northern inland areas. It can, however, thrive in less suitable areas such as the south and south-west of the state during years of favourable rainfall, with distribution shrinking back to irrigated areas during dryer years [<xref rid="B2-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The majority of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> adults are believed to disperse up to 1 km, although larvae are readily transported in vehicles within infested fruit that pose a threat to many quarantined production areas within suitable climatic zones [<xref rid="B3-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] such as those within NSW. <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> also has the potential to spread internationally because of its tolerance of a wide range of climatic conditions and large host range, as well as its tendency to be dispersed by humans at the larval stage inside infested fruit [<xref rid="B3-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The expansion of <italic>B. tryoni </italic>within Australia began as rainforests were cleared and large areas, including inland irrigation zones, were planted with susceptible fruit crops. The largely unrestricted interstate trade of fruits during the late 1890s also contributed to this pest&#x02019;s spread. Infested fruits quickly become rotten and inedible causing considerable losses in production, often resulting in complete destruction of fruits rather than only cosmetic damage as is caused by many other insect pests [<xref rid="B4-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Currently, <italic>B. tryoni </italic>is managed using mainly surveillance (trapping), bait spraying, the sterile insect technique (SIT) and chemical control as well as public education [<xref rid="B5-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, with diminishing pesticide options for the control of <italic>B. tryoni</italic>, industries are increasingly looking at other alternatives. The aim of this review is to draw-together available information on the biology, methods for study, and culturing of hymenopteran parasitoids of the Queensland fruit fly, <italic>B. tryoni. </italic>In order to assess prospects for improving biological control of this serious pest in Australia, the international literature on biological control of other fruit fly species is synthesised<italic>.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>2. Biological Control Strategies</title><p>Natural enemies when applied properly are promising, environmentally-friendly and effective tools for sustainable control of arthropod pests to the extent that biological control of insect pests is one of the most cost effective and environmentally sound methods of pest management [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In the past 120 years, more than 200 species of exotic arthropods have been introduced on more than 5,000 occasions into 196 countries for the control of insect pests [<xref rid="B8-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Such inoculative or classical biological control offers the advantage that well-chosen agents, compatible with the conditions into which they are released, have the ability to maintain self-perpetuating populations from generation to generation [<xref rid="B9-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], providing good continuity of control. There is always a risk however, that the agent will attack non-target species. Parasitoids are, therefore, often considered a better option than predators, as the former rely on the host for development and are often more host specific [<xref rid="B10-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] so reducing the risk of the agent attacking non-target species. Parasitoids are categorised based on factors such as egg development pattern in the adult female (synovigenic <italic>versus</italic> proovigenic), whether larvae develop within the host (endoparasitoid) or externally (ectoparasitoid), whether the host continues development (koinobiont parasitoid) and feeding after parasitism or is arrested (idiobiont parasitoid), and whether the adult parasitoid feeds upon the host [<xref rid="B11-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Many parasitoid wasps (including Braconidae) have the advantage of being self-dispersing giving wide coverage in areas where other techniques such as spraying cannot be readily applied [<xref rid="B12-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In addition, parasitoids are in no way dangerous to human health making them an attractive option for fruit fly control in urban areas such as those found in the Risk Reduction Zone (RRZ) in NSW and Victoria [<xref rid="B13-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. </p><p>Another response to the potential risks of exotic biological control agents is the use of conservation biological control. Conservation biological control aims to maximise the impact of existing natural enemies and has proven effective in many crop/pest systems [<xref rid="B14-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There has been little research attention devoted to conservation biological control against fruit flies so the major focus of the present review is in other forms of biological control. A general limitation of many forms of biological control, however, is that the natural enemies will not typically provide adequate pest suppression alone (including braconid parasitoids), thus integration with other pest management tools such as the sterile insect technique (SIT) [<xref rid="B9-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B15-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] or bait sprays [<xref rid="B16-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] is required. The use of an integrated pest management (IPM) approach is especially important in eradicating local outbreaks of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> in Australia [<xref rid="B6-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B17-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>3. Historical Use of Biological Control for Fruit Flies in Australia</title><p>Of the eight opiine braconids that occur in Australia and are known to attack <italic>B. tryoni</italic> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], there are four that are of particular interest for use in augmentative release, not just in Australia but worldwide due largely to their ease of rearing, range of target hosts, climatic/environmental tolerance and levels of parasitism achieved. These four opiine braconids attack a range of tephritid pest species in other locations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t001">Table 1</xref>), including several species that are considered a biosecurity risk to Australia. <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> (Sonan) is an egg-pupal parasitoid [<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii</italic> (Fullaway) and <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Cameron) target late second to early third instar larvae, while <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> (Ashmead) target third instar larvae [<xref rid="B20-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-03-01056-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Of these, only <italic>D. kraussii</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> are native and have been detected from far north Qld. [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] to southern inland NSW [<xref rid="B23-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic>, although originally from Malaysia, was introduced from Hawaii and ranges from far north Qld, as far south as Sydney [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; while <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> also introduced from Hawaii, has been recorded in far north Qld and Lord Howe island [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="insects-03-01056-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">insects-03-01056-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Host records of the opiine braconids, <italic>Diachasmimorpha </italic>spp. and <italic>Fopius arisanus </italic>parasitising major tephritid pests that occur worldwide. (- indicates no record).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Major Tephritid Pests</th><th colspan="4" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Major Opiine Braconids</th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. longicaudata</italic>
</th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. kraussii</italic>
</th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. tryoni</italic>
</th><th valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F. arisanus</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Anastrepha ludens </italic>(Loew) (Mexican fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Anastrepha suspense </italic>(Loew) (Caribbean fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B26-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera cacuminata </italic>(Hering) (Wild tobacco fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera cucurbitae </italic>(Coquillett) (Melon fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B27-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera dorsalis </italic>(Hendel) (Oriental fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B28-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B28-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera latifrons </italic>(Hendel) (Malaysian fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera oleae </italic>(Gmelin) (Olive fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B32-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera papaya </italic>Drew &#x00026; Hancock (Papaya fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bactrocera tryoni </italic>(Froggatt) (Queensland fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B25-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Ceratitis</italic>
<italic>capitata </italic>(Wiedemann) (Mediterranean fruit fly)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B30-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="insects-03-01056-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A female <italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic> sp.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="insects-03-01056-g001"/></fig><p>The first effort to introduce braconids into Australia was in 1902 for the control of the Mediterranean fruit fly (<italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> Wiedemann) in Western Australia after unsuccessful searches for native natural enemies of this pest [<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Between 1932 and 1938, the NSW Department of Primary Industries (DPI) attempted biological control of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> with introductions of several thousand <italic>Tetrastichus giffardianus </italic>Silv., and small numbers of <italic>Opius humilis </italic>Silv. and <italic>O</italic>. <italic>fullawayi </italic>Silv. [<xref rid="B34-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Later, large numbers (over 205,000 in NSW alone) of <italic>Melitobia</italic> (<italic>Syntomosphyrum</italic>) <italic>indicum </italic>Silv. [<xref rid="B34-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] were released, however, all of these biological control attempts failed with none of the released species establishing [<xref rid="B34-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. There is no published literature documenting augmentative release of mass-reared parasitoids, whether native or exotic, against <italic>B. tryoni</italic> in Australia.</p></sec><sec><title>4. International Use of Biological Control for Fruit Flies</title><p>Utilising parasitic wasps for the control of fruit flies dates back to the early 1900s [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Initial attempts were centred on classical biological control whereby parasitic species associated with the target pest in its place of origin were inoculated into new geographical locations. For example, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic>, originally from south-east Asia [<xref rid="B35-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], was successfully introduced into Hawaii [<xref rid="B36-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and subsequently into Australia from Hawaii in 1956&#x02013;1957 [<xref rid="B37-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This species is now widely established in the east of Australia, including Lord Howe Island [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], as well as in Florida (USA), the south of Central America and throughout South America [<xref rid="B38-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic>, also native to south-east Asia [<xref rid="B35-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], was established in Hawaii and later Australia (1956&#x02013;1957) [<xref rid="B28-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Its introduction into other parts of the world including Israel, Mexico, and South America, however, was less successful, except in Costa Rica where it has achieved patchy establishment [<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B39-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. </p><p>Other examples of parasitoid species used in classical biological control include the native Australian species <italic>D. kraussii</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii</italic> has been successfully introduced to Israel and Hawaii [<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B41-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and while approximately 15 <italic>D. tryoni </italic>were initially released in Maui, Hawaii, around 4.1 million were later augmentatively released [<xref rid="B42-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] for control of <italic>C. capitata</italic> [<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B43-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Shortly after its introduction, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> became the most abundant parasitoid in Hawaii [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], comprising up to 33% of total parasitoids in Kula, Maui [<xref rid="B44-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Mass releases of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> in Mazapa de Madero Canyon in Mexico between 1987 and 1989 have also been successful, substantially reducing infestations in mangoes and oranges and greatly decreasing populations of <italic>Anastrepha ludens </italic>(Loew) and <italic>Anastrepha oblique </italic> (Macquart) [<xref rid="B39-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p>In recent decades, increasing interest in the active integration of parasitoids into integrated pest management programs has replaced classical biological control. This is likely to reflect not only an increased awareness of the risk of non-target impacts but also significant advancements in rearing techniques and artificial diets for rearing hosts for augmentative biological control programs [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="B47-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. These advances have allowed parasitoid wasps to be used as biological control agents against various fruit fly pests in augmentative release programs [<xref rid="B48-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="B49-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Augmentative biological control involves the supplemental release of parasitoids and relies on the mass-production of large numbers of parasitoids in a laboratory. Relatively few natural enemies may be released at a critical time of the season (inoculative release) sometimes with the expectation that reproductive populations will establish or literally millions may be released (inundative release). In addition, the crop/host plant system may be modified to support or augment the parasitoids, often known as habitat manipulation or cultural management. Parasitoids have been used successfully in augmentative release programs in Hawaii, Mexico, Guatemala and Israel [<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B39-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B51-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The major species utilised in augmentative research and control programs worldwide are <italic>D. kraussii</italic>, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic>, <italic>D. tryoni </italic>and <italic>F. arisanus</italic> with the expectation that the released parasitoids will suppress the targeted pest. A particularly successful example of augmentative biological control of fruit flies occurred in Hawaii where parasitoids dramatically reduced fruit fly (mainly <italic>Bactrocera dorsalis </italic>(Hendel) and <italic>C. capitata</italic>) densities within one year [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Trials of <italic>C. capitata</italic> control in Hawaii using the native Australian parasitoid, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> involved releasing 4.2 million parasitoids, averaging 265,000 per week, resulting in significantly lower <italic>C. capitata</italic> per fruit compared to an untreated control area [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. </p><p>Introducing biocontrol agent species to new habitats, especially in such large numbers, may raise host specificity risks [<xref rid="B9-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. For example, imported parasitoids have been reported to form new host associations [<xref rid="B53-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], sometimes with other introduced species [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Since the introduction of <italic>D. tryoni </italic>to Hawaii for the control of <italic>C. capitata</italic>, this parasitoid has formed host associations with two gall&#x02011;forming tephritids, the lantana gall fly, <italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta </italic>Aldrich, and the Pamakani gall fly, <italic>Procecidocharea utilis </italic>Stone, introduced to Hawaii for the control of weeds [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. These new host associations of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> are thought to possibly be due to the introduction of <italic>F. arisanus</italic>, a competitor of <italic>D. tryoni. Diachasmimorpha kraussii </italic>was also introduced to Hawaii for the control of <italic>Bactrocera latifrons </italic>(Hendel), the solanum fruit fly. Tests of possible host associations with native and introduced tephritid fruit flies in Hawaii found that gravid <italic>D. kraussii </italic>females would oviposit into all host larvae presented [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. These studies were performed under confined laboratory conditions in choice and no&#x02011;choice scenarios, and while it is not known whether such host associations occur in the field, the aforementioned findings illustrate the potential implications (e.g., unfavourable new host associations) of introducing a species into a new habitat and the desirability of using native parasitoids over exotics. </p></sec><sec><title>5. Mass Production of Parasitoids</title><p>A limiting factor of mass-rearing most species of parasitoids (and all that attack fruit flies) is that it requires the use of live hosts, which in turn, increases production costs [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The quality (weight and size) of the host must be appropriately monitored as parasitoid cultures from low quality hosts tend to have a male biased sex ratio [<xref rid="B56-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Hymenopteran parasitoids are haplodiploid with infertile eggs producing males and fertilised eggs producing females [<xref rid="B57-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Rearing facilities aim to optimise production of female parasitoids as females are the sex responsible for exerting biological control of the target species.</p><p>The size of host larvae is also a crucial factor for parasitoid emergence. High quality hosts that allow production of comparatively large fruit fly larvae increases parasitoid emergence [<xref rid="B56-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The age and condition of the larvae used during the rearing process is an important factor influencing both percentage emergence and sex ratio of mass reared parasitoids [<xref rid="B58-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Measurements used to monitor the quality of mass reared parasitoids include: host weight, adult emergence, survival, fecundity, flight and searching behaviour [<xref rid="B60-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Such monitoring is important because the performance of mass reared insects produced for augmentative biological control can decrease over generations due to their adaptation to laboratory conditions [<xref rid="B61-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. These changes may decrease their performance in the field and reduce the success of a parasitoid in a particular biological control program [<xref rid="B61-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Therefore, various aspects of parasitoid biology need to be considered in order to optimise the rearing of parasitoids in large numbers. </p><sec><title>5.1. Mating Behaviour</title><p>Many insect species have adult female parasitoids that respond to air- and substrate-borne male courtship signals [<xref rid="B62-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] that are pivotal to successful mating. Males usually emerge a few days before females so are ready to mate immediately when females emerge, although the optimum mating activity occurs when females are 3&#x02013;7 days old [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Five species of male parasitoids including <italic>D. tryoni</italic> and <italic>D. longicaudata</italic>, exhibit pulses produced by male wing fanning that are repeated numerous times during courtship [<xref rid="B61-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. A constraint in mass rearing is that the artificial rearing environment can affect the transmission and detection of these important courtship vibrations and thus impact rearing efficacy. Mass production can also lead to selection for mating traits that are adaptive in the rearing facility but that can adversely impact subsequent success of the female wasp when released in the field [<xref rid="B61-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. </p></sec><sec><title>5.2. Substrate Cues and Oviposition</title><p>Successful host location is a major problem for gravid parasitoids. Consequently, the exploitation of cues associated with the presence of hosts is very important in parasitoid foraging [<xref rid="B63-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and determines their success in both mass rearing and the wild. Both host larvae and their associated substrate (fruit), produce cues that trigger ovipositor-probing behaviour in gravid parasitoids [<xref rid="B62-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The cues from host larvae are mainly vibrations and/or sound created by larvae feeding and crawling inside the fruit. The cues from the host substrate are probably contact short-range volatile chemicals originating from the fermentation process caused by larval damage and/or the excrement of feeding larvae. Frugivorous tephritid larvae frequently cause bacteria-related decay of fruit, which subsequently emit chemical cues that may be used by parasitoids to search for hosts within the fruit. Chemical cues from the fermented host substrate are just as important as host vibration cues in the host searching process [<xref rid="B62-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. These chemical and/or physical cues associated with the infested fruit or produced by the feeding larvae are critical stimuli which allow female wasps to find and recognise infested fruit and available hosts [<xref rid="B43-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. If these important host cues are absent in mass rearing, or not recognised as a result of the rearing environment, the parasitoids will not commence oviposition behaviour [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. </p><p>Local arrestment of a foraging parasitoid occurs after a host-infested fruit has been located via chemical cues [<xref rid="B62-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The parasitoid female then uses her antennae to perceive locally high concentrations of the chemical cues produced by the host infestation. Parasitoids may respond to the chemical cues by increasing their rate of turning or reducing their walking speed. Vibrotaxis involves the parasitoid standing stationary on the fruit surface and using its legs to perceive vibrations caused by a feeding or moving host larva. In response to detecting vibrations, the parasitoid will probe that particular area with the ovipositor. Ovipositor probing is an essential element of host-searching behaviour [<xref rid="B44-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and commences only after successful perception of other, preliminary cues. Accordingly, ovipositor probing is used as an indicator of the level of acceptance of a specific host&#x02011;substrate [<xref rid="B43-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. </p></sec><sec><title>5.3. Emergence and Pre-Release Interventions</title><p>Host pupal weight is positively correlated with emergence percentage (e.g., <italic>D. tryoni</italic> [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]), while high larval weights produce larger adult parasitoids [<xref rid="B64-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Larval weights greater than 4 mg are considered optimal in mass-rearing to ensure maximum emergence of fruit fly parasitoids [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. A problem that can prevent parasitoid development and emergence is encapsulation. Encapsulation is the process whereby haemocytes form a multi-layered envelope around the invading organism [<xref rid="B65-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Egg encapsulation is a typical immune response by host insects in response to attack by parasitoids and has been recorded in numerous host species [<xref rid="B65-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Parasitoid eggs laid in hosts, other than the natural hosts are usually killed by encapsulation [<xref rid="B44-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Advances in rearing techniques include the use of irradiated larvae which improves parasitism rates by compromising the hosts&#x02019; immune system [<xref rid="B66-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], reducing the likelihood that immature parasitoids will be encapsulated. Irradiation of hosts also offers the advantage that only parasitised hosts will emerge and flies that are not parasitised fail to develop [<xref rid="B67-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,<xref rid="B68-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. The effect of a sublethal does of radiation is usually not apparent until the next moult [<xref rid="B69-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Radiation affects actively growing cells and large molecules of DNA [<xref rid="B70-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] and as dose increases, damage caused to the cells and DNA makes it impossible for an adult fly to develop. This is important because rates of parasitism are rarely 100% and the escape or release of unirradiated or non-sterile adult hosts from a parasitoid rearing facility could contribute to pest impact. Purcell [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] recommends a ratio of host larvae to female parasitoids of at least 15:1 in order to avoid hosts being attacked by multiple ovipositing wasps. Such super-parasitism can cause parasitoid mortality, low emergence rates and poor host quality in mass rearing [<xref rid="B13-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], however, recent studies have demonstrated that moderate levels of superparasitism by <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> in the Mexican fruit fly, <italic>A. ludens</italic>, may result in a female-biased sex ratio with few negative effects on the offspring [<xref rid="B71-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].</p><p>Mass-release of parasitoids involves transporting parasitoids to the intended area of release, a process that may take several days, during which parasitoids may suffer a decline in viability. In order to avoid this, parasitoids may be chilled (3.5&#x02013;4.5 &#x000b0;C). Larios <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B72-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] reported that there was little or no adverse effect of chilling on parasitoid longevity, production of daughters or offspring sex ratio. Methods of release for <italic>D. tryoni</italic> now include chilling followed by aerial release, similar to the method used to dispense chilled sterile fruit flies for SIT [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Chilling has no discernable effect on the short&#x02011;term mortality of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> or on its ability to take flight immediately after aerial release [<xref rid="B72-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].</p><p>The behaviour (e.g., foraging) of a parasitoid is directly linked to their nutritional state [<xref rid="B74-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="B75-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In addition, food is an essential component in maximising the reproductive success of adult female parasitoids [<xref rid="B76-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The pre-release environment provides opportunities for interventions, including pre&#x02011;release feeding to maximise longevity and fecundity [<xref rid="B74-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,<xref rid="B77-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], and the exploitation of parasitoid learning ability to maximise the chance of locating and parasitising a host [<xref rid="B78-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,<xref rid="B79-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,<xref rid="B80-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Pre-release feeding of parasitoids offers scope to maximise their performance following release, however, few studies have investigated the effect of different pre-release food types on parasitoid longevity in the laboratory or in the field. One such experiment used honey-water (50% solution by volume) as the food source to test the mating status and oviposition of <italic>D. kraussii</italic> and <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> and determine the effect on parasitoid longevity [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Zamek <italic>et al. </italic> [<xref rid="B81-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] provided 10% solutions of several diets to <italic>D. tryoni</italic>. Adult females fed white sugar had the longest lifespan whilst honey and golden syrup (56% invert syrup (glucose and fructose), 44% sucrose) resulted in similar survivorship curves. This suggests that there is a need to compare white sugar (and other food types) at varying concentrations with the current common practice in many mass-rearing facilities worldwide of providing pure honey to fruit fly parasitoids. Finding suitable hosts in which to lay their offspring is a difficult task for female parasitoid wasps. In order to overcome this location problem, female wasps use stimuli that are derived from their hosts or that indicate suitable hosts [<xref rid="B82-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,<xref rid="B83-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The use of indirect, chemical information is an important solution for parasitoid wasps to be able to detect their hosts. Parasitoids of dipteran hosts use odours of decaying substrates like fruits or carcasses to find host fly larvae. In parasitoid wasps, learning of odour cues has been the focus of most studies (e.g., [<xref rid="B83-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,<xref rid="B84-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]), however parasitoids are able to learn other cues such as colours, patterns, shapes and spatial information (e.g., [<xref rid="B82-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,<xref rid="B85-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,<xref rid="B86-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]). Parasitoids may also use learned information about the availability of suitable hosts and use that information during successive visits to other areas. For parasitoids of dipteran larvae, previous experience with unparasitized hosts reduces the acceptance of ensuing hosts that already have been parasitized [<xref rid="B87-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Parasitoids can change their innate preferences for odour cues that guide them to areas with hosts after an oviposition experience, permitting female parasitoids to find hosts sooner; possibly increasing their lifetime foraging success [<xref rid="B88-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Although learning in parasitoids is not a new area of study (for review, see [<xref rid="B78-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]), the exploitation of the learning abilities to enhance parasitoid searching success in a release program is a novel aspect requiring further investigation.</p></sec><sec><title>5.4. Release Rates and Monitoring</title><p>Release rate is also pivotal to successful augmentative release programs. In a modelling study, on no specific parasitoid species, Knipling [<xref rid="B89-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] predicted a release ratio of a larval parasitoid to pest at 3.3:1 would result in 96% parasitism, however, in practice, Sivinski [<xref rid="B90-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] preferred a ratio of parasitoid (<italic>D. longicaudata</italic>) to pest (<italic>A. suspensa</italic>) of 10:1. Knipling [<xref rid="B89-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] draws attention to the notion that different parasitoid/pest complexes will require different ratios. Control programs, therefore, need to be efficient and developed with adequate monitoring tools. Traditional monitoring methods for parasitoids rely on rearing and dissection of host material for identification and quantification of parasitism [<xref rid="B33-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B91-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. These tasks can be tedious, as <italic>B. tryoni</italic> does not emerge until fourteen days after pupation and parasitoids at least a further two days. Furthermore, related parasitoid species often have few or no morphologically distinguishable features in the immature stage [<xref rid="B91-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], making it impossible for identification after dissection. In systems where quick identification and quantification of parasitism levels are required, such as in augmentative releases programs, molecular diagnostic tools would be of great use [<xref rid="B92-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. With rapid advancements of molecular genetics, a new wealth of techniques have been developed that are relevant [<xref rid="B92-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="B93-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] and applicable for augmentative release program monitoring. Data, such as current parasitism levels, could be quickly processed, and a decision made to release further parasitoids if required. Molecular techniques have been used to monitor the incidence of parasitism in other species [<xref rid="B93-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], however, they have not been applied to the parasitoids of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> nor has molecular identification been implemented as a monitoring tool for <italic>B. tryoni</italic> parasitism in field collected samples [<xref rid="B92-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. </p><p>A final problem associated with mass-production and augmentative release of biological control agents is that the large numbers of released insects can modify the genetic structure of the wild population by mating with wild individuals. This &#x0201c;reverse bottleneck&#x0201d; is an instance in which the genetic structure of a population is diluted in the presence of a more numerous domesticated population of differing genetic structure [<xref rid="B42-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This effect can be overcome by regularly infusing laboratory cultures with fresh &#x02018;wild&#x02019; specimens to ensure the genetic diversity of the original wild population is maintained.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>6. Prospects for Parasitoid-Based Biological Control of Fruit Flies in Australia</title><p>Despite the success of parasitoids as agents in international augmentative tephritid biological control programs, parasitoids have not yet been used for augmentative release in Australia against <italic>B. tryoni</italic> or <italic>C. capitata</italic>, the two key economic fruit fly pests in Australia. Mass-rearing facilities for <italic>B. tryoni</italic> and <italic>C. capitata</italic> are located in NSW and Western Australia, respectively. These facilities currently produce flies for the sterile insect technique (SIT), and could be a source or expand production to supply host material for parasitoid rearing. As 70% of the cost of parasitoid rearing is associated with the production of host material [<xref rid="B94-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>] the existence of host rearing infrastructure and expertise in Australia is a benefit to the economics of parasitoid rearing. </p><p>Information on the biology of parasitoids is of great value in developing and improving mass&#x02011;rearing techniques and augmentative release programs [<xref rid="B95-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Accordingly, to assess the potential utilisation of available parasitoid species for biological control of fruit flies in Australia, the following sections review key aspects of parasitoid biology, together with available information on the methods that are used for the study of fruit flies and their parasitoids, focusing particularly on the four major opiine braconids, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic>, <italic>D. kraussi</italic>, <italic>D. tryoni</italic>, and <italic>F. arisanus </italic>that are currently being considered for augmentative biological control.</p><sec><title>6.1. Suitability of Parasitoid to Release into the Environment</title><sec><title>6.1.1. Climate Matching</title><p>Information on the thermal biology of parasitoids is important in assessing their utility in augmentative biological control as this allows their effective range to be determined by using models such as CLIMEX. A complementary approach for assessing the zones in which a given parasitoid may have potential as an augmentative biological control agent is to study their spatial and seasonal abundance. This can indicate currently unoccupied areas into which the parasitoid could be released and is of particular relevance to Australia, where <italic>B. tryoni</italic> exists in some regions as a meta-population. This is a result of the large size of the country, highly variable climatic zones, presence of areas of irrigated horticulture and towns in otherwise uninhabitable arid vegetation, combined with high levels of human movement for commerce and leisure.</p><p>The distribution of <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> is temperature delimited to areas with mean temperatures above 10.5 &#x000b0;C and below 30 &#x000b0;C, despite the presence of its host in the region at these temperatures. The longevity of adult <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> is reduced to 3 days at constant temperatures above 30 &#x000b0;C [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. At moderate temperatures (15 &#x000b0;C to 25 &#x000b0;C), longevity decreases with increasing temperature (from 19 days down to 7 days, respectively). Caution is, however, required in interpreting the results from such laboratory studies in which constant temperatures are used. Diurnal fluctuations in the field are likely to allow parasitoids respite and allow foraging for hosts [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This is important because summer temperatures in some <italic>B. tryoni</italic>-infested zones of Australia can exceed 30 &#x000b0;C. An additional point of caution regarding the longevities cited in the aforementioned study is that humidity was not regulated in the experiments. Future work should aim to match humidity levels to those likely to be encountered in the field as this can strongly affect longevity. For example, <italic>D. kraussii</italic> survived up to 30 days at 25 &#x000b0;C and 60% relative humidity (RH) [<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], surviving significantly longer than when humidity was not controlled [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>The longevity of <italic>D. kraussii</italic> also decreases with increasing temperatures over the range likely to be encountered in the field in Australia (e.g., from 36 days to 11 days at 15 &#x000b0;C to 25 &#x000b0;C) [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. While both adult <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> and <italic>D. kraussii</italic> can survive for only 3 days at constant temperatures above 30 &#x000b0;C, <italic>D. kraussii </italic>is more likely to be able to survive high temperatures than <italic>D. longicaudata </italic>by resting in the heat of the day and foraging at cooler times [<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Information is sparse for <italic>D. tryoni</italic> and <italic>F. arisanus </italic>but it has been reported for the latter that it does not survive below 15.5 &#x000b0;C [<xref rid="B96-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], although maximum threshold temperatures have not been studied. The impact of high temperatures on all of these species could be ameliorated to some extent, however, by allowing adult parasitoids to feed and mate prior to releases being made in summer months. Potentially, adults should also be held for several days under favourable storage conditions to allow egg maturation so that adult females are able to parasitise available hosts immediately upon release. </p></sec><sec><title>6.1.2. Field Sampling</title><p>The study of parasitoids and their potential as biological control agents is underpinned by field surveys in which the parasitoid fauna is determined. Because of its fundamental importance, the literature on sampling methods is detailed. Fruit harbouring hosts, and potentially parasitoids, can be collected from research orchards [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], backyards [<xref rid="B28-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B97-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>], or bushland [<xref rid="B97-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Fruit has rarely been sampled from commercial orchards because pesticides used in these settings, along with the practice of collection and destruction of fallen fruit, are likely to lead to low parasitoid densities [<xref rid="B99-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Parasitoids can be collected by direct capture of adults in the field, utilising some form of aspirator [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or rearing them from parasitised hosts within infested fruits. The latter collection technique is often preferred as this will also indicate the identity of hosts [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,<xref rid="B101-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>].</p><p>Due to the polyphagous nature of most tephritids, both native and exotic fruit trees need to be surveyed [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="B99-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. As host plant species fruit at different times of the year and for different lengths of time, sampling must reflect such temporal trends. It is important, therefore, to build up a database of trees in the sampling area and revisit these sampling sites throughout the fruiting season. Sampling needs to include fallen fruit as well as fruit on the trees as different host insects preferentially target these resources [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="B97-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Lopez <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] advocate climbing trees or the use of a ladder, with fruit collected in a bucket attached to a pole. In a research orchard, this may be practical; however, it may be cumbersome when collecting in multiple locations throughout the day. Fruit ready to abscise will give the best indication of natural parasitism levels as the pest larvae in the fruit have been exposed to parasitoids for the maximum possible period of time [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B66-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In order to determine if fruit is ready to drop, tree branches can be gently shaken [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B66-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Picking fruit that is not completely ripe can lead to an underestimation of parasitism rates due to the decrease in the period where larvae are susceptible to attack, with some larvae having never been vulnerable to attack (dependent upon oviposition preferences of parasitoid species present) [<xref rid="B47-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. This also allows a shorter rearing time as the larvae are more likely to be near pupation [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In order to alleviate this issue, Wong <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] dissected fruit at collection, removing mature larvae for rearing. In a different approach, Sivinski [<xref rid="B66-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] considered only larvae which exited fruit within three days of sampling. </p><p>Collections have been made at weekly [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] to monthly intervals [<xref rid="B102-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] for periods of seven months [<xref rid="B23-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], twelve months [<xref rid="B99-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] to two years [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Sample size differed with quantity and fruit varieties available [<xref rid="B97-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,<xref rid="B103-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>] or time spent sampling [<xref rid="B102-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Sample size ranged from five per tree per week [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] to 2&#x02013;100 pieces of fruit of each type of fruit available [<xref rid="B28-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The concurrent collection of site and management data is important for the full interpretation of trends. For example, any pesticide applications need to be noted [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].</p><p>In tropical regions especially, native fruit trees may act as alternate hosts for pest fruit flies and therefore require sampling for parasitoids [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Longer fruiting seasons in these regions are also likely to lead to higher numbers of parasitoids, as well as pests, and would be good locations for collections when the aim is to establish or supplement parasitoid colonies. In more temperate regions, such alternative host plants may be less readily available. There may however, be non-pest species of fruit flies that act as hosts for parasitoids when the major economic pest is not available. </p><sec><title>6.1.2.1. Sentinel Fruits</title><p>The use of sentinel fruits, fruit items infested with host larvae and placed out in a sampling pattern and collected later for study, can be particularly useful for determining whether a parasitoid species prefers to forage within the canopy or on fallen fruit [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. There is conflicting evidence in the literature as to whether or not sentinel fruits maximise the general efficiency of collection of parasitic wasps. It was suggested by Jessup and Walsh [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] that the use of sentinel fruits optimises the collection of wild parasitic wasps due to the extended amount of time the fruit remains in the field. However, Hernandez&#x02011;Ortiz <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B99-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] found that fruit picked directly at the site had parasitism rates more than twice as high as sentinel fruits (68.5% <italic>versus</italic> 31.5%). </p><p>Sentinel fruits should ideally be placed in the field within a layered container system, consisting of one vessel with holes above another containing a pupation medium. Protection from rain is provided by a final container or sheet of fiberglass or similar material. A gap of 50&#x02013;100 cm will allow parasitoids to detect the fruit fly infested fruit and enter [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Adhesives such as Tanglefoot (Grand Rapids, MI, USA) will protect the sentinel fruits from ants [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The use of a cover is important to prevent sunburn of sentinel fruits [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Generally, the use of sentinel fruits is best restricted to sites with controlled access, where human disturbance is unlikely. </p></sec><sec><title>6.1.2.2. Sample Processing</title><p>Samples can be returned to the laboratory in labeled paper bags [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>], labeled plastic bags [<xref rid="B104-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>] or directly into the vessels in which wasps will be reared-out (see below). Where possible, fruit should be transported to the laboratory on a daily basis [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] in order to reduce the risk of spoilage. To determine the identity of host fruit flies, fruits should be placed in individual containers [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] until the emergence of pests or parasitoids [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Moistened vermiculite [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B102-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], sand [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>] or soil [<xref rid="B99-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] can be used as a pupation medium, usually with a depth of 1 cm [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Ventilation of containers can be achieved by cutting a hole in the container lid and covering with mesh [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. This also prevents flies and wasps escaping and <italic>Drosophila</italic> spp. from entering and contaminating the culture [<xref rid="B105-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Where only one species of fruit fly is expected or where host records are not of concern, fruit can be placed in bulk lots consisting of a single fruit type from each location [<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Whether rearing out in individual or bulk containers, it is preferable to elevate fruit above the pupation medium [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. This can be achieved by using sieves with holes large enough to allow larvae to pass through after exiting the fruit [<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>], wire mesh [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], or suspending the fruit with netting [<xref rid="B104-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. </p></sec><sec><title>6.1.2.3. Sample Maintenance</title><p>Recommendations on sample maintenance vary from daily [<xref rid="B102-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], to once a week [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Fruit should be checked for mould and moistness of media regularly, but may only need attention at longer intervals [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,<xref rid="B98-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Several researchers, including Sivinski <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], Aguiar-Menezes <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B97-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] and Mkize <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="B100-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>], advocate sifting media every second day and counting or moving pupae to fresh vermiculite in a separate rearing container. This practice, however, is very time consuming for large scale survey work. At 26 &#x000b0;C, all host larvae will leave the fruit within two weeks [<xref rid="B106-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], however, if the fruit is completely covered with mould it should be dissected earlier to determine if all larvae have emerged [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Earlier dissection will prevent fruit rotting fungi (e.g., <italic>Penicilium</italic> spp.) progressing to attack the pupae. If larvae are not found in the fruit, the fruit sample may be discarded. If immature larvae are found, the fruit, or the least non-rotten portion, should be returned to the container to allow the larvae to complete their lifecycle [<xref rid="B105-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Artificial diets are useful for rearing larvae recovered from decomposing fruit, but if only a few fruits yield larvae, it may not be economical. Emergence of flies and wasps should be assessed every three days [<xref rid="B55-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] for approximately four weeks [<xref rid="B21-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B26-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Many parasitoid species enter diapauses so uneclosed pupae should either be retained for up to twelve months [<xref rid="B73-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] or dissected to identify the developing imago. Wing venation, however, is an important distinguishing feature between the braconid genera <italic>Fopius</italic> and <italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic> [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, it is preferable to allow natural eclosion of adults so that this identification feature is well developed. Dead pupae can be reconstituted by soaking in water for 48&#x02013;96 hours. Dissection of the re-hydrated pupae enables detection of at least basic features that will discriminate flies from wasps [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Alternatively, molecular analyses for identification can be used in this situation [<xref rid="B92-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>6.2. Host Range and the Risk of Non-Target Impact</title><p><italic>Fopius arisanus</italic>, <italic>D. kraussii</italic>, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> all attack a wide range of tephritid fruit flies, including species native to and exotic to Australia, not all of which are pests. Potentially a wide host range facilitates biological control by allowing a parasitoid to persist and reproduce in an area during times of local scarcity of the target (pest) by exploiting other (non-pest) host species. Offsetting this, however, is the fact that risk to a non-target host can make regulatory authorities reluctant to allow biological control programs. This is certainly the case when a classical biological control introduction is being considered but may also apply to augmentative biological control that will increase local parasitoid abundance and increase the magnitude of risk.</p><sec><title>6.2.1. Non-Target Impacts</title><p>Tephritidae are grouped into several sub-families and include fruit feeders (commonly referred to as fruit flies), gall-formers and flower-feeders [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Tephritid flies are parasitised by wasps in the subfamilies Opiinae (Fam. Braconidae), Dirhininae (Fam. Chalcidae), Euderinae, Tetrastichinae and Entedoninae (Fam. Eulophidae) [<xref rid="B107-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. It is commonly assumed that the opiine braconids coevolved with their frugivorous tephritid hosts [<xref rid="B35-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], however, there are reports of opiine braconids also parasitizing gall-formers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t002">Table 2</xref>) and flower-feeding tephritid flies worldwide (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t003">Table 3</xref>). </p><table-wrap id="insects-03-01056-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">insects-03-01056-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Non-target impacts of opiine braconids, <italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic>, <italic>Fopius</italic>, <italic>Psyttalia</italic>, and <italic>Tetrastichus</italic> spp., on gall-forming tephritids. (- indicates no record).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasitoid</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oviposition recorded in gall</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oviposition into larvae in artificial diet</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasitoid able to complete lifecycle</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threat</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Phaeogramma lortnocoibon</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. longicaudata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. longicaudata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B109-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares alani</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. longicaudata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares utilis</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. kraussii</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. kraussii</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Phaeogramma lortnocoibon</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. tryoni</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares alani</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. tryoni</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. tryoni</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,<xref rid="B110-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares alani</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F. ceratitivorus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B111-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Phaeogramma lortnocoibon</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P. fletcheri</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares alani</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P. fletcheri</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B109-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P. fletcheri</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B112-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Procecidochares alani</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T. giffardianus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="insects-03-01056-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">insects-03-01056-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Non-target impacts of opiine braconids, <italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic>, <italic>Fopius</italic>, and <italic>Psyttalia</italic> spp., on flower-feeding tephritids. (- indicates no record).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasitoid</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oviposition recorded in flowerhead</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oviposition into larvae in artificial diet</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parasitoid able to complete lifecycle</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threat</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. longicaudata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B113-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ensina sonchi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. kraussii</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. kraussii</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D. </italic>
<italic>tryoni</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ensina sonchi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>D.</italic>
<italic> tryoni</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F. arisanus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F. ceratitivorus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B111-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P. fletcheri</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B113-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F. caudatus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02713;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000d7;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very low</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Most research on the non-target effects of opiine parasitoids has been conducted in Hawaii, where there are native and introduced gall-formers, the latter introduced for weed biocontrol [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] and flower feeders which are important pollinators of rare and endemic plants [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Four gall-formers have been introduced into Hawaii from Mexico for weed biological control: <italic>E. xanthochaeta </italic>Aldrich, for the control of the woody weed lantana (<italic>Lantana camara </italic>L.), pamakani gall fly, <italic>Procecidochares alani </italic>Stekyskal, for the control of pamakani weeds, and <italic>Ageratina riparia </italic>(Regel) and <italic>P. utilis </italic>for the control of crofton weed, <italic>Ageratina adenophorum </italic> Spreng. The bidens gall fly, <italic>Phaeogramma lortnocoibon </italic>Asquith, is endemic to Kauai Island, Hawaii and is associated solely with the plant, <italic>Bidens cosmoides </italic> (A. Gray) Sherff [<xref rid="B52-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B109-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,<xref rid="B112-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. There have been a number of laboratory studies into non-target impacts of fruit fly parasitoids with such gall-formers (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t002">Table 2</xref>). It is suggested that some <italic>Diachasmimorpha</italic> spp. parasitise <italic>E. xanthochaeta </italic>galls due to the favourable ratio of ovipositor length to gall wall thickness [<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. However, in choice tests, <italic>D. kraussii</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> preferred frugivorous flies in fruit or artificial diet over gall flies [<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B110-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. When tested against their natal host, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> preferred to oviposit into coffee berries rather than lantana stem galls [<xref rid="B110-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], although wasps emerging from <italic>E. xanthochaeta</italic> probed their natal host more frequently than those emerging from <italic>C. capitata</italic> [<xref rid="B114-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Field studies have recovered <italic>D. tryoni</italic>, <italic>Eurytoma tephritidis</italic> Fullaway (Eurytomidae), and <italic>Bracon terryi</italic> (Bridwell) (Braconidae: Braconinae) from mature galls [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Field releases of <italic>D. longicaudata </italic>in lantana patches resulted in 0.8% parasitism [<xref rid="B109-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. These results are supported by field surveys by Duan <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B112-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>] on the parasitoid complex attacking <italic>E. xanthochaeta</italic>, showing <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> to be the least abundant parasitoid. These results and previous data confirm <italic>D. tryoni</italic> as the most abundant parasitoid of <italic>E. xanthochaeta</italic>, comprising over 85% of the parasitoid complex [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B115-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. <italic>Eurytoma tephritidis</italic>, and <italic>B. terryi</italic> are also major parasitoids of <italic>E. xanthochaeta </italic>galls in Hawaii [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. <italic>Psyttalia fletcheri </italic>(Silvestri),introduced from India for the control of melon fly, <italic>Bactrocera cucurbitae</italic> Coquillett, has never been recorded parasitising gall-forming tephritids in Hawaii [<xref rid="B115-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. <italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic> galls harvested near <italic>D. tryoni</italic> releases and in non&#x02011;release areas showed no significant increase in parasitism of galls when 100,000 <italic>D. tryoni</italic> adults were released per hectare per week [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> parasitised significantly more <italic>E. xanthochaeta</italic> as the elevation increased and land use moved from agriculture to native forest [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Overall, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> was more abundant in the highland habitat areas [<xref rid="B36-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B116-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. In this cooler, more humid area, lantana was much more abundant (and therefore the number of galls present were higher), providing increased off-target opportunities, however, there was also an abundance of strawberry guava trees, <italic>Psidium littorale </italic>var. <italic>cattleianum</italic> (Sabine) which harboured <italic>C. capitata</italic> and Oriental fruit fly, <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>. Regardless of larval host, gravid females strongly favoured fruit hosts to lantana stem galls. The finding that <italic>D. tryoni</italic> incidence was correlated with site but not with gall density [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], supports the theory of climate preference and presence of the usual host, rather than preference for gall flies. Duan <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B45-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] suggest that the parasitoids are attracted to the habitats of the preferred host, where less preferred hosts may also be present. </p><p>Laboratory studies also show scope for non-target impacts of fruit fly parasitoids on flower-feeders (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t003">Table 3</xref>). Generally, flower-feeding tephritids are at less risk of attack by opine parasitoids than are gall-forming tephritids and it has been suggested that galls are more attractive to fruit fly parasitoids as they are more similar in shape and size to fruit than flowerheads [<xref rid="B113-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. The number of visits to, and probing of flowerheads, was low and not significantly different in the presence or absence of normal fruit fly hosts [<xref rid="B7-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The exception is <italic>E. sonchi </italic>and <italic>D. tryoni</italic>, with the presence of <italic>C. capitata </italic>significantly decreasing off-target interactions [<xref rid="B54-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Whilst these braconids are not likely to affect <italic>T. dubautiae </italic>and <italic>E. sonchi</italic> in the field, the chalcids <italic>Habrocytus elevatus </italic>(Pteromalidae) and <italic>Euderus metallicus </italic>(Eulophidae) have been observed to attack <italic>Trupanea </italic>spp. in the wild [<xref rid="B113-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>].</p><p>Other than extrapolation from the international studies reviewed above, there is little information available on the risks of non-target effects in Australia. Flower-feeding tephritid genera in Australia comprise <italic>Dioxyna</italic>, <italic>Tephritis</italic> and <italic>Trupanea </italic>spp., which feed on Asteraceaous plants, and <italic>Oedaspoides</italic>, which feed on Goodeniaceae plants [<xref rid="B107-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. There is no information, however, on attack, if any, by parasitoids. In the case of gall-forming tephritidae, there is anecdotal evidence of the parasitoids <italic>D. tryoni</italic> and <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> (both present in Australia) attacking <italic>P. utilis </italic>in Hawaii [<xref rid="B108-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The latter tephritid was introduced to NSW and QLD for the biological control of crofton weed [<xref rid="B107-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Although there do not appear to be any records of attack in Australia, the risk of attack could be elevated if augmentative releases were made and is indicative of the more general need for caution in the use of these parasitoids in biological control. The vulnerability of a non-target host to a parasitoid depends upon the attractiveness of a host for oviposition and its physiological suitability for the completion of the parasitoids&#x02019; lifecycle [<xref rid="B109-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. These biological factors, which also have a bearing on the more general suitability of the parasitoid for mass rearing and use in augmentative biological control, are examined for species of relevance to Australia in the following sections.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>6.3. Parasitoid Biology</title><sec><title>6.3.1. Fecundity</title><p><italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> compares favourably with other parasitoids for reproductive output, regardless of host. When reared on <italic>A. ludens</italic>, <italic>B. dorsalis</italic> and <italic>B. oleae</italic>, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> produced 187, 93 and 24 offspring per female, respectively. When reared on <italic>A. ludens</italic>, <italic>F. arisanus</italic> produced less than half of this number of offspring (71 offspring), whilst <italic>D. tryoni</italic> produced just under half as many offspring as <italic>F. arisanus</italic> (39 offspring). When reared on <italic>B. dorsalis</italic>, <italic>F. arisanus</italic> produced 199 eggs per female and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> produced 50 eggs per female on <italic>C. capitata</italic>. When reared on its ancestral host (<italic>B. tryoni</italic>) in an artificial diet, <italic>D. kraussii</italic> produced 112 offspring; on <italic>B. oleae</italic> in olives, the result was much lower, at 23 offspring. <italic>Anastrepha ludens</italic> trials were conducted in mango fruits, <italic>B. oleae</italic> trials in olives and <italic>B. tryoni</italic> on artificial diet [<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B31-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. </p></sec><sec><title>6.3.2. Longevity</title><p>Adult longevity is an important attribute of parasitoid utility [<xref rid="B20-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. At 25&#x02013;26 &#x000b0;C and 60% RH, <italic>F. arisanus</italic> had the greatest longevity (69 days) of the parasitoids potentially available for use in augmentative biological control in Australia. The next most long-lived species is <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> (51 days). The native species <italic>D. kraussii</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> have shorter lifespans at 30 and 26 days, respectively. Adult <italic>F. arisanus</italic> that emerged from <italic>C. capitata</italic> and <italic>A. serpentina</italic> had shorter life spans of 54 and 49 days, respectively, indicating host has an effect on longevity of the adult parasitoid [<xref rid="B22-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B117-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Pre-release feeding can increase adult longevity and subsequent parasitoid success in the field [<xref rid="B118-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. A related biological attribute to longevity is generation time. <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> had similar generation times (23 and 22 days, respectively), whilst <italic>F. arisanus</italic> was almost double (42 days). The longer generation time of <italic>F. arisanus</italic> makes field establishment more difficult than for the other two species [<xref rid="B24-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>6.3.3. Ease of Rearing</title><p>Whilst the egg parasitoid <italic>F. arisanus</italic> may give better fruit fly control in the field as it attacks earlier in the lifecycle of the pest than do the other larval parasitoid species [<xref rid="B19-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], it is known to be difficult to culture [<xref rid="B119-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> is known to be amenable to mass-rearing as large numbers (4.1 million/week) have been achieved in production facilities in Hawaii [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Similarly, both <italic>D. kraussii</italic> [<xref rid="B40-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> [<xref rid="B120-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>] are suitable for mass-rearing. Furthermore, although mass releases of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> and <italic>D. kraussii</italic> have not been tested against <italic>B. tryoni</italic>, they have led to the successful control of other fruit flies including <italic>C. capitata</italic>. </p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>7. Conclusion</title><p><italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> poses an enormous threat to the sustainability of Australian horticulture. In particular, the Fruit Fly Exclusion Zone (FFEZ) which provides <italic>B. tryoni</italic>-free areas permitting Australian producers to export to areas which are climatically favourable to <italic>B. tryoni</italic> and therefore, are susceptible to outbreaks. If <italic>B. tryoni</italic> cannot be managed effectively in both the FFEZ and RRZ, Australia&#x02019;s economy may suffer from limited exports, as well as widespread crop damage. A solution to the over reliance on chemical insecticides is to develop a more integrated system to control populations in the RRZ and other endemic areas and stop their incursion into the FFEZ and other major endemic horticultural production areas. Parasitoids offer an attractive means of achieving this. </p><p>Of the four parasitoid species currently available in Australia for possible use in an augmentative biological control program against <italic>B. tryoni</italic>, <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> and <italic>F. arisanus</italic> have the longest adult longevity and highest fecundity. However, as they cannot survive below 15 &#x000b0;C, they are probably unsuitable for Australia&#x02019;s major horticultural production regions within the FFEZ and surrounding RRZ in inland NSW, Australia. These species also parasitise a wide range of fruit fly species and are therefore more likely to constitute a risk to non-target tephritid species, including natives and any introduced for biological control of weeds. The native parasitoids <italic>D. kraussii </italic> and <italic>D. tryoni</italic> were the only <italic>B. tryoni</italic> parasitoids detected in a survey undertaken in inland NSW [<xref rid="B23-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and are thus likely to be better suited climatically to this region. <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> appears to be better adapted to cooler climates than other parasitoids [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] (<xref ref-type="table" rid="insects-03-01056-t004">Table 4</xref>) and could therefore be released early in the season before large <italic>B. tryoni</italic> populations become established, or to deal with localised, early season outbreaks. Mature larvae of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> enter a winter diapause within host puparia [<xref rid="B44-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and emerge at the beginning of the season at the same time that <italic>B. tryoni</italic> emerge. Surveys have shown that <italic>D. tryoni</italic> is more abundant at higher elevations (greater than 600 metres) where temperatures are generally lower than at sea level [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The distribution of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> is similar to that of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> and occurs in all commercial fruit crops (except pineapple and strawberries) and many vegetable crops [<xref rid="B121-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="insects-03-01056-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">insects-03-01056-t004_Table 4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of characteristics for the two Australian native parasitoids of <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> (Adapted from [<xref rid="B18-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B29-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B40-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1">Australian native parasitoids of <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic>
</th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Life stage attacked</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larva</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larva</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temporal pattern</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detected early in the season (cold tolerance)</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detected late in the season (heat tolerance)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical pattern</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Found in areas of higher elevation. </td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relatively large geographical range</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult longevity</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;25 days </td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;30 days </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous use on augmentative release</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous success in Hawaii and Mexico</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous success in Hawaii.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Importantly for augmentative releases, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> is known to be amenable to mass-rearing [<xref rid="B50-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Additionally, although mass releases of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> have not been tested against <italic>B. tryoni</italic>, they have led to the successful control of other fruit flies such as <italic>C. capitata</italic>. Being suited to mass release in inland NSW is attractive because a widespread augmentative biological control program could decrease <italic>B. tryoni</italic> pest pressure on the FFEZ and also be used against isolated outbreaks within the FFEZ.</p><p>While the available information supports the viability of augmentative releases of <italic>D. tryoni</italic> against <italic>B. tryoni</italic> in inland NSW, there are large knowledge gaps concerning mass-rearing techniques, host specificity, and success rates. Although it is native to Australia, <italic>D tryoni</italic> has never been mass-reared for release in Australia or been field tested under Australian conditions. This information is critical to the success of biological control. Further, techniques that could optimise the mass-rearing process, such as an optimal food source for pre-release feeding and the influence of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> host size to maximise longevity and fecundity, have not been extensivelt explored for <italic>D. tryoni</italic> although literature is available for closely related species that indicates appropriate methods to fill these knowledge gaps. There have been non-target effects from the release of <italic>D. tryoni </italic>on gall forming fruit flies introduced to Hawaii as biological control agents of the weed <italic>L. camara</italic> [<xref rid="B122-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Yet because <italic>D. tryoni</italic> is native to eastern Australia, where no gall forming insects have been recorded as hosts [<xref rid="B110-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], they are unlikely to have equivalent non-target effects in Australia. <italic>Lantana camara</italic> is a pest weed in Australia, however, the biological control agents used to control it do not include gall-forming tephritids [<xref rid="B123-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. </p><p>Like most parasitoids, <italic>D. tryoni</italic> is susceptible to insecticides even at exposure rates well under the recommended field application rates used for <italic>B. tryoni</italic> control [<xref rid="B47-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Insecticides known to be harmful to <italic>D. tryoni</italic>, include carbaryl, permethrin and malathion [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The application of insecticides to control <italic>B. tryoni</italic> or other insect pests could significantly reduce the success of biological control against <italic>B. tryoni</italic> [<xref rid="B47-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and this needs to be considered in integrated pest management strategies. Targeted bait spraying is potentially less harmful to natural enemies because widespread application of toxins is avoided, however, baits containing sugars are potentially attractive to adult parasitoids. The combination of GF-120 bait sprays and biological control using <italic>D. tryoni</italic> has been described as a compatible control option [<xref rid="B124-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. The field effect of baits such as GF-120 has never been tested with <italic>D. tryoni</italic>, although mortality is known from direct exposure in laboratory conditions [<xref rid="B124-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Thus, further research is required.</p><p>A more harmonious combination of control methods for <italic>B. tryoni</italic> is the release of parasitoids together with SIT [<xref rid="B125-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. These two techniques complement each other because they act on two different stages of <italic>B. tryoni</italic> (larvae and mating adult). A synergistic suppressive action can lead to local pest eradication [<xref rid="B89-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. This occurs as parasitoids tend to have a greater impact on relatively dense host populations because hosts are easy to locate and the parasitoid is able to reproduce efficiently. In contrast, SIT is expensive to use against large, dense pest populations but becomes more cost effective at lower pest densities [<xref rid="B126-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Thus, parasitoids are generally released before sterile insects as parasitoids will suppress pest populations and reduce the number of sterile insects needed to achieve acceptable over-flooding ratios [<xref rid="B46-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Success with SIT and biological control has been analysed in Mexico with <italic>D. longicaudata</italic> [<xref rid="B56-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The use of both techniques helped to create fly-free zones, which allowed access to new markets valued at US $15 million [<xref rid="B56-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. There is evidence of this synergistic relationship in studies with <italic>F. arisanus</italic> and <italic>D. kraussii</italic> [<xref rid="B40-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and in the control of other insect pests such as codling moth [<xref rid="B10-insects-03-01056" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Research into IPM strategies involving SIT and <italic>D. tryoni </italic>(or indeed other parasitoid species), however, have not been conducted in Australia and should be further researched to establish the ability of combining SIT and other biological control methods to eradicate and/or suppress <italic>B. tryoni</italic> in the FFEZ and RRZ.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Catherine Gulliver is thanked for assistance with manuscript preparation. This work has been funded by Horticulture Australia Ltd. using Riverina Citrus Voluntary Contributions and matched funds from the Australian Government, the EH Graham Centre and the Rural Management Research Institute of the University of Sydney.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-insects-03-01056"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weldon</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylow</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The ecology of <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae): What do we know to assist pest management?</article-title>
<source>Ann. Appl. Biol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>158</volume>
<fpage>26</fpage>
<lpage>54</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7348.2010.00448.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-insects-03-01056"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dominiak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Queensland fruit fly</article-title>
<source>NSW Department of Primary Industries: Primefacts #250</source>
<publisher-name>N.S.W. Department of Primary Industries</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>NSW, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>2007</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-insects-03-01056"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meats</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgerton</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Short- and long-range dispersal of the Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic>, and its relevance to invasive potential, sterile insect technique and surveillance trapping</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Exp. Agr.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>1237</fpage>
<lpage>1245</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/EA07291</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-insects-03-01056"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<article-title>Plant Protection Service. Fruit fly control methods for Pacific Island countries and territories</article-title>
<source>Pest Advisory Leaflet</source>
<publisher-name>Secretariat of the Pacific Community</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Suva, Fiji Islands</publisher-loc>
<year>2001</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-insects-03-01056"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dominiak</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Further development of a low-cost release method for sterile Queensland fruit fly <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> (Froggatt) in rural New South Wales</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Exp. Agr.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>407</fpage>
<lpage>417</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/EA01145</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-insects-03-01056"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meats</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duthie</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clift</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominiak</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Trials on variants of the sterile insect technique (SIT) for suppression of populations of the Queensland fruit fly in small towns neighbouring a quarantine (exclusion) zone</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Exp. Agr.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>395</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/EA02064</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-insects-03-01056"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokonon-Ganta</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Egg-larval opiine parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) of tephritid fruit fly pests do not attack the flowerhead-feeder <italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>J. Appl. Entomol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>716</fpage>
<lpage>722</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0418.2004.00920.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-insects-03-01056"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knipling</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of parasitoid augmentation and sterile insect techniques in areawide management of agricultural insect pests</article-title>
<source>J. Agr. Entomol.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>273</fpage>
<lpage>301</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-insects-03-01056"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vreysen</surname><given-names>M.J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ionising radiation and area-wide management of insect pests to promote sustainable agriculture. A review</article-title>
<source>Agron. Sustain. Dev.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>233</fpage>
<lpage>250</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/agro/2010009</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-insects-03-01056"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cossentine</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Releases of <italic>Trichogramma platneri</italic> (Hymenoptera: Trichogrammatidae) in apple orchards under a sterile codling moth release program</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.2000.0828</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-insects-03-01056"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarovits</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goettel</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Adventures in Biocontrol</source>
<publisher-name>Cromwell Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>
<year>2007</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-insects-03-01056"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitthawee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dujardin</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> complex: Reproductive isolation and geometric patterns of the wing</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>191</fpage>
<lpage>197</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.06.011</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-insects-03-01056"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Suppression of a Mediterranean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) population with concurrent parasitoid and sterile fly releases in Kula, Maui, Hawaii</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1992</year>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>1671</fpage>
<lpage>1681</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-insects-03-01056"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wratten</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Biodiversity and insect Pests: Key Issues for Sustainable Management</source>
<publisher-name>Wiley Blackwell Oxford</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>
<year>2012</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-insects-03-01056"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kvedaras</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Synergizing biological control: Scope for sterile insect technique, induced plant defences and cultural techniques to enhance natural enemy impact</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>198</fpage>
<lpage>207</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.02.013</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-insects-03-01056"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuate</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potential for areawide integrated management of Mediterranean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) with a braconid parasitoid and a novel bait spray</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>817</fpage>
<lpage>825</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493-94.4.817</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11561838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-insects-03-01056"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherst</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collyer</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonow</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The vulnerability of Australian horticulture to the Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera (Dacus) tryoni</italic>, under climate change</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Agr. Res.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>467</fpage>
<lpage>480</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR98203</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-insects-03-01056"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Opiine parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) of tropical fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) of the Australian and South Pacific region</article-title>
<source>Bull. Entomol. Res.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>545</fpage>
<lpage>569</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16336703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-insects-03-01056"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative demography of six fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1049-9644(02)00046-4</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-insects-03-01056"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Desirable attributes of mass reared parasitoids for fruit fly control: A comment</article-title>
<source>Vedalia</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>53</fpage>
<lpage>58</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-insects-03-01056"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Breeding of Fruit Fly Parasitoids for Inundative Release</source>
<publisher-name>NSW Agriculture</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Gosford, NSW, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>1997</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-insects-03-01056"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rungrojwanich</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The Australian fruit fly parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii</italic> (Fullaway): Life history, ovipositional patterns, distribution and hosts (Hymenoptera: Braconidae: Opiinae)</article-title>
<source>Pan-Pac. Entomol.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-insects-03-01056"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spinner</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>O.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parasitoid fauna of Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni</italic> Froggatt (Diptera: Tephritidae) in inland New South Wales, Australia and their potential for use in augmentative biological control</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Entomol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>445</fpage>
<lpage>452</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-6055.2011.00828.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-insects-03-01056"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biological attributes of three introduced parasitoids as natural enemies of fruit flies, genus <italic>Anastrepha</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>J. Appl. Entomol.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>133</volume>
<fpage>181</fpage>
<lpage>188</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0418.2008.01323.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-insects-03-01056"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rousse</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilici</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Fopius arisanus</italic>, an egg-pupal parasitoid of Tephritidae</article-title>
<source>Overview. Biocontrol News Inform.</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>69</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-insects-03-01056"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eitam</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biogeography of braconid parasitoids of the Caribbean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Florida</article-title>
<source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>928</fpage>
<lpage>939</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0013-8746(2004)097[0928:BOBPOT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-insects-03-01056"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quimio</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host preference and host suitability in an egg-pupal fruit fly parasitoid, <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> (Sonan) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>J. Appl. Entomol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>135</fpage>
<lpage>140</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0418.2001.00514.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-insects-03-01056"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowball</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukins</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The utilization of parasites of oriental fruit fly (<italic>Dacus dorsalis</italic>) against Queensland fruit fly (<italic>Strumeta tryoni</italic>)</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Agr. Econ.</source>
<year>1962</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>
<lpage>460</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR9620443</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-insects-03-01056"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host specificity tests of <italic>Dichasmimorpha kraussii</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), a newly introduced opiine fruit fly parasitoid with four nontarget tephritids in Hawaii</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>28</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.2000.0842</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-insects-03-01056"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host range and reproductive output of <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii </italic>(Hymenoptera: Braconidae), a parasitoid of tephritid fruit flies newly imported to Hawaii</article-title>
<source>Area-Wide Control of Fruit Flies and Other Insect Pests, Joint Proceedings of the International Conference on Area-Wide Control of Insect Pests, Penerbit Universiti Sains Malaysia: Pulau Pinang, Malaysia, 28 May&#x02013;2 June 1998 and the Fifth International Symposium on Fruit Flies of Economic Importance, Penang, Malaysia, 1&#x02013;5 June, 1998</source>
<publisher-name>Penerbit Universiti Sains Malaysia</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Pulau Pinang, Malaysia</publisher-loc>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>713</fpage>
<lpage>718</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-insects-03-01056"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sime</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daane</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title><italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> and <italic>D. kraussii</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), potential parasitoids of the olive fruit fly</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>169</fpage>
<lpage>179</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-insects-03-01056"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvitti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oviposition response and development of the egg-pupal parasitoid <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> on <italic>Bactrocera oleae</italic>, a tephritid fruit fly pest of olive in the Mediterranean basin</article-title>
<source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>73</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-insects-03-01056"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argov</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazit</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biological control of the Mediterranean fruit fly in Israel: Introduction and establishment of natural enemies</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>502</fpage>
<lpage>507</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2008.04.021</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-insects-03-01056"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Melittobia (Syntomosphyrum) indicum (Silv.) (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea), a parasite of the Queensland fruit fly, Strumeta tryoni (Frogg.)</article-title>
<source>Proc. Linn. Soc. N.S.W.</source>
<year>1942</year>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>
<lpage>276</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-insects-03-01056"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilstrap</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Key to and status of opiine Braconid (Hymenoptera) parasitoids used in biological control of <italic>Ceratitis</italic> and <italic>Dacus s. l.</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am.</source>
<year>1983</year>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>721</fpage>
<lpage>742</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-insects-03-01056"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Seasonal abundance of parasitoids of the Mediterranean and oriental fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) in the Kula area of Maui, Hawaii</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1984</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>140</fpage>
<lpage>145</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-insects-03-01056"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowball</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukins</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Culture and consignment techniques used for parasites introduced against Queensland fruit fly (<italic>Strumeta tryoni</italic> (Froggatt))</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Agr. Res.</source>
<year>1962</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>233</fpage>
<lpage>248</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/AR9620233</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-insects-03-01056"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Rosa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Celedonio</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fruit infesting Tephritids (Diptera: Tephritidae) and associated parasitoids in Chiapas, Mexico</article-title>
<source>Entomophaga</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>
<lpage>48</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02374299</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-insects-03-01056"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ovruski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hymenopteran parasitoids on fruit-infesting Tephritidae (Diptera) in Latin America and the southern United States: Diversity, distribution, taxonomic status and their use in fruit fly biological control</article-title>
<source>Integrated Pest. Manag. Rev.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009652431251</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-insects-03-01056"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rendon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloem</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of sterile males and two braconid parasitoids, <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> (Sonan) and <italic>Diachasmimorpha krausii</italic> (Fullaway) (Hymenoptera), on caged populations of Mediterranean fruit flies, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Wied.) (Diptera: Tephritidae) at various sites in Guatemala</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>224</fpage>
<lpage>231</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2005.10.006</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-insects-03-01056"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bokonon-Ganta</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuate</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Natural establishment of a parasitoid complex on <italic>Bactrocera latifrons</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Hawaii</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>365</fpage>
<lpage>373</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2007.05.019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-insects-03-01056"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vorsino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieczorek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Using Molecular Tools to Identify and Describe Ecological and Evolutionary Processes Affecting Augmentative Biological Control</source>
<publisher-name>Department of Plant and Environmental Protection Sciences</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Christchurch, New Zealand</publisher-loc>
<year>2008</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-insects-03-01056"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of origin and experience on patterns of host acceptance by the opiine parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic></article-title>
<source>Ecol. Entomol.</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<lpage>291</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2311.1999.00206.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-insects-03-01056"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Is the oriental fruit-fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) a natural host for the opiine parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)? Environ</article-title>
<source>Entomol.</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>761</fpage>
<lpage>769</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-insects-03-01056"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Association of the opiine parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) with the lantana gall fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) on Kauai</article-title>
<source>Environ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>419</fpage>
<lpage>426</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-insects-03-01056"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contribution of biological control to integrated pest management of tephritid fruit flies in tropics and subtropics</article-title>
<source>Integrated Pest. Manag. Rev.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009647429498</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-insects-03-01056"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Insecticde effect on three tephritid fruit flies and associated braconid parasitoids in Hawaii</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>1455</fpage>
<lpage>1462</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B48-insects-03-01056"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sime</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daane</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> as a biological control agent for the olive fruit fly in California</article-title>
<source>Agric. For. Entomol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>423</fpage>
<lpage>431</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-9563.2008.00401.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B49-insects-03-01056"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benrey</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biological control of <italic>Anastrepha</italic> spp. (Diptera: Tephritidae) in mango orchards through augmentative releases of <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Ashmead) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>216</fpage>
<lpage>224</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.2000.0819</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B50-insects-03-01056"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimoto</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Augmentative releases of <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) to suppress a Mediterranean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae) population in Kula, Maui, Hawai</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>2</fpage>
<lpage>7</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/1049-9644(91)90094-G</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B51-insects-03-01056"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klugness</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Short-range dispersal of mass-reared<italic> Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> and <italic>D. tryoni </italic>(Hymenoptera: Brachonidae), parasitiods of tephritid fruit flies</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>975</fpage>
<lpage>985</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B52-insects-03-01056"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Response of three Hymenopteran parasitoids introduced for fruit fly control to a gall-forming Tephritid, <italic>Procecidochares alani</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1997.0533</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B53-insects-03-01056"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Medel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz-Fleischer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Romero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Foraging behavior by six fruit fly parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) released as single- or multiple-species cohorts in field cages: Influence of fruit location and host density</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>43</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>22</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2007.06.008</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B54-insects-03-01056"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> on two non-target flowerhead-feeding tephritids</article-title>
<source>BioControl</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage>
<lpage>125</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009944520353</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B55-insects-03-01056"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hymenopterous larval-pupal and pupal parasitoids of <italic>Anastrepha</italic> flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Mexico</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<lpage>129</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1999.0711</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B56-insects-03-01056"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villasenor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>SIT and biological control of <italic>Anastrepha </italic>fruit flies in Mexico</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the 6th International Symposium on Fruit Flies of Economic Importance</source>
<publisher-name>Isteg Scientific Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Stellenbosch, South Africa</publisher-loc>
<year>2002</year>
<fpage>245</fpage>
<lpage>249</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B57-insects-03-01056"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scarratt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wratten</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shishehbor</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Measuring parasitoid movement from floral resources in a vineyard</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>107</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2008.03.016</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B58-insects-03-01056"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klugness</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Quality control parameters of mass-reared opiine parasitoids used in augmentative biological control of tephritid fruit flies</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1993</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>140</fpage>
<lpage>147</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1993.1021</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B59-insects-03-01056"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>O.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henaut</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Lopez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Is host size an indicator of quality in the mass-reared parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)?</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>441</fpage>
<lpage>449</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/024.092.0305</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B60-insects-03-01056"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Advances and Perspectives in the Mass Rearing of Fruit Fly Parasitoids in Mexico</source>
<publisher-name>Isteg Scientific Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Salvador, Brazil</publisher-loc>
<year>2006</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B61-insects-03-01056"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinson</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Romero</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernal</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of continuous rearing on courtship acoustics of five braconid parasitoids, candidates for augmentative biological control of <italic>Anastrepha</italic> species</article-title>
<source>BioControl</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>573</fpage>
<lpage>582</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10526-010-9278-x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B62-insects-03-01056"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of host substrate and vibration cues on ovipositor-probing behavior in two larval parasitoids<italic> Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> and <italic>Biosteres longicaudata</italic> of tephritid fruit flies <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic></article-title>
<source>J. Insect Behav.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B63-insects-03-01056"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gienapp</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Exploitation of the host's chemical communication in a parasitoid searching for concealed host larvae</article-title>
<source>Ethology</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>105</volume>
<fpage>223</fpage>
<lpage>232</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0310.1999.00361.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B64-insects-03-01056"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Influence of parasitoid size and age on male mating success of <italic>Opiinae</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), larval parasitoids of fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1991</year>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>248</fpage>
<lpage>255</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/1049-9644(91)90074-A</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B65-insects-03-01056"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ero</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamacek</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Preference among four <italic>Bactrocera</italic> species (Diptera: Tephritidae) by <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii</italic> (Fullaway) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Entomol.</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>324</fpage>
<lpage>331</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-6055.2010.00772.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B66-insects-03-01056"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The past and potential of biological control of fruit flies</article-title>
<source>Fruit Fly Pests: A World Assessment of Their Biology and Management</source>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>McPheron</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-name>St Lucie Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Delray Beach, FL, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>369</fpage>
<lpage>375</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B67-insects-03-01056"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Irradiation of <italic>Anastrepha ludens</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) eggs for the rearing of the fruit fly parasitoids, <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> and <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata </italic>(Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>167</fpage>
<lpage>177</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150802439827</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B68-insects-03-01056"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>O.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rearing the biological control agent <italic>Diachasmimorpha kraussii </italic>(Fullaway) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) on irradiated larvae of the Queensland fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera tryoni </italic>(Froggatt) (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the 8th International Symposium on Fruit Flies of Economic Importance</source>
<conf-loc>Valencia, Spain</conf-loc>
<conf-date>2010</conf-date>
<fpage>231</fpage>
<lpage>253</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B69-insects-03-01056"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallman</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Expanding radiation quarantine treatments beyond fruit flies</article-title>
<source>Agric. For. Entomol.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>85</fpage>
<lpage>95</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1461-9563.2000.00057.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B70-insects-03-01056"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von Sontag</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>The Chemical Basis of Radiation Biology</source>
<publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
<year>1987</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B71-insects-03-01056"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Lachaud</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Superparasitism in the fruit fly parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) and the implications for mass rearing and augmentative release</article-title>
<source>Insects</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>900</fpage>
<lpage>911</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects3040900</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B72-insects-03-01056"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larios</surname><given-names>G.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of chilling on the fecundity and life span of mass-reared parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) of the Mediterranean fruit fly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>215</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150120124469</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B73-insects-03-01056"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeronimo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Development of aerial releases of <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni </italic>(Cameron) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae), a parasitoid that attacks the Mediterranean fruit fly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> (Weidemann) (Diptera: Tephritidae), in the Guatemalan highlands</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>15</fpage>
<lpage>25</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150029341</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B74-insects-03-01056"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Food sources for adult <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic>, a parasitoid of tephritid fruit flies: Effects on longevity and fecundity</article-title>
<source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>193</fpage>
<lpage>202</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.2006.00379.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B75-insects-03-01056"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The effect of food deprivation on the innate visual and olfactory preferences in the parasitoid <italic>Cotesia rubecula</italic></article-title>
<source>J. Insect Physiol.</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>641</fpage>
<lpage>649</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-1910(94)90091-4</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B76-insects-03-01056"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T.C.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The nutritional value of aphid honeydew for non-aphid parasitoids</article-title>
<source>Basic. Appl. Ecol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>286</fpage>
<lpage>297</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.baae.2007.02.001</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B77-insects-03-01056"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A comparison of nectar- and honeydew sugars with respect to their utilization by the hymenopteran parasitoid <italic>Cotesia glomerata</italic></article-title>
<source>J. Insect Physiol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>1077</fpage>
<lpage>1084</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-1910(01)00088-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11472770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B78-insects-03-01056"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoedjes</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruidhof</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huigens</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vet</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Natural variation in learning rate and memory dynamics in parasitoid wasps: Opportunities for converging ecology and neuroscience</article-title>
<source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>889</fpage>
<lpage>897</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2010.2199</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21106587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B79-insects-03-01056"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meiners</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Associative learning of complex odours in parasitoid host location</article-title>
<source>Chem. Senses</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>231</fpage>
<lpage>236</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/chemse/28.3.231</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12714445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B80-insects-03-01056"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Baaren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Learning affects host discrimination behavior in a parasitoid wasp</article-title>
<source>Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>16</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002650050406</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B81-insects-03-01056"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamek</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>O.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Micallef</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Carbohydrate diet and reproductive performance of the fruit fly parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Cameron)</article-title>
<source>J. Ins. Sci.</source>
<year>2012</year>
<comment>in press</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B82-insects-03-01056"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>T.C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wackers</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vet</surname><given-names>L.E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Learning of host-finding cues by hymenopterous parasitoids</article-title>
<source>Insect Learning: Ecological and Evolutionary Perspectives</source>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Papaj</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>78</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B83-insects-03-01056"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vet</surname><given-names>L.E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Card&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parasitoid foraging and learning</article-title>
<source>Chemical Ecology of Insects</source>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Card&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B84-insects-03-01056"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukovinszky</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steidle</surname><given-names>J.L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleeker</surname><given-names>M.A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Loon</surname><given-names>J.J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vet</surname><given-names>L.E.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Species-specific acquisition and consolidation of long-term memory in parasitic wasps</article-title>
<source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>274</volume>
<fpage>1539</fpage>
<lpage>1546</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2007.0305</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17439855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B85-insects-03-01056"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Nouhuys</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaartinen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A parasitoid wasp uses landmarks while monitoring potential resources</article-title>
<source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>275</volume>
<fpage>377</fpage>
<lpage>385</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2007.1446</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18063555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B86-insects-03-01056"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A comparison of color-, shape- and pattern-learning by the hymenopteran parasitoid <italic>Microplitis croceipes</italic></article-title>
<source>J. Comp. Physiol. A</source>
<year>1999</year>
<volume>184</volume>
<fpage>387</fpage>
<lpage>393</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s003590050337</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B87-insects-03-01056"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmeister</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Decision-making dynamics in parasitoids of Drosophila</article-title>
<source>Adv. Parasit.</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>66</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-308X(09)70002-8</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B88-insects-03-01056"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papaj</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vet</surname><given-names>L.E.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Odor learning and foraging success in parasitoid, <italic>Leptopilina heterotoma</italic></article-title>
<source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source>
<year>1990</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>3137</fpage>
<lpage>3150</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00979616</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24263300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B89-insects-03-01056"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knipling</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sterile insect and parasite augmentation techniques: Unexploited solutions for many insect pest problems</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>160</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B90-insects-03-01056"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calkins</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brambila</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Suppression of a Caribbean fruit fly (<italic>Anastrepha suspensa</italic> (Loew) Diptera: Tephritidae) population through augmented releases of the parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Ashmead) (Hymenoptera: Braconidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>
<lpage>185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1996.0022</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B91-insects-03-01056"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenstone</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular methods for assessing insect parasitism</article-title>
<source>Bull. Entomol. Res.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>13</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BER2005402</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16441900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B92-insects-03-01056"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Micallef</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>O.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular techniques for the detection and differentiation of host and parasitoid species and the implications for fruit fly management</article-title>
<source>Insects</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>763</fpage>
<lpage>788</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects3030763</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B93-insects-03-01056"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kean</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Behavioral studies, molecular approaches, and modeling: Methodological contributions to biological control success</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>255</fpage>
<lpage>262</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2009.03.018</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B94-insects-03-01056"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="commun">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Programa Moscafrut SAGARPA-IICA, Metapa de Dominguez, Chiapas, Mexico. Cost of parasitoid rearing</article-title>
<source>Personal communication</source>
<year>2009</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B95-insects-03-01056"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Egg maturation in the parasitoid <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae): Do host-associated stimuli promote ovarian development?</article-title>
<source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>571</fpage>
<lpage>578</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0013-8746(2003)096[0571:EMITPF]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B96-insects-03-01056"><label>96.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowball</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukins</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Status of introduced parasites of Queensland fruit fly (<italic>Strumeta tryoni</italic>), 1960-62</article-title>
<source>Aust. J. Agr. Res.</source>
<year>1964</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>596</fpage>
<lpage>608</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B97-insects-03-01056"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguiar-Menezes</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittar</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassino</surname><given-names>P.C.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Native hymenopteran parasitoids associated with <italic>Anastrepha</italic> spp<italic>.</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Seropedica City, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>84</volume>
<fpage>706</fpage>
<lpage>711</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3496405</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B98-insects-03-01056"><label>98.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguiar-Menezes</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Natural occurrence of parasitoids of <italic>Anastrepha</italic> spp Schiner, 1868 (Diptera: Tephritidae) in different host plants, in Itaguai (RJ), Brazil</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1996.0485</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B99-insects-03-01056"><label>99.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez-Ortiz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delfin-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escalante-Tio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manrique-Saide</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hymenopteran parasitoids of Anastrepha fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) reared from different hosts in Yucatan, Mexico</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>89</volume>
<fpage>508</fpage>
<lpage>515</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/0015-4040(2006)89[508:HPOAFF]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B100-insects-03-01056"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mkize</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoelmer</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villet</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A survey of fruit-feeding insects and their parasitoids occurring on wild olives, <italic>Olea europaea ssp cuspidata</italic>, in the Eastern Cape of South Africa</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol Sci. Technol.</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>991</fpage>
<lpage>1004</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150802450154</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B101-insects-03-01056"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trostle</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimani-Njogu</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Overholt</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivinski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parasitoids of medfly, <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic>, and related tephritids in Kenyan coffee: A predominantly koinobiont assemblage</article-title>
<source>Bull. Entomol. Res.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>517</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11107253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B102-insects-03-01056"><label>102.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aluja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Staples</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macias-Ordonoez</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinero</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcpheron</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Ortiz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nonhost status of <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> cultivar Valencia and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>paradisi</italic> cultivar Ruby Red to Mexican <italic>Anastrepha fraterculus </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>1693</fpage>
<lpage>1703</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493-96.6.1693</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B103-insects-03-01056"><label>103.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>F.R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corseuil</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Native Hymenopteran parasitoids associated with fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) in Santa Catarina State, Brazil</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>517</fpage>
<lpage>521</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1653/0015-4040(2004)087[0517:NHPAWF]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B104-insects-03-01056"><label>104.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fruit fly handling</article-title>
<source>Personal communication</source>
<publisher-name>Agricultural Scientific Collections Unit, New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, Orange Agricultural Institute</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Orange, New South Wales, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>2009</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B105-insects-03-01056"><label>105.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauers-Muller</surname><given-names>v.A.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host plants of the Carambola fruit fly, <italic>Bactrocera carambolae</italic> Drew &#x00026; Hancock (Diptera: Tephritidae), in Suriname, South America</article-title>
<source>Neotropical Entomology</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1519-566X2005000200008</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B106-insects-03-01056"><label>106.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fruit fly life cycle</article-title>
<source>Personal communication</source>
<publisher-name>New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, University of Newcastle, Ourimbah Campus, Ourimbah</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New South Wales, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>2009</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B107-insects-03-01056"><label>107.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation</collab></person-group>
<source>The Insects of Australia. A Textbook for Students and Research Workers</source>
<edition>2nd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>Melbourne University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Carlton, VIC, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>1991</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B108-insects-03-01056"><label>108.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ovipositional responses of three opiine fruit fly parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) to gall-forming tephritids (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>88</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1997.0526</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B109-insects-03-01056"><label>109.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of the impact of the fruit fly parasitoid <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) on a nontarget tephritid, <italic>Eutreta xanthochaeta</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1996.0487</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B110-insects-03-01056"><label>110.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dukas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host selection of <italic>Diachasmimorpha tryoni</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae): Comparative response to fruit-infesting and gall-forming tephritid flies</article-title>
<source>Environ. Entomol.</source>
<year>2000</year>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>838</fpage>
<lpage>845</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0046-225X-29.4.838</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B111-insects-03-01056"><label>111.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biological control of invasive species: Solution or pollution?</article-title>
<source>Front. Ecol. Environ.</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>132</fpage>
<lpage>140</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1540-9295(2006)004[0132:BCOISS]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B112-insects-03-01056"><label>112.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parasitoids of non-target tephritid flies in Hawaii: Implications for biological control of fruit fly pests</article-title>
<source>Entomophaga</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>245</fpage>
<lpage>256</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B113-insects-03-01056"><label>113.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of two opiine parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) introduced for fruit fly control on a native Hawaiian tephritid, <italic>Trupanea dubautiae</italic> (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1997.0503</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B114-insects-03-01056"><label>114.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaenike</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaj</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Behavioral Plasticity and Patterns of Host Use by Insects</source>
<publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>1992</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B115-insects-03-01056"><label>115.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Response of two opiine fruit fly parasitoids (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) to the lantana gall fly (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Environ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1996</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1428</fpage>
<lpage>1437</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B116-insects-03-01056"><label>116.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parasitization of the Mediterranean and oriental fruit flies (Diptera: Tephritidae) in the Kula area of Maui, Hawaii</article-title>
<source>J. Econ. Entomol.</source>
<year>1987</year>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>77</fpage>
<lpage>80</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B117-insects-03-01056"><label>117.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zenil</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cancino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reproductive biology of <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) on <italic>Ceratitis capitata</italic> and <italic>Anastrepha</italic> spp. (Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>169</fpage>
<lpage>178</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1049-9644(03)00140-3</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B118-insects-03-01056"><label>118.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The fruit fly parasitoid <italic>Fopius arisanus</italic>: Reproductive attributes of pre-released females and the use of added sugar as a potential food supplement in the field</article-title>
<source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>247</fpage>
<lpage>255</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B119-insects-03-01056"><label>119.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reproductive biology of <italic>Biosteres arisanus</italic> (Sonan), an egg larval parasitoid of the Oriental fruit fly</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>1994</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>93</fpage>
<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bcon.1994.1016</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B120-insects-03-01056"><label>120.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ovruski</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezdjian</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Nieuwenhove</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albornoz-Medina</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliserman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Host preference by <italic>Diachasmimorpha longicaudata</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) reared on larvae of <italic>Anastrepha fraterculus</italic> and <italic>Ceratitis capitata </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Fla. Entomol.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>295</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B121-insects-03-01056"><label>121.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>On the specific status of <italic>Dacus (Bactrocera) aquilonis</italic> and <italic>D. (Bactrocera) tryoni </italic>(Diptera: Tephritidae)</article-title>
<source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am.</source>
<year>1986</year>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>870</fpage>
<lpage>878</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B122-insects-03-01056"><label>122.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The ectoparasitic pupal parasitoid, <italic>Pachycrepoideus vindemmiae</italic> (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae), attacks other primary tephritid fruit fly parasitoids: Host expansion and potential non-target impact</article-title>
<source>Biol. Control</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>227</fpage>
<lpage>236</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2004.04.019</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B123-insects-03-01056"><label>123.</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<article-title>Weed Management C.R.C</article-title>
<source>Lantana (Lantana camara)</source>
<publisher-name>National Heritage Trust</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc>
<year>2003</year>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B124-insects-03-01056"><label>124.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opp</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krugner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daane</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Honeydew and insecticide bait as competing food resources for a fruit fly and common natural enemies in the olive agroecosystem</article-title>
<source>Entomol. Exp. Appl.</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>139</volume>
<fpage>128</fpage>
<lpage>137</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.2011.01114.x</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B125-insects-03-01056"><label>125.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barclay</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Models for pest control: Complementary effects of periodic releases of sterile pests and parasitoids</article-title>
<source>Theor. Popul. Biol.</source>
<year>1987</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>76</fpage>
<lpage>89</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-5809(87)90041-4</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B126-insects-03-01056"><label>126.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaspi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parella</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Synergistic interaction between parasitoids and sterile insects</article-title>
<source>International Organization for Biological and Integrated Control of Noxious Animals and Plants West Palaearctic Regional Section: Working Group "Integrated Control in Protected Crops, Temperate Climate", Proceedings of the Working Group meeting; International Organization for Biological and Integrated Control of Noxious Animals and Plants (OIBC/OILB), West Palaearctic Regional Section (WPRS/SROP): Sint Michielsgestel, The Netherlands, 21&#x02013;25 April 2008</source>
<fpage>99</fpage>
<lpage>102</lpage>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>