<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5787290</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">208</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-018-0208-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Indigenous uses of ethnomedicinal plants among forest-dependent communities of Northern Bengal, India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9910-1666</contrib-id><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>Antony Joseph</given-names></name><address><email>drajr.aaidu@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Biswakarma</surname><given-names>Saroj</given-names></name><address><email>Sarojkhati001@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pala</surname><given-names>Nazir A.</given-names></name><address><email>nazirpaul@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>Gopal</given-names></name><address><email>gopalshukla12@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vineeta</surname></name><address><email>babra.vini@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Munesh</given-names></name><address><email>muneshmzu@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>Sumit</given-names></name><address><email>c_drsumit@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>Rainer W.</given-names></name><address><email>rainer.bussmann@savingknowledge.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Forestry, Uttar Banga Krishi Vishwavidyalaya, Cooch Behar, West Bengal India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0681 6439</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412161.1</institution-id><institution>Department of Forestry and Natural Resources, </institution><institution>HNB Garhwal University, </institution></institution-wrap>Srinagar Garhwal, Uttarakhand India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Saving Knowledge, Casilla, 13092 La Paz, Bolivia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1539 8988</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.30820.39</institution-id><institution>Mekelle University, </institution></institution-wrap>Mekelle, Tigray Ethiopia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>8</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Traditional knowledge on ethnomedicinal plant is slowly eroding. The exploration, identification and documentation on utilization of ethnobotanic resources are essential for restoration and preservation of ethnomedicinal knowledge about the plants and conservation of these species for greater interest of human society.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The study was conducted at fringe areas of Chilapatta Reserve Forest in the foothills of the eastern sub-Himalayan mountain belts of West Bengal, India, from December 2014 to May 2016. Purposive sampling method was used for selection of area. From this area which is inhabited by aboriginal community of Indo-Mongoloid origin, 400 respondents including traditional medicinal practitioners were selected randomly for personal interview schedule through open-ended questionnaire. The questionnaire covered aspects like plant species used as ethnomedicines, plant parts used, procedure for dosage and therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total number of 140 ethnomedicinal species was documented, in which the tree species (55) dominated the lists followed by herbs (39) and shrubs (30). Among these total planted species used for ethnomedicinal purposes, 52 species were planted, 62 species growing wild or collected from the forest for use and 26 species were both wild and planted. The present study documented 61 more planted species as compared to 17 planted species documented in an ethnomedicinal study a decade ago. The documented species were used to treat 58 human diseases/ailments including nine species used to eight diseases/ailments of domestic animals. Stomach-related problems were treated by maximum number of plants (40 species) followed by cuts and wounds with 27 plant species and least with one species each for 17 diseases or ailments. Maximum number of 12 diseases/ailments was cured by <italic>Melia azedarach</italic> followed by <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> and <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> which were used to cure 11 diseases/ailments each.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The list of 140 plant species indicates that the Chilapatta Reserve Forest and its fringe areas are rich in biodiversity of ethnobotanical plant species. <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> were the most valuable species in terms of its maximal use with higher use value. The documentation of 78 species maintained in the home gardens indicates the community consciousness on the conservation values of these ethnobotanical species. The communities should be encouraged with improved cultivation techniques of commercially viable ethnobotanical species through capacity building, timely policy intervention along with strong market linkage. This will ensure income generation and livelihood improvement and ultimate conservation of these species.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Tradition</kwd><kwd>Indigenous</kwd><kwd>Disease</kwd><kwd>Liver</kwd><kwd>Policy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Due to globalization and green revolution, natural resources are rapidly dwindling due to the unsustainable anthropogenic activity. Consequently, the primary challenge to human society is the steady change in climate, reduction in biodiversity and dependence on external resources without giving emphasis on the enriched localised natural resources. In this setting, there is a need to explore the indigenous knowledge base for ecological, economic and environmental sustainability. Especially, forest fringe communities are associated with the forest for maintaining their livelihoods. Use of medicinal plants to treat various diseases has been part of human culture since ancient times [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Botanically derived medicinal plants play a major role in human society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Traditional medicine forms a valuable resource for the development of new pharmaceuticals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The exploration, utilization and conservation of these ethnobotanic resources are essential for restoration and preservation of traditional and indigenous knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This acquired knowledge about the plants is very essential to be used in the near future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Moreover, in developing countries now, the trend is to incorporate traditional medicines in local healthcare system and interest has increased among the researchers to explore the huge potential of ethnomedicinal knowledge for treating various diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">In India and particularly in West Bengal people living in remote and rural localities are still dependent on traditional medicines for treatments of various ailments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Indigenous people of Indo-Mongoloid origin inhabiting Chilapatta Reserve Forest in northern part of West Bengal are still using forest-originated products for their healthcare needs due to lack of availability of modern medical facilities and poor socio-economic condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The tendency of disinterestedness in old traditions is feared by elders as a major cause of losing this wealth of knowledge in coming time soon. Since traditional knowledge on ethnomedicinal plant is being eroded through acculturation and the loss of plant biodiversity along with indigenous people and their cultural background, hence, promoting research on these plants is crucial in order to safeguard this information for future societies for sustainable use and their conservation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Ethnomedicinal surveys provide data and information basis for conservation and sustainable utilization of local wild plants and also contribute to preserve cultural and genetic diversity. No new plant product, particularly wild, will be accepted by the urban population without proper testimony from specialists. The present study was therefore undertaken in the forest fringe area of Chilapatta Forest of West Bengal having objectives (i) document the ethnomedicinal plant species used by the community, (ii) tradition medicinal use and pattern and (iii) comparison of reported uses with different publications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par8">The present study was carried out at the forest fringe villages of Chilapatta Reserve Forest located in the sub-Himalayan mountain belts of West Bengal, India. The forest spreading over 41&#x000a0;km<sup>2</sup> lies within the jurisdiction of Cooch Behar Wildlife Division in Alipurduar district (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The forest is about 30&#x000a0;km away both from Cooch Behar and Alipurduar town, headquarters of Cooch Behar and Alipurduar district, and is transected by National Highway no. 31C. The fringe villages are Uttar Simlabari, Uttar Chaukakheti, Andu Basty, Bania Basty, Dakshin Mendabari, Uttar Mendabari, Kodal Basty, Kurmai Basty and Chilapatta Kumarpara. The elevation of the working site as measured by GPS (Garmin 72) was latitude 26&#x000b0; 32.85&#x02032; N and longitude 89&#x000b0; 22.99&#x02032; E. Mean altitude of the area was 47&#x000a0;m above MSL. The region is sub-tropical receiving average annual rainfall of 250&#x02013;300&#x000a0;cm from south-west monsoon of which 80% is received from June to August. The summer and winter temperature are mild with 34&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C as the highest in the month of May while the lowest temperature is 7.5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C during January. The forest villages with around 1000 households (average family size of 5&#x02013;7 members) are inhabited by local communities of Indo-Mongoloid origin, including the Raj Bangshis, Mech, Ravas, Totos, Limbus, Lepchas, Nageshias, Uraons and Mundas. These fringe communities of the Chilapatta Reserve Forest are economically disadvantaged and thus depend on the forest and subsistence farming for their livelihoods.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Plant parts used for ethnomedicinal purposes. <bold>b</bold> Map of the study area</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2018_208_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Ethnobotanical data collection</title><p id="Par9">The study was conducted from December 2014 to May 2016. The villages selected were purposive. An exhaustive list of households in each village was prepared with the active cooperation of State Forest Department and local village administration (&#x02018;Panchayat&#x02019;). Prior informed consent and permission to interview the villagers was obtained from the village administration and each participant verbally. A pre-tested open-ended personal interview schedule was used to elucidate aspects like plant species used as ethnomedicines, plant parts used, procedure for dosage, diseases treated and therapy. Field surveys were conducted for collecting information through interviews. Only participants over 30&#x000a0;years of age were considered as respondents. The age of a person was reported significantly effecting traditional knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Thus, a total number of 400 respondents including traditional medicinal practitioners were selected randomly. Among the respondents, 91% were males. Females did not responded to our questionnaire without their male folk; and so only those female respondents were considered who responded independently. Forty-nine per cent of the respondents were in the age range of 33&#x02013;52&#x000a0;years, 39% in range of 53&#x02013;72&#x000a0;years and 12% in the range of 73&#x02013;92&#x000a0;years. Majority of the respondents (71%) have attended school up to primary level or more. The schedule was administered to the respondent in local language, and the responses were recorded in English on the schedule.</p><p id="Par10">The plant specimens were collected during the survey with the help of respondents. The specimens were mounted on herbarium sheets and were identified with the herbariums of Department of Forestry, Uttar Banga Krishi Viswavidyala, Pundibari, and Department of Botany, North Bengal University, Siliguri, West Bengal. The collected information on the ethnomedicinal plants was also cross checked with published available literature. For each species, the use value (UV), as adapted by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] from the proposal of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], was calculated. This quantitative method evaluates the relative importance of each medicinal species based on its relative use among informants. Use value is estimated as <italic>U</italic>/<italic>n</italic>, where <italic>U</italic> is the number of times a species is cited and <italic>n</italic> is the number of informants. The use value of each species is therefore based objectively on the importance attributed by the informants and does not depend on the opinion of the researcher [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The collected data were analysed by using Microsoft Excel.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Ethnomedicinal richness</title><p id="Par11">A total number of 140 ethnomedicinal species represented by 116 genera and 65 families used by the indigenous communities dwelling in the fringe areas of Chilapatta Reserve Forest were documented (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Out of these, 139 species were plants and one was fungus (<italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>). Among these total species documented, 52 species were planted by the indigenous communities of forest fringe area, 62 species were growing wild or collected from the forest for use and 26 species were both wild and planted. Of these ethnomedicinally used species, trees dominated the list with 55 species (21 planted, 19 wild while 15 both growing wild and planted/domesticated) followed by herbs with 39 species (15 planted and 18 wild while 6 both growing wild and planted/domesticated), shrubs with 30 species (10 planted and 17 wild while 3 both growing wild and planted/domesticated), climber with 12 species (4 planted and 8 wild), ferns are <italic>Christella dentata</italic> and <italic>Diplazium esculentum</italic> (both wild) and least used was a creeper (<italic>Ipomoea batatas</italic>&#x02014;planted) and a fungus (wild).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of documented ethnobotanic plants used by the communities living in fringe villages of Chilapatta Reserve Forest</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>6</th><th>7</th><th>8</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3">Acanthaceae</td><td><italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm.f.) Wall. ex Nees</td><td>
<italic>Kalmegh, Chirawta</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Basakpatta</italic>
</td><td>0.05</td><td>S</td><td>Sp*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O, Cr</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Justicia gendarussa</italic> Burm. f.</td><td>
<italic>Bishalyokoroni</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, B</td></tr><tr><td>Acoraceae</td><td><italic>Acorus calamus</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Ghorbaj Vasa bach, bojho</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, Cr</td></tr><tr><td>Amaranthaceae</td><td><italic>Alternanthera brasiliensis</italic> (L.) Kuntze</td><td>
<italic>Lalful, Itingjhar</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>O, N</td></tr><tr><td>Amaryllidaceae</td><td><italic>Urginea indica</italic> (Roxb.) Kunth</td><td>
<italic>Janglipiyaz</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W/Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Anarcardiaceae</td><td><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Amba</italic>
</td><td>0.05</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O, Ck</td></tr><tr><td>Annonaceae</td><td><italic>Annonas squamosa</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Atafol, Saripha</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Apiaceae</td><td><italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Soya sag</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Centella asiatica</italic> (L.) Urb.</td><td>
<italic>Bang Sag, Thankuni, Gortapre</italic>
</td><td>0.13</td><td>H</td><td>Co*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O, Ck, N, B</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Centella annua</italic>
<break/>M. Schub. &#x00026; B.-E. van Wyk</td><td>
<italic>Mana-muni, Beng sag</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, O, B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Apocynaceae</td><td><italic>Alstonia scholaris</italic> (L.) R. Br.</td><td>
<italic>Chatian</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>T</td><td>Fr*, Sp**</td><td>W/Pl</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Calotropis procera</italic> (Aiton) R. Br.</td><td>
<italic>Akhanda, Akwanpata</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R, B</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rauvolfia serpentine</italic> (L.) Benth ex Kurz.</td><td>
<italic>Nakbail, Sarpaganda</italic>
</td><td>0.11</td><td>H</td><td>E*</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>M, R, O, Cr, N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tabernaemontana divaricata</italic> (L.) R. Br. ex Roem. &#x00026; Schult.</td><td>
<italic>Baramasheful, Setoful, Tagarful</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td>R**</td><td>W</td><td>O, N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Thespesia populnea</italic> (L.) Sol. ex Corr&#x000ea;a</td><td>
<italic>Kanaliful, Karabiful</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>Ck</td></tr><tr><td>Araceae</td><td><italic>Colocasia esculenta</italic> (L.) Schott</td><td>
<italic>Ban-kachu</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td>Sp**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Arecaceae</td><td><italic>Areca catechu</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Supari, Goi)</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R, N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cocos nucifera</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Nariyal, Narkel</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phoenix sylvestris</italic> (L.) Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Khejur</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Asclepiadaceae</td><td><italic>Hemidesmus indicus</italic> (L.) R. Br.</td><td>
<italic>Anantamul</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td>Asparagaceae</td><td><italic>Asparagus racemosus</italic> Willd.</td><td>
<italic>Satomuli, Satalu</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td>Pl*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Asteraceae</td><td><italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> (Spreng.)<break/>R.M. King &#x00026; H. Rob.</td><td>
<italic>Banmara, German gach, Asamiapatta</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>S</td><td>A*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ageratum conyzoides</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Uchanti, Bhusuripata, Elame</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td>A*, R**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eupatorium odoratum</italic>L.</td><td>
<italic>Asamia, Banmara</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td>Fr**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tagetes erecta</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Mainalibibod, Marigold, Gendaful, Saipatri</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O, Ck, N</td></tr><tr><td>Athyriaceae</td><td><italic>Diplazium esculentum</italic> (Retz.) Sw.</td><td>
<italic>Khukri, Dhekia sag, Niguro</italic>
</td><td>0.05</td><td>F</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>Bambucaceae</td><td><italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> L<italic>.</italic></td><td>
<italic>Semul</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*, Sp**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>Basellaceae</td><td><italic>Basella alba</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Puin sag, Poi sag</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>C</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Bignoniaceae</td><td><italic>Oroxylum indicum</italic> (L.) Kurz.</td><td>
<italic>Kanaidingi, Totola, Surimala</italic>
</td><td>0.09</td><td>T</td><td>Fr*, Sp**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>R, O, N, B</td></tr><tr><td>Brassicaceae</td><td><italic>Brassica rugosa</italic> (Roxb.) L.H. Bailey</td><td>
<italic>Raya sag</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>Bromeliaceae</td><td><italic>Ananas comosus</italic> (L.) Merr.</td><td>
<italic>Anaras, Bhuikathar</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td>Cactaceae</td><td><italic>Opuntia ficus-indica</italic>Haw.</td><td>
<italic>Sidhugach, Fanimanasa</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Caricaceae</td><td><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Papita, Mewa</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td>Chenopodiaceae</td><td><italic>Chenopodium album</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Bethu sag (N)</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Combretaceae</td><td>
<italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic>
<break/>(Roxb. ex DC.) Wight &#x00026; Arn</td><td>
<italic>Arjun</italic>
</td><td>0.09</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>M, R, O, N, Bi</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Boir, Bahera, Barra</italic>
</td><td>0.06</td><td>T</td><td>R*, Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz.</td><td>
<italic>Haritaki, Harra</italic>
</td><td>0.09</td><td>T</td><td>R*, Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>M, R, O, N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Convolvulaceae</td><td><italic>Cuscuta europaea</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Kankor, Pahelolahara</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ipomoea batatas</italic> (L.) Lam.</td><td>
<italic>Sakarkanda, Mistialu</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>Cr</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ipomoea carnea</italic> Jacq.</td><td>
<italic>Karmigach, Thater</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Crassulaceae</td><td><italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic> (Lam.) Kurz.</td><td>
<italic>Patharkuchi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Cucurbitaceae</td><td><italic>Coccinia coridifolia</italic> (L.) Cogn.</td><td>
<italic>Kundri</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Coccinia indica</italic> Wight &#x00026; Arn.</td><td>
<italic>Kundli, Telakuchu</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lagenaria siceraria</italic> (Molina) Standl.</td><td>
<italic>Lou</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Luffa aegyptiaca</italic> Mill.</td><td>
<italic>Gongra, Dhudol, Gherawla</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Momordica diocia</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Jangli karela, Ban karola</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>C</td><td>Co*</td><td>W</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td>Dilleniaceae</td><td><italic>Dillenia indica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Pachkol (chalta)</italic>
</td><td>0.07</td><td>T</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>M, R, O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Dioscoreaceae</td><td><italic>Dioscorea belophylla</italic> Voigt</td><td>
<italic>Janglialu, Ban alu, Gichikanda, Ghetuallu</italic>
</td><td>0.05</td><td>C</td><td>R**</td><td>W</td><td>R, O, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dioscorea bulbifera</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Kowatumbil</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Diptrocarpaceae</td><td><italic>Shorea robusta</italic> Gaertn.</td><td>
<italic>Sal</italic>
</td><td>0.09</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*, Fr**</td><td>W</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td>Elaeocarpaceae</td><td><italic>Elaeocarpus ganitrus</italic>Roxb. ex G. Don</td><td>Rudrax</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>E<sup>1</sup></td><td>W</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8">Euphorbiaceae</td><td><italic>Baccaurea ramiflora</italic> Lour.</td><td>
<italic>Notko, Latkafal</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Baccaurea sapinda</italic>
<break/>(Roxb.) M&#x000fc;ll. Arg.</td><td>
<italic>Kusum</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Codiaeum variegatum</italic> (L.) Blume</td><td>
<italic>Pattabahargach</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Emblica officinalis</italic> Gaertn.</td><td>
<italic>Amlai, Amla, Amloki</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, N, Bi</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> (Willd. ex A. Juss.) M&#x000fc;ll. Arg.</td><td>
<italic>Loborgach</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Arandi, Bharenda</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, Cr</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mallotus tetracoccus</italic> (Roxb.) Kurz.</td><td>
<italic>Pethali</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Aranda,Varenda, Rahari</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Fabaceae</td><td><italic>Acacia catechu</italic> (L. f.) Willd.</td><td>
<italic>Khairgach</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*</td><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> (L.) Willd. ex Delile</td><td>
<italic>Kadamkapurgach, Babul</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bauhinia malabarica</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Kanchan, Tanki, Karmai</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>R, N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Huth</td><td>
<italic>Rahar, Raheri</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cassia alata</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Chakora</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cassia sophera</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Choto-kalkasunda</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hippocrepis emerus</italic> (L.) Lassen</td><td>
<italic>Heranchi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Lajjabati</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td>Fr*, R**</td><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> (L.) Merr.</td><td>
<italic>Karanj</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tamarindus indica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Tetul, Tittri</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl</td><td>Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> Spreng.</td><td>
<italic>Gila, Gilathakuri</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*</td><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Trigonella foerum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Methi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Fagaceae</td><td><italic>Quercus castanopsis</italic> H. Lev</td><td>
<italic>Guras</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td>Ganodermataceae</td><td><italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> (Curtis) P. Karst.</td><td>
<italic>Kath mushroom</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>Fn</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Lamiaceae</td><td><italic>Clerodendrum viscosum</italic> Vent.</td><td>
<italic>Bhauti, Dhatupatta, Ghentu, Bhatghato</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>S</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>O, Ck, N, B</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Gmelina arborea</italic> Roxb. ex. Sm.</td><td>
<italic>Gamar</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Fr*, Sp**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Leucas aspera</italic> (Willd.) Link</td><td>
<italic>Kanshisa, Ghuma, Thumbai</italic>
</td><td>0.08</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, R, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Tulsi</italic>
</td><td>0.08</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, R, O, B</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (L.) J. Presl</td><td>
<italic>Dalchini</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Machilus villosa</italic>
<break/>(Roxb.) Hook. f.</td><td>
<italic>Kawla</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Fr**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Lecythidaceae</td><td><italic>Careya arborea</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Kumbhi</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td>Fr**</td><td>Pl</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Lythraceae</td><td><italic>Lagerstroemia speciosa</italic> (L.) Pers.</td><td>
<italic>Jarul</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Fr**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Darim, Bedana</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Malvaceae</td><td><italic>Abroma augusta</italic> (L.) L.f.</td><td>
<italic>Ulatkambal</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td>Sp*</td><td>W</td><td>O, Cr</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Pajatiful</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td>Melastomataceae</td><td><italic>Melastoma malabathricum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Datrangi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td>R**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Meliaceae</td><td><italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss</td><td>
<italic>Neemgach</italic>
</td><td>0.05</td><td>T</td><td>Pl*</td><td>Pl</td><td>R, O, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Melia azedarach</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Ghora neem, Bakain, Bakaina</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Menispermaceae</td><td><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (Willd.) Miers ex Hook. f. &#x00026; Thom.</td><td>
<italic>Gulancha</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td>E*, Fr**</td><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9">Moraceae</td><td><italic>Artocarpus hetrophyllus</italic> Lam</td><td>
<italic>Kathal</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>T</td><td>Pl*</td><td>Pl</td><td>R, O, Cr</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artocarpus lakoocha</italic> Wall. ex Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Ban-kathal</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*; Fr**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus benghalensis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Bar rukh</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus carica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Dumber</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus elmeri</italic> Merr.</td><td>
<italic>Jog dumur</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus geniculata</italic> Kurz</td><td>
<italic>Futkol, Kabragach, Pakri</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus hispida</italic> L. f.</td><td>
<italic>Kuchuli</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus racemosa</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Dumur</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O, Cr</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Morus alba L.</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>Neel tuth, Tuth</italic>
</td><td>0.06</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, R, O</td></tr><tr><td>Moringaceae</td><td><italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam.</td><td>
<italic>Sajana</italic>
</td><td>0.06</td><td>T</td><td>Co*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, R, O, N</td></tr><tr><td>Musaceae</td><td><italic>Musa balbisiana</italic> Colla</td><td>
<italic>Kola</italic>
</td><td>0.08</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, R, O, Ck, Cr</td></tr><tr><td>Myristicaceae</td><td><italic>Myristica longifolia</italic> Wall. ex Blume</td><td>
<italic>Raktakamal, Rakatgach</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>T</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>O, Cr, B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Myrtaceae</td><td><italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Peyara, Asputai</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>T</td><td>Co*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, R, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Syzygium cumini</italic>(L.) Skeels</td><td>
<italic>Jamura, Jam, Jamur, Jamun</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td>Fr**</td><td>Pl</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>Oleaceae</td><td><italic>Nyctanthes arbor-tristis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Sefaliful</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Oxalidaceae</td><td><italic>Averrohoa carambola</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Kamringa, Charpatay</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td>Piperaceae</td><td><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Golmorich</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>Bi</td></tr><tr><td>Plumbaginaceae</td><td><italic>Plumbago zeylanica</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Chitwar</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td>R*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Poaceae</td><td><italic>Arundo donax</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Nolkhagra</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>R</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bambusa vulgaris</italic> Schrad. ex J.C. Wendl.</td><td>
<italic>Bans</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (L.) Pers.</td><td>
<italic>Dubbaghass</italic>
</td><td>0.06</td><td>H</td><td>A*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eleusine indica</italic> (L.) Gaertn.</td><td>
<italic>Kodoghass</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Thysanolaena latifolia</italic>
<break/>(Roxb. ex Hornem.) Honda</td><td>
<italic>Berni</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td>Pl*</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Ghehu</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Polygonaceae</td><td><italic>Polygonum dichotomum</italic> Blume.</td><td>
<italic>Biskathali</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Polygonum hydropiper</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Sukurpota, Biskutli, Pirrojhar</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td>Rubiaceae</td><td><italic>Anthocephalus cadamba</italic> (Roxb.) Miq.</td><td>
<italic>Kadam</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Rutaceae</td><td><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) Corr&#x000ea;a</td><td>
<italic>Bael</italic>
</td><td>0.06</td><td>T</td><td>Pl*, R**</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, O, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Osbeck</td><td>
<italic>Gololebu, Nimbu</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M, O, N</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Murraya koenigii</italic> (L.) Spreng.</td><td>
<italic>Norsing, Karipatta</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td>Scrophulariaceae</td><td><italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Pith berela, Mithapatta,Chinipatta</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td>Co*</td><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td>Simaroubaceae</td><td><italic>Ailanthus integrifolia</italic> Lam.</td><td>
<italic>Gokul</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>T</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W/Pl</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Solanaceae</td><td><italic>Datura metel</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Datura</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, O, B</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum indicum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Bithifal, Brihati, Rambegun</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum khasianum</italic> C.B. Clarke</td><td>
<italic>Bijri kata</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Bagun</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Maichung, Kakmachi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td>A*</td><td>W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum xanthocarpum</italic> Schrad. &#x00026; J.C. Wendl.</td><td>
<italic>Kantakari</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>M</td></tr><tr><td>Sterculiaceae</td><td><italic>Sterculia villosa</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Udal</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Thelypteridaceae</td><td><italic>Christella dentata</italic> (Forssk.) Brownsey &#x00026; Jermy</td><td>
<italic>Bis-dhekia</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>F</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Typhaceae</td><td><italic>Typha elephantina</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Hogla, Bhoglapatta</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Verbenaceae</td><td><italic>Lantana camara</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Ban-tulsi</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td>Sp**</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> L. f.</td><td>
<italic>Segun</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>T</td><td>Fr**</td><td>Pl/W</td><td>O, M, R, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Vitex negundo</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Nisinda</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>S</td><td>Fr*</td><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Vitaceae</td><td><italic>Cissus quadrangularis</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Harjora</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cissus repanda</italic> Vahl</td><td>
<italic>Panilarang, Panilata, Panilahara</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>C</td><td/><td>W</td><td>O</td></tr><tr><td>Xanthorrhoeaceae</td><td><italic>Aloe vera</italic> (L.) Burm. f.</td><td>
<italic>Ghewkumari, Gritokumari</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl</td><td>R, O, N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Zingiberaceae</td><td><italic>Alpinia malaccensis</italic> (Burm.f.) Roscoe</td><td>
<italic>Purundigach</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>S</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>R, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma caesia</italic> Roxb.</td><td>
<italic>Kala haldi, Kalohaledo</italic>
</td><td>0.03</td><td>H</td><td/><td>W</td><td>M, R, Ck</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.</td><td>
<italic>Halud, Haldi</italic>
</td><td>0.04</td><td>H</td><td>Sp*</td><td>Pl</td><td>M, O</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Zingiber zerumbet</italic> (L.) Roscoe ex Sm.</td><td>
<italic>Jangliadha, Jangliadhua</italic>
</td><td>0.02</td><td>H</td><td/><td>Pl/W</td><td>M, O</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>1: family; 2: scientific name; 3: vernacular name; 4: use value; 5: plant form, 6: conservation status; 7: growing status; 8: community using the species</p><p><italic>M</italic> Mech, <italic>R</italic> Rava, <italic>O</italic> Oraon, <italic>Ck</italic> Chikbaraik, <italic>Cr</italic> Cherwa, <italic>N</italic> Nepali, <italic>B</italic> Bengali, Bi Bihari, <italic>T</italic> tree, <italic>H</italic> herb, <italic>S</italic> shrub, <italic>C</italic> climber, <italic>Cr</italic> creeper, <italic>F</italic> fern, <italic>Fn</italic> fungus, <italic>W</italic> wild, <italic>Sp</italic> sparse/less frequent, <italic>Pl</italic> planted, <italic>A</italic> abundant, <italic>Fr</italic> frequent, <italic>Co</italic> common, <italic>E</italic> endangered, <italic>R</italic> rare</p><p>*[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] Chhetri et al. 2005</p><p>**[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] Shukla 2010</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par12">The tree species were represented by 44 genera and 29 families, shrubs represented by 26 genera and 17 families, herbs represented by 36 genera and 25 families, climbers represented by 10 genera and seven families, ferns represented by two genera and two families and one genus and one family each represented creeper and fungus. Trees were dominated by genus Ficus with six species and family Moraceae with nine species; shrubs were dominated by genus Solanum with three species and families Apocynaceae, Fabaceae, Euphorbiaceae and Solanaceae with three species each; herbs were dominated by genera Ageratum, Centella and Curcuma with two species each and family Poaceae with five species; and climbers were dominated by genera Coccinia and Dioscorea with two species each and family Cucurbitaceae with four species (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">The cultivated ethnomedicinal plant species were grown/planted by the respondents in their home garden, and it was found during the survey that almost all the respondents were maintaining a home garden contributing to conservation of the species they were using. Similar documentation was also reported by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In total, 78 ethnomedicinal plant species were documented to be maintained in the home gardens by the indigenous community residing in and around the Chilapatta Reserve Forest of West Bengal. Similar report on home gardens maintaining rich biodiversity of ethnomedicinal plants was also reported from Ethiopia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. There are ample of similar documentation from the plains and Himalayan region of West Bengal including Sikkim Himalayas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">A similar study from the same study area a decade ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] reported 79 ethnomedicinal plant species represented by 41 families and 68 genera. This means an increment of use of 61 ethnomedicinal plant species by the community. A decade ago, the community were growing only 17 species in their home garden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] but now, it increased to 78 species (present study). This increased the entries of ethnomedicinal plant species in the list which was documented a decade ago. This may be because of plant accessibility and visibility in the cultural landscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] increasing accessibility to obtain useful plants. The farther the species grows from home, the less frequently it is used, but if the plants are more desirable than well-known, species growing near home, it is worthwhile to domesticate these plants instead of undertaking long trips now and then. Plant accessibility and visibility in the cultural landscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] seem to have important factors influencing strategies for obtaining useful plants. Researchers conducting studies in different parts of the world indicate that knowledge of ethnomedicinal plants increases in proportion to their proximity to human habitations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. People usually know less about plants growing far from their homes and more about species that grow nearby. The same principle applies to use: people usually choose plants that grow in the immediate vicinity of their place of residence for ethnomedicinal use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. This explains the reason in increment in the number of planted ethnomedicinal plant species over a decade period in the study area.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Ethnomedicinal uses</title><p id="Par15">The documented species were used to treat 58 human diseases or ailments. Eight diseases of animals were also reported to be treated by some of the documented species (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) of humans and domestic animals, respectively. The ethnomedicinal information documented for these species was also validated with earlier studies (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Thirty plant species which were not reported in previous studies from the area. Stomach-related problems were documented to be treated by the maximum number of plants (40 species) followed by cuts and wounds with 27 plant species and least with one species each for 17 diseases or ailments (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). It was noted that the common day-to-day problems (fever, stomach-related disorders cuts, wounds and burns) were treated with many species. It was documented that the communities were treating severe diseases like cancer, pox, ulcer, tuberculosis, typhoid, malaria, pneumonia and bronchitis. An earlier study on Rava community using 41 ethnomedicinal species was also documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Nine plant species were also used as ethnoveterinary medicines to cure diseases/ailments like tongue and mouth problem; cough, cold and worms; lactation problem; fatigue/weakness; diarrhoea; cuts and wounds; and appetiser (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). There are many ethnomedicinal studies that similarly documented the use of plant species used as ethnoveterinary medicines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ethnomedicinal uses of documented species and validated with earlier studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plants name/voucher no.</th><th>Uses (present study)</th><th>Therapy/procedure of use</th><th>Earlier studies</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm.f.) Wall. ex Nees<break/>UBKV FOR 253</td><td>Diabetes, liver problems, fever, cough and cold, stomach pain, malaria</td><td>Whole plant is crushed, mixed with water and consumed twice daily&#x02014;early morning in empty stomach and night post dinner for diabetes and liver problem. Whole plant is soaked over night, and the solution is consumed empty stomach to get relief from fever, cough, cold, stomach pain and malaria. The solution is also a tonic drink for health.</td><td>Malaria, fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; poison bites, menstrual disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; for skin boils leucoderma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> L. UBKV FOR 328</td><td>Cough and cold, paralysis, allergy, stop bleeding, cuts and wounds</td><td>5&#x02013;6 leaves mixed with ginger is boiled half to its original amount and taken with honey for curing cough for 3 times a day. In serious case, it can be taken for 10&#x02013;15&#x000a0;days approximately. Leaf paste is rubbed on cuts and wound. Leaves are boiled and the solution is used for taking bath for curing itching and stopping bleeding. Leaf extract is added with mustard oil; <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> extract and ginger extract and heated lightly. One teaspoon and half cup of this mixture is administered orally in empty stomach to children and adult, respectively for treating cough and cold. Young leaves of <italic>Justicia adhatoda,</italic> papaya and <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> are packed under banana leaf and heated on a pan. After heating, its half teaspoon extract is administered empty stomach once a day as an alternate therapy for cough.</td><td>Cough, cold, piles, leprosy, diabetes, bronchitis, asthma, sinusitis, anti-inflammatory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Justicia gendarussa</italic> Burm. f.<break/>UBKV FOR 329</td><td>Cancer, septic, headache, cuts and wounds</td><td>Leaf extract is heated with coconut oil and placed on the affected part of the body for curing cancer, sceptics and cuts. The extract is also applied on cut and wound for healing and on forehead for relief from headache.</td><td>Rheumatism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acorus calamus</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 252</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>Stem of <italic>Acorus calamus</italic> and leaves of <italic>Artemisia dubia</italic> are mixed and grinded to form a paste which is then applied on paining joints till it is cured.</td><td>Delayed delivery, eye and skin problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; throat infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; asthma, bronchitis, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; rhizome to remove lice of animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>] cough, whooping cough, bronchitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Alternanthera brasiliensis</italic> (L.) Kuntze<break/>UBKV FOR 281</td><td>Cuts and wounds</td><td>Extract after crushing the twigs/leaves or flowers applied on cut or wounded part of the body and dressed.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Urginea indica</italic> (Roxb.) Kunth<break/>UBKV FOR 278</td><td>Tongue problem of domestic animals</td><td>Cloves are pasted and made solution with water and fed to suffering animals once for 2&#x000a0;days.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 265</td><td>Jaundice, blood dysentery, diarrhoea</td><td>Tender leaves of <italic>Mangifera indica</italic>, <italic>Syzygium cuminii</italic>, and <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> are crushed sugar candy, mentha, <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> and <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, and the extract is taken twice a day to cure diarrhoea. Bark is used for curing diarrhoea of domestic animals. Bark of <italic>Mangifera indica</italic>, <italic>ambera</italic> (<italic>sadri lang</italic>) and <italic>Syzygium cuminii</italic> are grinded and boiled with banana leaf and concentrated to one fourth of the initial volume. The concentrate is then administered orally to the patient to cure blood dysentery. One glass water solution of bark extract is consumed once a day in empty stomach early in the morning for 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days to cure jaundice.</td><td>Indigestion, dysentery, cough and cold, worm, infection, hypertension, heat stroke<bold>,</bold> digestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Annona squamosa</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 284.</td><td>Stomach disorders</td><td>Ripe fruit pulp are used for curing stomach problem.</td><td>Diabetes and wounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]; ulcer, tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> L. UBKV FOR 283</td><td>Blood pressure</td><td>Leaves are used in curry to control pressure.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Centella asiatica</italic> (L.) Urb.<break/>UBKV FOR 257</td><td>Jaundice, typhoid, body pain, pneumonia, diabetes, cough, gastroenteritis, dysentery, stomach disorder, appetiser, dog bite, vegetable</td><td>- Leaves of <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, bamboo and <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> with earthworm are boiled with water and sieved, and half a glass solution is taken for 3 times a day for 3&#x000a0;days to treat aundice and typhoid.<break/>- Leaves are eaten as vegetables which also help in removing body pain and fever.<break/>- Leaf extract in water solution and one glass of this solution is taken during early morning in empty stomach to heal wounds.<break/>- Roots are either eaten raw or cooked with potato (fried) for curing the pneumonia, jaundice and diabetes.<break/>- Besides this therapy, <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> and cardamom (2&#x02013;3 nos.) are grinded and hot water solution is made which is orally administered for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days.<break/>- Seeds of <italic>Piper nigrum</italic>, barks of <italic>Cinnamomom camphora</italic>, roots of <italic>halufan</italic>, and seeds of cardamom are mixed, grinded with <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, made into tablets and sun dried which is consumed with hot water three times for phenomena, joint pain, appetite and cough.<break/>- The plant/leaf extract is consumed empty stomach (2 spoons for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days) to cure gasteroenteritis, dysentery and other stomach problems. It is also consumed as an appetiser and digestive tonic.<break/>- The plant extract is mixed with sugar candy or palm candy taken 1 glass/day in empty stomach for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days to treat stomach disorders.</td><td>Constipation, indigestion, diarrhoea, dysentery, stomach problems, stomach ache, skin disease, blood related problems, diabetes, tonsillitis, cold, health and memory tonics, insomnia, blood pressure, chicken pox, stomach worm, leucorrhoea, poor urination, jaundice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Centella annua</italic> M. Schub. &#x00026; B.-E. van Wyk<break/>UBKV FOR 301</td><td>Gastroenteritis, stomach disorder, stomach pain, dysentery, liver problem,</td><td>The plant is either cooked as vegetable or its extract is consumed to get relief from gasteroenteritis, dysentery and stomach disorders. Its extract solution with water is taken daily as liver tonic.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Alstonia scholaris</italic> (L.) R. Br.<break/>UBKV FOR 09</td><td>Cough and cold, stomach worms of human and domestic animals, cough of domestic animals (pig), alcoholic beverage</td><td>Smelling of flowers cure cough and cold.</td><td>Increase lactation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>];</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Calotropis procera</italic> R. Br. UBKV FOR 297</td><td>Swelling body, hydrocoel</td><td>Leaves are burnt lightly on fire and dressed on swelling area to get relief from pain. Leaves are smeared with vegetable oil and heated, then applied on scrotum to cure hydrosol. The process is continued for a week.</td><td>Nocturnal eneuresis, tumour, leprosy, dropsy, cut and wound, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rauvolfia serpentine</italic> (L.) Benth ex Kurz.<break/>UBKV FOR 271</td><td>Paralysis, diabetes, fever, cuts and wounds, pneumonia, jaundice, stomach worm, dysentery, snake bite, gastroenteritis, stomach pain, snake repellent</td><td>Roots are eaten in empty stomach or its powder/extracts can also be taken for at least 3&#x000a0;months to cure diabetes. Leaves are rubbed on the body for curing paralysis. Bark is grinded adding water and kept for half an hour. This solution is taken as medicine for 3 times for curing fever and wounds. Leaf or root paste is applied on snale bite. It can simply be chewed to cure stomach pain, snake bites and dysentery. Entire plant or any other part is dried and powdered and taken in minute amount with water to cure jaundice. It should be taken in empty stomach early in the morning for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days. Root extract solution (1&#x02013;2 drops for 2&#x000a0;days) is administered orally to cure fever or stomach worms.</td><td>Hypertension, insanity, blood pressure, fever, malaria, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tabernaemontana divaricata</italic> R. Br. ex Roem. &#x00026;Schult<break/>UBKV FOR 14</td><td>Conjunctivitis</td><td>Flowers are simply rubbed on hands and its extract in the liquid form (only 1 drop for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days) is used to cure eye infection.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Thespesia populnea</italic> (L.) Sol. ex Corr&#x000ea;a<break/>UBKV FOR 354</td><td>Toothache, healing, cuts andwound</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Colocasia esculenta</italic> (L.) Schott<break/>UBKV FOR 22</td><td>Malaria, blood purifier</td><td>Fruits are cooked as vegetable and eaten with meal to cure malaria. This also cleanses blood.</td><td>Constipation, weakness, alopecia, blood circulation, cuts and injuries, liver problems, hair lengthening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Areca catechu</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 286</td><td>Periodic problems of women</td><td>Betel leaf and nuts are masticated to get relief from gastric problems. Young roots of <italic>Areca catechu</italic> and flowers of <italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> are crushed together to extract juice. The juice is sieved, added with salt and lightly boiled which is then consumed twice daily by woman for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cocos nucifera</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 309</td><td>Weight loss, hair vitalizer</td><td>Coconut milk is consumed to cure stomach problem, loose body fat and control hair loss.</td><td>Itching, sore in nose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phoenix sylvestris</italic> (L.) Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 341</td><td>Asthma, cough, dehydration, diarrhoea, fever, heart-related problems, pain, dental pain, tuberculosis</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Inflammation and wounds, nervous debility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hemidesmus indicus</italic> (L.)<break/>Schultes<break/>UBKV FOR 360</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Asparagus racemosus</italic> Willd.<break/>UBKV FOR 255</td><td>Cuts and wound, urine disorder, kidney and body swelling</td><td>Root extract is added with water, sieved and solution is consumed in empty stomach daily for 4&#x02013;5&#x000a0;days for curing urine disorder. Roots are also pasted with rice, mixed with half a glass of water and consumed in empty stomach for a week or two to get relief from body and kudney swelling. Leaf extract is applied on wounds of domestic animals and dressed.</td><td>Health tonic, brain tonic, cough and cold, cut and wound, fever, diabetes, dysentery, abortion, stomach disorder, piles, tuberculosis, bronchitis, back pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ageratina adenophora</italic> (Spreng.) R.M. King &#x00026; H. Rob.<break/>UBKV FOR 276</td><td>Massaging body, cuts and wounds</td><td>Barks and roots are washed and cooked in oil then sieved to remove the solid particles. The oil solution used to massage any body part during winter once a day for 2&#x000a0;days.<break/>Leaves are crushed in between the palms and then applied on cuts and bandaged.</td><td>Cuts and wounds, dysentery and jaundice, antifungal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ageratum conyzoides</italic> L. UBKV FOR 29</td><td>Cuts and wounds</td><td>Leaves are washed and crushed for extracting its juice and applied on cuts including leaves. It is tied with a piece of cloth, which results in healing cuts as well as stops bleeding.</td><td>Stomach ache, cuts and wounds, stop bleeding, antihelmenthic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eupatorium odoratum</italic> L. UBKV FOR 30</td><td>Cuts and wound, bleeding</td><td>Leaf extract is applied on cuts to stop bleeding and healing as well.</td><td>Stop bleeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tagetes erecta</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 352</td><td>Dental problem, mouth ulcer, cuts and wounds</td><td>Leaf extract is applied on cuts and dressed for healing. Flower extract is applied on mouth for healing ulcers. Leaves are chewed early in the morning to stop bleeding during brushing of teeth.</td><td>Blood coagulator, cuts and wounds, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Diplazium esculentum</italic> (Retz.) Sw.<break/>UBKV FOR 33</td><td>Stomach problem</td><td>Leaves are cooked as vegetable and eaten with rice for curing stomach problem.</td><td>Constipation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> L<italic>.</italic><break/>UBKV FOR 35</td><td>Stomach pain, diarrhoea</td><td>Root extract administered orally twice a day to treat diarrhoea. Tender leaves are chewed raw in empty stomach twice a day for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days to get relief from stomach pain.</td><td>Headache, fracture, blood dysentery, pimples, skin eruptions, tooth ache, leprosy, gonorrhoea, diabetes, pimples, anaemia, and scorpion sting, virility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Basella alba</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 292</td><td>Skin burns, blood pressure</td><td>The entire plant is pasted and applied on infected part once to get relief from burn. Cooked as vegetable to reduce blood pressure but is not taken by people having cut and wounds.</td><td>Tuberculosis, dysentery, constipation, intestinal disorder, vomiting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Oroxylum indicum</italic> (L.) Benth.<break/>UBKV FOR 34</td><td>Jaundice, cuts and wounds, body pain, liver problem</td><td>Flowers and leaves are cooked and taken with meal for curing jaundice and regulate blood pressure. Bark soaked in water used for taking bath also cures jaundice. Bark powered and mixed in water for taking bath is used for curing pneumonia. Dried bark powder is applied on cuts and wounds to heal. Bark extract consumed early in the morning for 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days cure jaundice and liver problem.</td><td>Jaundice, regulate blood pressure, cough, fever, pneumonia, stomach/chest/body pain, bronchial asthma, diarrhoea, dysentery, joint pain, appetiser, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Brassica rugosa</italic> (Roxb.) L.H. Bailey<break/>UBKV FOR 294</td><td>Skin eruptions, ulcers, headache</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ananas comosus</italic> (L.) Merr.<break/>UBKV FOR 282</td><td>Stomach worms</td><td>Two teaspoons of leaf extract are consumed in empty stomach daily for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;weeks against stomach worms.</td><td>Leaf extract to kill worms; fruit juice against scurvy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Opuntia ficus-indica</italic> Haw.<break/>UBKV FOR 340</td><td>Tuberculosis</td><td>Jelly-type branch after peeling is cooked with wild onion and ghee till it is completely dried which is then consumed after meal three times a day to cure tuberculosis.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 298</td><td>Gastroenteritis, appetiser, digestive</td><td>Unripe fruits cooked and eaten to improve digestion or eaten raw to get relief from oral infection. Flowers are cooked as vegetable to maintain appetite. Both ripe or unripe fruits are eaten to cure gasteroenteritis.</td><td>Digestion, jaundice, dysentery, tooth ache, cough, indigestion, liver tonic, piles, heart problem, skin infection, fracture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Chenopodium album</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 302</td><td>Clearing stool, piles, gastroenteritis</td><td>Plant is cooked as vegetable and consumed for clearing stool, curing piles and gasteroenteritis.</td><td>Fever and influenza, constipation, intestinal worms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic> (Roxb.ex DC.) Wight &#x00026; Arn.<break/>UBKV FOR 272</td><td>Asthma, heart problem, diabetes, stomach disorder, gastroenteritis, appetiser</td><td>Bark extract solution is administered orally to cure heart problem. Bark of <italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic>, <italic>Alstonia scholaris</italic> and fruits of <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic>, <italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic> and <italic>Emblica officinalis</italic> are powdered and its solution in a glass of water is consumed once a day early in the morning for 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days as appetiser and cure gastroenteritis. Small pieces of bark is boiled in water and concentrated, cooled and taken in doses of two teaspoon of this cooled solution is consumed twice a day before meal or the bark pieces are powdered adding sweet candy and two teaspoon of this powder is consumed mixed in a glass of water to cure diabetes. Bark is soaked in water overnight and the solution is taken early in the morning for curing gastroenteritis and also as liver tonic. Half glass bark extract in water solution is administered orally twice a day for 5&#x02013;7&#x000a0;days for curing breathing and heart problem.</td><td>Skin disease, leucoderma, liver disorder, fractured bones, tuberculosis<bold>,</bold> cardiac problem, hypertension, pimples and other minor skin eruption, cardio tonic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia bellerica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 45</td><td>Cough and cold, stomach disorder, indigestion, gastroenteritis</td><td><italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic>, <italic>Piper nigrum</italic>, <italic>Terminalia chebula,</italic> cloves and <italic>Cinnamomom camphora</italic> are crushed together and made into tablets which are administered in empty stomach for curing cough. A glass of root extract is administered once a day for a week in empty stomach to cure stomach disorder. Besides the root xtract is also used to massage on stomach where pain is felt. Fruits are crushed into tablets and administered in empty stomach once a day to cure cough and cold. Fruit pulp extract is boiled (1&#x000a0;kg fruit in 2&#x000a0;l) and the hot solution is consumed for curing gasteroenteritis. Fruit pulp is crushed to tablets and taken empty stomach twice a day for a month for curing severe cough and cold. Dry fruit is crushed to powder and swallowed to cure stomach problem.</td><td>Skin disease, cold, constipation, leucoderma, grey hair, rheumatism, diarrhoea, dysentery, indigestion, dyspepsia, cooling agent, health tonic, cuts and wounds, tonsillitis, bronchitis, piles, dropsy, leprosy, headache, asthma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz. UBKV FOR 46</td><td>Almost for all sickness, appetiser, cough and cold, gastroenteritis, jaundice, liver, pneumonia</td><td>Fruits of <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic>, <italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic>, <italic>and Emblica officinalis</italic> are dried and one fruit of each is soaked in water for 24&#x000a0;h and taken in empty stomach for making the liver strong and also as appetiser. Parts of plants are beaten to powder or is boiled and consumed twice a day for curing any kind of sickness. Fruits are crushed and mixed with water consumed for treatment of cold and cough. Two teaspoons dried fruit pulp powder is consumed twice a day in empty stomach for indigestion, cough and cold. Fruit pulp is boiled, cooled and the solution is consumed emptyty stomach (one glass a day for 4&#x02013;5&#x000a0;days) for curing cough. Flowers are cooked and consumed to cure cough. Fruit pulp is boiled with black salt, crushed into tablets, sundried for few days and then consumed early in the morning to cure gastroenteritis. Fruits are soaked over night in water overnight and then the solution is taken in empty stomach as appetiser, cure jaundice and making liver strong. Fruits are also chewed to get relief from cough and cold as well as pneumonia.</td><td>Carminative, laxative, digestive, appetiser, constipation, piles, stomach disorder/pain, tonsillitis, diabetes, intestinal ulcer, rheumatism, urinary problem, skin problem, cold and cough, respiratory troubles, fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cuscuta europaea</italic> L. UBKV FOR 311</td><td>Jaundice</td><td>The whole plant is boiled and either taken bath with light warm water once a day for 2&#x02013;3 times or a glass of this solution mixed with salt is consumed as a therapy for jaundice.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ipomoea batatas</italic> (L.) Lam.<break/>UBKV FOR 326</td><td>Tumours of the mouth and throat, asthma, burns, fever, diabetes</td><td>Rhizomes are cooked and consumed by diabetic patients</td><td>Diabetes, scorpion sting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ipomoea carnea</italic> Jacq.<break/>UBKV FOR 327</td><td>Fungal infection between toes and fingers</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Fungal infection between toes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bryophyllum pinnatum</italic> Kurz.<break/>UBKV FOR 295</td><td>Burn injuries, cuts and wound</td><td>Leaves are grinded, applied on affected part and dressed.</td><td>Gall bladder stone, piles, stomach problems, antiseptic, kidney stone, skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Coccinia coridifolia</italic> Cogn.<break/>UBKV FOR 307</td><td>Lowers blood pressure</td><td>Fruits are cooked as vegetables and taken with meal to lower blood pressure.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Coccinia indica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 308</td><td>Lowers blood pressure, gastroenteritis</td><td>Fruits are chewed or cooked as vegetables to lower blood pressure. Leaves are pasted and added with water. It is consumed for curing gasteroenteritis.</td><td>Hypertension, healing wound, ulcer, jaundice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lagenaria siceraria</italic> (Molina) Standl.<break/>UBKV FOR 330</td><td>Boils</td><td>Tender leaf extract are used to treat boils.</td><td>Jaundice, diarrhoea and dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Luffa aegyptiaca</italic> Mill.<break/>UBKV FOR 332</td><td>Anaemia, liver disorder, menstrual problems</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Momordica dioica</italic> Roxb. ex Willd.<break/>UBKV FOR 335</td><td>Stomach disorder, fever</td><td>Fruits are consumed to cure stomach disorder. One glass leaf extract twice a day is consumed for 2&#x000a0;days to cure fever.</td><td>Urinary trouble, piles, diabetes, jaundice, ulcer, dysentery, ear pain, breast swelling, hair vitalizer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dillenia indica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 62</td><td>Stomach disorder</td><td>Bark is boiled and taken for curing stomach disorder.</td><td>Bark to get relief from indigestion, gasteroenteritis, diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dioscorea belophylla</italic> Voigt<break/>UBKV FOR 65</td><td>Appetiser, jaundice, body pain, stomach disorder, pneumonia</td><td>Fruits are cut into pieces and soaked in water overnight, boiled and eaten as appetiser. Tuber is crushed and messaged on the whole body once a day to get relief from pain. Tuber is cut into pieces and partially boiled and is dip in water for a night. In morning it is fried as curry with little oil and eaten with meal for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days for curing pneumonia.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Dioscorea bulbifera</italic> L. UBKV FOR 312</td><td>Jaundice</td><td>Tubers are crushed and soaked in water for 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;min. One glass of this solution is consumed to treat jaundice.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Shorea robusta</italic> Gaerth f.<break/>UBKV FOR 68</td><td>Cuts and wounds, burns, stomach pain, blood coagulant, dysentery</td><td>Bark powder/extract is and mixed with water to form solution and taken 3 times a day in empty stomach for curing stomach problems. Bark powder is applied on burns once a day for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days for relief.</td><td>Gonorrhoea, diarrhoea, dysentery, burning sensation, chest pain, pox, ear pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Elaeocarpus ganitrus</italic> Roxb. ex G. Don<break/>UBKV FOR 313</td><td>Piles, good sleep, asthma, cough</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Baccaurea remiflora</italic> Lour. UBKV FOR 289</td><td>Skin disease</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Baccaurea sapinda</italic>
<break/>(Roxb.) M&#x000fc;ll.-Arg<break/>UBKV FOR 290</td><td>Tooth ache</td><td>Twigs are used to brush teeth to get relieve from tooth pain.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Codiaeum variegatum</italic> (L.) A. Juss.<break/>UBKV FOR 310</td><td>Gastroenteritis, ulcers, fencing, decorative, religious, fuel wood</td><td>The whole plant is simply used for fencing purpose, decorative purpose, after the plant is dried it is used as fuel wood, and the leaves is used as religious purpose (puja).</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Emblica officinalis</italic> Gaerth.<break/>UBKV FOR 263</td><td>Hair loss, liver problem, stomach pain</td><td>Raw fruits are eaten to get relief from stomach pain. Fruits of <italic>Emblica officinalis</italic>, <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> and <italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic> are dried, crushed and made into powder. One teaspoon of this powdered in water solution is consumed daily early in the morning to restrict hair loss and to cure liver problem.</td><td>Constipation, fever, itching, digestive, gasteroenteritis, haemorrhage, jaundice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic> (Willd. ex A. Juss.) M&#x000fc;ll.-Arg.<break/>UBKV FOR 323</td><td>Ornamental (landscape)</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 264</td><td>Diarrhoea, headache</td><td>Sugar candy and few drops of <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> latex are mixed and consumed for treatment of diarrhoea. Seeds are pasted with water and applied on forehead for curing headache.</td><td>Cuts and wounds, skin disease, seeds digestive, twigs used in tooth and gum problem, rheumatic pain, night blindness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mallotus tetracoccus</italic> (Roxb.) Kurz.<break/>UBKV FOR 333</td><td>Skin diseases, ring worm</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L. UBKV FOR 84</td><td>Cough, headache, dental problem, jaundice</td><td>Leaf extract is massaged in neck for 3 times a day for 5&#x000a0;days for curing cough; however during the therapy period non-vegeterian food is avoided. Seed oil extract is applied on head to get relief from headache. Leaf extract is mixed with sugar and consumed for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days to cure jaundice. Alternately, fruits are also boiled with grains of <italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> and consumed to cure jaundice. Twigs are used for brushing teeth for healthy dentals.</td><td>Piles, wounds (human and animal), joint pain, jaundice, headache, fever, boils, dysentery, stomach problems, indigestion, skin disease, hair loss, sores, boils, burns, rheumatic swelling, stomach worms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acacia catechu</italic> (L. f.) Willd.<break/>UBKV FOR 251</td><td>Cuts and wounds, burns, sore throat, diarrhoea, digestion</td><td>Soft wood is cut in small pieces and boiled with water for some time and left for cooling to soilidify. The preparation is smeared with betel leaf for chewing to cure gastric problem.</td><td>Leaf for indigestion, bark, gum and root to control rheumatism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]; body ache, fracture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]; toothache, cough and cold, stomach pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; astringent, boils and skin eruptions, diarrhoea and dysentery, bleeding from nose, chest pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> (L.) Delile<break/>UBKV FOR 275</td><td>Evil spirit</td><td>Dental problems</td><td>Jaundice, itching, skin disease, worms, maggot wounds, dental problems, easy delivery, burns, asthma, fever, headache, stomach problems, indigestion, cholera, diarrhoea, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]; indigestion and gas problem of cattle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bauhinia malabarica</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 293</td><td>Stomach pain</td><td>Leaves are boiled and consumed daily for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;months to get relief from stomach pain after pregnancy.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cajanus cajan</italic> (L.) Mill<break/>UBKV FOR 296</td><td>Gall bladder stone, diabetes, jaundice and liver problem</td><td>Leaf extract is taken to cure diabetes. Fruits are eaten to get rid of gall bladder stone. Leaf extract solution is made with 200&#x000a0;ml of water and 100&#x000a0;g of either palm candy or sugar candy and administered orally once in the morning for 3&#x000a0;days in empty stomach. Roots are also used for curing jaundice by grinding them with water, sieved and 200&#x000a0;ml solution administered orally early morning in empty stomach for 3&#x000a0;days.</td><td>Jaundice, dysentery, ear pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cassia alata</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 299</td><td>Bees sting, allergy, appetiser for children, weakness</td><td>Leaves are crushed and applied on bee sting and infected area of skin infection. Bark extract is consumed for appetiser and health tonic.</td><td>Skin disease, body pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cassia sophera</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 300</td><td>Dysentery, cuts and wounds, cough, blood purifier</td><td>Leaf, flower and root extract is consumed to cure dysentery, wounds, cough and purify blood.</td><td>Diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hippocrepis emerus</italic> (L.) Lassen<break/>UBKV FOR 325</td><td>Skin infection</td><td>Leaves are crushed and rubbed on infected skin for curing.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 93</td><td>Reddening of eye</td><td>Leaf extract not more than a drop is applied for curing red eye.</td><td>Orchitis and depurative, infertility, dental pain, head ache, kidney/urine trouble, piles, sores, diarrhoea, dysentery, hydrocoel, jaundice, wounds and swelling, placenta prolepses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 344</td><td>Swelling, tooth pain</td><td>Seed oil extract is massaged to reduce swelling. Tender branches are used as tooth brush to cure dental pain.</td><td>Fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tamarindus indica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 353</td><td>Neck pain, tonsils and swelling</td><td>Fruits are soaked in cold water for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days, mixed intensively and seeds are removed. The solution is taken a glass a day for curing neck pain, tonsil and swelling. Leaves can also be eaten for curing neck pain and swelling for both human beings and animals.</td><td>Diarrhoea/dysentery (human and animals), indigestion, fever, piles, ulcer, nausea, vomiting, swelling, jaundice, gastropathy, wounds, scorpion bite, scabies, stomach pain, boils, cold, cough, skeletal flurosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 356</td><td>Diabetes, joint pain</td><td>Whole plant is cooked and consumed to cure diabetes and joint pain. Seeds are also taken in empty stomach with water to curb diabetes.</td><td>Alopecia, diabetes, stomach problems, easier pregnancy, diarrhoea of animals, increase lactation of cattles, joint pain of animals, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Quercus castanopsis</italic> H. L&#x000e9;v.<break/>UBKV FOR 346</td><td>Neck pain</td><td>Flowers are eaten for removing fish or meat bones stuck in the neck.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> (Curtis) P. Karst.<break/>UBKV FOR 322</td><td>Asthma, lungs problem, lowers cholesterol</td><td>The fruiting body is cooked as vegetable and consumed to control the diseases/ailments.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Clerodendrum viscosum</italic> Vent.<break/>UBKV FOR 246</td><td>Skin disease, stomach worm, stomach pain, tooth pain</td><td>Leaves are boiled taken bath to get cure from body itching. Tender leaves and <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> are crushed, and the extract (1&#x02013;2 teaspoons for children and adult, respectively) is consumed in empty stomach twice a day for 3&#x000a0;days to get relief from stomach worm and stomach pain. Twigs are used to brush the teeth to get relief from tooth ache.</td><td>Pain, skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Gmelina arborea</italic> Roxb. UBKV FOR 247</td><td>Appetiser, piles, abdominal pain, burning sensation, fever, headache, ulcer</td><td>Flowers are cooked and consumed to control the diseases/ailments.</td><td>Vomiting, diarrhoea, weakness, snake bite, cut and wound, piles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Leucas aspera</italic> (Willd.) Spreng.<break/>UBKV FOR 331</td><td>Stomach disorder, swelling, headache, stop bleeding, headache, body pain, tooth pain, cuts and wounds</td><td>Half a cup leaf extract with salt is takenr 2&#x02013;3 times a day to cure stomach disorder or swelling. Leaf extract or any plant part is inhaled to get relief from headache. Leaf extract is applied on cuts to stop bleeding and heal as well. Tender plant is cooked and consumed to get relief from body pain and gastroenteritis. Leaves are dried, mixed with raw rice and powdered, and half cup of its water solution is consumed in empty stomach daily for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days to remove swelling. Roots are chewed after dinner for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days to get relief from dental pain.</td><td>Cuts and worms of cattle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]; skin disease, sore in thigh [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 267</td><td>Cough and cold, neck pain, cancer, gastroenteritis</td><td>Leaf extract of <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> and <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> are mixed with water, sieved and the solution is mixed with 5&#x000a0;ml honey which is consumed 3&#x02013;4 times a day for 2&#x000a0;days to cure cough. Leaves mixed with ginger are chewed to get relief from cough and cold. Taking three leaves daily anytime with water in a day helps to keep cancer away. For curing gastroenteritis and cough, leaf extract can be taken any time in a day. Dried young stem are laced and tied around neck to avoid any disease.</td><td>Asthma, cold and cough, fever, bronchitis, genito-urinary disorders, diaphoteric, antiperiodic, stimulating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cinnamomom camphora</italic> (L.) J. Presl<break/>UBKV FOR 303</td><td>Stomach disorder, diabetes, reduce weight</td><td>Dried bark or leaves can be taken as such for curing stomach disorder, diabetes and also helps in reducing weight.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Machilus villosa</italic> (Roxb.) Hook. f.<break/>UBKV FOR 361</td><td>Joint pain</td><td>Bark extract is placed on joints for an hour to get relief from pain.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Careya arborea</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 125</td><td>Body pain, dysentery</td><td>Bark extract is sieved and solution is taken in empty stomach once a day for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days to cure dysentery. Bark extract is also administered externally to get relief from body pain.</td><td>Dysentery, cough, mouth and throat infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lagerstroemia speciosa</italic> (L.) Pers.<break/>UBKV FOR 138</td><td>Ulcers and sore, diabetes, piles, to obtain white and strong teeth,</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 345</td><td>Nose bleeding</td><td>Leaves of <italic>Punica granatum</italic> and black cumin are grinded adding water and 2&#x02013;3 drops are dropped in nose to stop nose bleeding. Fruits when ripe are consumed to increase blood.</td><td>Diarrhoea, dysentery, bronchitis, fever, indigestion, heart problem, eye and ear infection, jaundice, nasal congestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Abroma augusta</italic> (L.) L.f.<break/>UBKV FOR 274</td><td>Night wetting, jaundice and stomach disorders</td><td>For night wetting&#x02014;bark of <italic>A. augusta</italic> and early roots of <italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> are mixed, washed and grinded into paste with palm candy. The paste is mixed with required amount of water and sieved. The solution is taken in empty stomach twice a day till the problem persists.<break/>For jaundice&#x02014;bark of roots is peeled and paste is made after grinding with sugar candy. The paste is mixed with water and stored overnight. The solution is taken in empty stomach during early hours of morning for 3&#x000a0;days.<break/>For stomach disorder&#x02014;roots and barks are washed, grinded lightly and soaked in water for overnight to form a jelly-like solution. The jelly is taken in empty stomach once a day for 5&#x000a0;days.</td><td>Menstrual disorder, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]; blood dysentery, diarrhoea, night wetting, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> L. UBKV FOR 324</td><td>Tonsillitis, dandruff, hair loss</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Mennorrhagia dysentery, fever, headache, burn, boil, skin disease, cough and cold, fatigue, hair fall, abortion, burning sensation, twitching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Melastoma malabathricum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 144</td><td>Cuts and wounds, stomach ulcers, dysentery, diarrhoea, dental pain</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Pneumonia, diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss.<break/>UBKV FOR 256</td><td>Allergy, fever, pneumonia, small pox, appetite problem, brushing teeth, stomach disorder, skin disease, tooth pain</td><td>Leaf extract in water solution taken twice a day in empty stomach to get relief from fever.<break/>Domestic animals is also treated same way for fever. Half a glass juice extract is also administered orally daily for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days to cure pneumonia. Leaf extract is also consumed as appetiser. Leaves are boiled in water and used for taking bath for curing itching, fever and pox. For curing fever, leaves of neem and rice are grinded to powder and taken 1 spoon twice a day in empty stomach. Leaves are fried and consumed to cure mouth ulcers. Twigs are used to brush the teeth to get relief from tooth pain and dental problems. Leaves are beaten into tablets, sun dried and taken in empty stomach for curing gastric, appetite problems, fever, and other stomach disorder.</td><td>Allergy, skin disease, fever, boils, cut and wounds, cough and cold, eye and ear infection, dental problems/tooth brush, leprosy, intestinal worms, ulcer, stomach, ear and tooth ache, acidity, vomiting, blood sugar, diabetes, malaria, blood purifier, heart problems, typhoid, health tonic, cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Melia azedarach</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 334</td><td>Fatigueness, cough, fever, appetiser, deworming, cuts and wound, vomiting, skin disease, dental problem, piles, pox, mosquito repellent, purify blood,</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Blood purifier, reduce blood pressure, skin disease, head ache, fever, stomatitis, stomach worm, stone in urinary bladder, fever, antiseptic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (Willd.) Miers ex Hook. f. &#x00026; Thom.<break/>UBKV FOR 146</td><td>Stomach pain, diabetes</td><td>Small pieces of roots are soaked in water overnight and the solution is consumed empty stomach early in the morning 1&#x02013;2 times a day for 3&#x02013;6&#x000a0;months to cure diabetes and stomach pain.</td><td>Rheumatism, jaundice, diabetes, burning sensation during urination, piles, eye infection, fever, diarrhoea, dysentery, malaria, skin disease, appetiser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Entada rheedii</italic> Spreng.<break/>UBKV FOR 315</td><td>Diarrhoea of domestic animals</td><td>The fruit pulp is crushed mixing with water and salt to feed domestic animals on banana leaf for treating diarrhoea.</td><td>Cuts and wounds, skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artocarpus hetrophyllus</italic> Lam<break/>UBKV FOR 254</td><td>Skin diseases, asthma, ulcers</td><td>Mature leaves are chewed mixed with salt.</td><td>Antiseptic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]; fever, boil, cut and wound, skin diseases, diarrhoea, toothache, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artocarpus lakoocha</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 154</td><td>Skin ailments, headache</td><td>Paste of leaf and bark are applied on infected part</td><td>Leaf and bark to treat skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus benghalensis</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 316</td><td>Chronic diarrhoea and dysentery, piles</td><td>Latex in water solution is used orally for treatment of piles. Bark extract for diarrhoea/dysentery.</td><td>Diabetes, gout, dysentery, diarrhoea, asthma, muscular pain, gasteroenteritis, hair vitaliser, joint pain, sexual disorder, stomach pain, dental problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus carica</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 317</td><td>Swellings, tumours, ulcers</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Constipation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus elmeri</italic> Merr.<break/>UBKV FOR 318</td><td>Fever</td><td>Leaves are boiled, and luke warm solution is taken for 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;days or leaf can be chewed for curing fever.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus geniculata</italic> Kurz<break/>UBKV FOR 319</td><td>Diarrhoea</td><td>Tender leaves either after cooking consumed or dried, powdered and consumed in water solution to cure diarrhoea.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus hispida</italic> L. f.<break/>UBKV FOR 320</td><td>Ulcer, jaundice, fever, liver problems</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Control blood sugar level, mouth ulcer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus racemosa</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 321</td><td>Mouth disease of domestic animals</td><td>Leaves are fed to the cattle/goat to cure their mouth disease.</td><td>Leucorrhoea, piles, stomach pain, dysentery, fiver, ulcer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Morus alba</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 337</td><td>Jaundice, fever, appetiser for domestic animal</td><td>Roots are cut into small pieces, wrapped in cloth and tied on neck for 12&#x000a0;days or leaves are boiled and after cooling the solution is consumed once a day to cure jaundice.</td><td>Sore throat, cough, brain and heart tonic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 336</td><td>Blood pressure, gastroenteritis, cold and cough, body pain, clearing stool, cuts and wounds of domestic animals, snake repellent</td><td>Leaf extract is taken to cure high pressure and gastroenteritis (1 glass for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;months daily). Root extract are helpful to cure cold and cough and heal wounds of domestic animals. Pods are eaten as vegetable which also help to regulate blood pressure and body pain. Tender leaves are also cooked as vegetables to cure gastric, body pain, digestion and clearing stool. Roots are cut into small pieces and spread around the house as snake repellent.</td><td>Tumours, leucoderma, liver disorder, snake bite, piles, cough, stomach worm, diarrhoea, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Musa balbisiana</italic> Colla<break/>UBKV FOR 338</td><td>Liver problem, gastroenteritis, dysentery, swelling, body severing, stomach disorder, teeth pain</td><td>Dark black roots of banana and <italic>Clerodendrum viscosum</italic> are crushed to paste and placed on chicks facing sunlight for an hour to get relief from dental pain. A full teaspoon of latex is consumed three times a day for 3&#x000a0;days to cure loose motion. Fruits or flowers are cooked and taken with daily meal to curing stomach disorder. Roots of banana are used for a night to reduce swelling and control body shiveringt. Ripe fruits or a cup of pseudostem sap is orally taken once for curing dysentery. One cup tender leaf extract solution is taken empty stomach early in the morning for at least 15&#x000a0;days to cure liver problems and dysentery. Fruit peel is pasted, mixed with glass of water and is consumed once in a day in empty stomach for about 15&#x000a0;days for curing gastroenteritis.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Myristica longifolia</italic> Wall. UBKV FOR 165</td><td>Stop bleeding, cough</td><td>Roots are soaked for few minutes and boiled in water till it turns red in colour. One cup of this solution after cooling is consumed as health tonic in empty stomach once a day for 3&#x000a0;days. The solution is also fed to domestic animals. Roots are crushed; boiled with water, cooled and one cup of this solution is taken daily twice for 3&#x000a0;days to stop menstrual bleeding. Root extract water solution of young plants is taken to cure cough.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 270</td><td>Dysentery/loose motion, stomach pain</td><td>Ripe fruits or tender leaves are eaten for curing dysentery. Tender leaves are chewed in empty stomach for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days or can be crushed and taken with adding water for curing stomach pain. Tender leaves extract (2&#x02013;3 spoons) is taken for 2&#x02013;3 times a day till loose motion is cured.</td><td>Cold and cough, fever (human and animal), indigestion, dysentery, diarrhoea (human and animal), ulcer, vomiting, dental pain, joint pain, dental pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Syzygium cumini</italic> (L.) Skeels<break/>UBKV FOR 169</td><td>Cough and cold, blood dysentery, gastroenteritis</td><td>Fruits are consumed to cure cough and cold, blood dysentery and gastroenteritis.</td><td>Indigestion, dysentery, diarrhoea, loose motion, stomach pain, diabetes, anti-inflammatory, sore throat, bronchitis, ulcers, joint pain, piles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Nyctanthes arbor-tristis</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 339</td><td>Fever</td><td>Leaf is either rubbed or its two teaspoon extract is consumed 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days for curing fever. Flowers are also used as medicine following the same procedure.</td><td>Rheumatism, malaria, fever, cough and cold, fracture, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Averrohoa carambola</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 288</td><td>Jaundice and liver problems</td><td>A glass of pulp juice is consumed three times a day in empty stomach for week to get a relief from jaundice.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 268</td><td>Cough and cold</td><td>Dried fruit powder in water solution is consumed for curing cough and cold.</td><td>Asthma, cold and cough, rheumatism, constipation, eye infection, throat infection, indigestion, piles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Plumbago zeylanica</italic> L. UBKV FOR 342</td><td>Hydrocoel, fever</td><td>Roots are tied with arms or thigh for 20&#x02013;30&#x000a0;min during morning to cure hydrosol. Rhizomes are crushed, boiled and half a glass taken early in the morning daily for 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;days to treat fever.</td><td>Eroenteritis, skin diseases, scabies, ulcer, diarrhoea, dysentery, indigestion, night blindness, abortion, leprosy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Arundo donax</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 287</td><td>Headache</td><td/><td>Skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bambusa vulgaris</italic> Schrad. UBKV FOR 291</td><td>Night wetting</td><td>The nodes of bamboo after cutting are left in the open for 2&#x000a0;days. The water in the nodes is collected after 2&#x000a0;days and given to young children for night wetting.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (L.) Pers.<break/>UBKV FOR 261</td><td>Cuts and wounds, bleeding, vomiting, nose bleeding, increase lactation of domestic animals</td><td>The grass is crushed, and extracts are applied on wounds to stop bleeding and healing as well. <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> and leaves of <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> are crushed together, and two teaspoons of this extract is taken orally to stop vomiting. Water solution of this extract is made mixing palm candy and half a cup of this solution is consumed once a day to stop nose bleeding.</td><td>Shoot and leaf juice to control vomiting, skin disease, leprosy, piles, asthma, arthritis, burning urination, indigestion, cancer, eye and mouth problem, dysentery, blood purifier, control nose bleeding, anti-septic, snake bite, stop bleeding, wounds, miscarriage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eleusine indica</italic> (L.) Gaertn.<break/>UBKV FOR 314</td><td>Weakness of children</td><td>Whole plant is crushed with water, and 2&#x02013;3 teaspoons of this solution is administered orally once a day for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days as tonic for general weakness.</td><td/></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Thysanolaena latifolia</italic>
<break/>(Roxb. ex Hornem.) Honda<break/>UBKV FOR 355</td><td>Tonsillitis, boils, abortion</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Boils, burns, tonsillitis, abortion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L. UBKV FOR 357</td><td>Hair loss</td><td>Half a glass tender leaf extract are consumed daily early in the morning for a month to prevent hair fall.</td><td>Flatulence in goats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Polygonum dichotomum</italic> Blume.<break/>UBKV FOR 269</td><td>Baby crying</td><td>Tender leaves of <italic>Opuntia ficus-indica</italic> and <italic>Polygonum dichotomum</italic> are mixed with milk and crushed together. Few drops are given for 2 times a day to stop baby crying.</td><td>Leaves and tender shoots against dental problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Polygonum hydropiper</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 343</td><td>Dysentery</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Blood coagulant, dysentery, gasteroenteritis, astringent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Anthocephalus cadamba</italic> (Roxb.) Miq.<break/>UBKV FOR 285</td><td>Asthma</td><td>Leaves of <italic>Anthocephalus cadamba</italic> along with alum powder are boiled together and then the water after is taken half cup 2 times a day for 2&#x000a0;days and again after 1&#x000a0;month taken for 2&#x000a0;days in the same quantity of dose (i.e. should be continued in interval of every months which helps in curing asthma.</td><td>Cholera, diarrhoea, dysentery, pyorrhoea, tooth brush, tooth pain, pimples, sores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) Corr&#x000ea;a<break/>UBKV FOR 218</td><td>Stomach disorder, appetiser, dysentery</td><td>One glass of fruit pulp juice is taken three times a day to cure dysentery, diarrhoea and other stomach problems. It is also used as appetiser.</td><td>Fever, piles, diarrhoea and dysentery, digestion, head ache, stomach ache, gastroenteritis, cough, asthma, tumours, mouth ulcer, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Osbeck UBKV FOR 306</td><td>Vomiting, dysentery, blackening of nerve of children after birth</td><td>Leaf or root extract of C. lemon, bark of papaya and roots of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> are administered externally once a day for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days for curing blackening of nerve of children. Leaves and fruits are either smelled or consumed as raw to avoid vomiting.</td><td>Stomach ache, dysentery/diarrhoea, stomach worms, dandruff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Murraya koenigii</italic> (L.) Sprengel<break/>UBKV FOR 266</td><td>Gastroenteritis</td><td>Leaaves are consumed raw or as extract once a day in empty stomach to cure gasteroenteritis.</td><td>Leaf extract for black fever and diarrhoea, dysentery, diabetes, anaemia, vomiting, cut and wound, inflammation, appetiser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scoparia dulcis</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 347</td><td>Piles, paralysis, diarrhoea, gastroenteritis</td><td>Leaf, stem, root or flower extract are consumed (2 teaspoons/day for 3&#x000a0;months) to cure piles. These parts are powdered and applied in the nose (2 times a day for 3&#x000a0;months) for treatment of paralysis. Plant (without root) extract solution is consumed in empty stomach (1 glass daily for 5&#x000a0;days) for curing diarrhoea and gasteroenteritis.</td><td>Cough, burning sensation in pulmonary artery and veins, painful urination, diabetes, bronchitis, piles, cough, fever, tumour, boils, pneumonia, kidney stones, antiseptic, menstruation disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ailanthus integrifolia</italic> Lam.<break/>UBKV FOR 224</td><td>Fever</td><td>Resin extract from the plant is lightly burnt for fumigation of patient to get relieve from fever.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Datura metel</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 262</td><td>Diarrhoea, dental pain, ear pain, cut and wounds, fatigueness/weakness of domestic animals</td><td>Fruits are roasted and consumed to cure diarrhoea. Root extract is mixed with water to feed domestic animals as general health tonic.<break/>The fruit pulp is mixed with coconut oil and heated which is then applied on ear after cooling twice a day for 2&#x000a0;days to get relief from pain. Unripe fruits are used to heal wound. Fruits or seeds crushed with mustard oil and heated and applied on teeth during morning for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days to get relief from pain.</td><td>Asthma, boils, leprosy, diarrhoea, piles, cold and cough, joint pain, antirabies, gout, sores, dandruff, hair loss [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum indicum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 348</td><td>Pneumonia, diabetes</td><td>Root beaten and made in the form of tablets to cure pneumonia. Fruits are cooked and eaten as vegetables for curing diabetes.</td><td>Ringworm in cattle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum khasianum</italic> C.B. Clarke<break/>UBKV FOR 230</td><td>Dental pain</td><td>Fruits are burnt and placed on the teeth for getting relief from pain.</td><td>Dental pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L. UBKV FOR 349</td><td>Antiseptic</td><td>Fruits are cut and rubbed for a week to treat infection.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 350</td><td>Dysentery, vomiting, asthma, bronchitis, fever, urinary discharge, cuts and wound</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Wound, jaundice, abdominal swellings, stomach pain, head ache, fever, gonorrhoea, piles, dysentery, boils, eye infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum xanthocarpum</italic> Schrad. &#x00026; J.C. Wendl.<break/>UBKV FOR 362</td><td>Stomach disorder, blood purifier, eye problem</td><td>Bark extract is boiled in water or fruits are eaten after ripening for purifying blood and cure gastroenteritis and dysentery. Fruit juice is applied twice a day to control eye problem.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sterculia villosa</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 233</td><td>Dysentery</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Seminal weakness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Christella dentata</italic> (Forssk.) Brownsey &#x00026; Jermy<break/>UBKV FOR 258</td><td>Cuts and wound</td><td>Leaves of <italic>Christella dentata</italic>, <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> and <italic>Clerodendrum viscosum</italic> are boiled and the solution is used to wash wounds till healed. The plant is also used as housefly and insects repellent.</td><td>Cuts and wounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Typha elephantina</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 358</td><td>Urine problem, purifies breast milk, internal bleeding</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Lantana camara</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 250</td><td>Cough and cold</td><td>Leaf extract is taken orally (1&#x02013;3 spoon 3 times a day) or the leaves are chewed or consumed with rice to cure cough and cold.</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> L. f.<break/>UBKV FOR 248</td><td>Dysentery, piles, diabetes, prevent unwanted hair growth, construction, furniture, agricultural implements, fodder</td><td>Young leaves are used as fodder.</td><td>Flowers used in bronchitis and urinary discharges; to promote hair growth along with coconut oil; leaf sap used to treat irregular menstrual cycle, burning sensation, kidney and skin disease, headache, tooth ache, swelling, stomach burning, skin irritation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Vitex negundo</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 273</td><td>Fever</td><td>Half a glass leaf extract solution in water is taken twice a day (before meal in morning and after meal at night) for 3&#x000a0;days to treat fever before meal in the morning and after meal at night.</td><td>Gout, fever, headache, cough and cold, sinusitis, diarrhoea, cardiac problems, rheumatism, fat burning, bedsore, wound, backbone pain, fracture, body swelling, joint swelling greying hair, memory vitaliser, stomach problem, swelling of joints, liver problem, jaundice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cissus quadrangularis</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 304</td><td>Fracture, paralysis, leg pain</td><td>Whole plant is crushed and dressed on the fractured body part for 24&#x000a0;h. The process is repeated for three times or till recovery. The therapy is same for domestic animals also.</td><td>Stem extract is used to treat broken bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cissus repanda</italic> Vahl<break/>UBKV FOR 305</td><td>Bone fractures, cuts and wounds</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aloe vera</italic> L. Burm.f.<break/>UBKV FOR 279</td><td>Fire burnt skin, stomach disorder, body pain</td><td>Pulp is used for curing burnt skin. The entire plant can be grinded for juice extraction and consumed to get relief from stomach disorder. Half a glass extract is also consumed daily early in the morning adding water and salt for relief from body pain.</td><td>Diabetes, general health, cough and cold, burns, cut and wound, fracture, arthritis, backbone pain, hepatitis, dermatitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]; stomach ache, piles, intestinal worms, eye disease, skin disease, allergy, tumours, liver tonic, purgative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Alpinia malaccensis</italic> (Burm.f.) Roscoe<break/>UBKV FOR 280</td><td>Cuts and wounds, sores, digestive</td><td>Inner part of the leaf is eaten as vegetables to help digestion.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma caesia</italic> Roxb.<break/>UBKV FOR 259</td><td>Period of woman, chest pain, stomach pain, gastroenteritis, cuts and wounds</td><td>Fruits are meshed with salt and consumed bu. woman to relief from periodic pain. It is taken in empty stomach (1&#x02013;1.5) teaspoon for 3&#x000a0;days. Tuber extract is mixed with water and taken to get relief from chest pain, stomach pain and gastric. The extract is applied on wounded part and dressed for 2&#x000a0;days.</td><td>Dried rhizome powder to treat skin disease, bone fracture, rhizome in rheumatic pains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.<break/>UBKV FOR 260</td><td>Lactation problem of domestic animals, crack on legs, cough and cold, fever, stomach disorder, cuts and wounds</td><td>Flowers are crushed, mixed with feed and fed to animals for increasing the milk production.<break/>Alum and lime is crushed to powder and mixed with unripe rhizomes and placed on ruptured portion of the skin for 20&#x000a0;min and then washed, dried and messaged with coconut oil is used for massage once a day for 3&#x000a0;days till recovery. Fresfh rhizomes are roasted in mustard oil for few minutes and applied on wounds. The process continues till the wound is healed. Alternately, the rhizomes are boiled and consumed for healing of wound and relief from fever, cough and cold. Fresh rhizome extract is added with water and a cup of the solution is consumed after dinner for to stomach disorders like gastric pain. This solution is also consumes as health tonic.</td><td>Dried and fresh rhizome powder to treat cuts and wound, skin disease, inflammation, cough and cold, sores, boils, bone fracture, swelling, muscular or body pains, snake bite, stomach ache, bronco asthma, antidote against poison, blood purifier, jaundice and liver disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Zingiber zerumbet</italic> (L.) Sm.<break/>UBKV FOR 359</td><td>Snake bite, septic, cuts and wounds, back pain, pregnancy</td><td>Rhizome is pasted and placed on any bites or affected parts. Also used as massage to remove body pain or back pain. Rhizomes with leaves of <italic>Raulfia serpentina</italic> and tubers of <italic>bedodgumi</italic> are crushed together. This extract is mixed with half cup of water and consumed twice a day after meal for 2&#x000a0;days which helps to boost pregnancy.</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Number of species used as ethnomedicine for a particular disease/ailment</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Human diseases/ailments</td><td>Species used</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Stomach-related disorder (stomach problem, dysentery, diarrhoea, indigestion, stomach pain)</td><td>40</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cuts and wounds</td><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Pain (joints pain, body pain, chest pain, neck pain, tooth pain)</td><td>25</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Jaundice/liver problem</td><td>19</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cough and cold</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Gastroenteritis</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fever</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Skin-related disease</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Diabetes</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Appetiser and ulcer</td><td>9 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Headache, piles,asthma and bleeding (internal, nose)</td><td>8 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Burns</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Swelling and pneumonia</td><td>6 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Hair loss/fall/dandruff problems, blood pressure and paralysis</td><td>5 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vomiting and bite (dog, bees, snake)</td><td>4 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Urine disorder, blood purifier and blood disease, sore throat and sores, tonsil</td><td>3 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Small/chicken pox, malaria, hydrocoel, tumours, cancer, septic, boils, eye infection/conjunctivitis/red eye, clearing stool, reduce weight, tuberculosis, heart problems, night wetting, periodic problems of women</td><td>2 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Typhoid, baby cry, dehydration, bronchitis, urinary discharge, abortion, gall bladder stone, pulmonary/lungs problem, anaemia, purifies breast milk, pregnancy, blackening of nerve, cholesterol, alcoholic medicine, fatigueness, body severing, body massager</td><td>1 each</td></tr><tr><td>Veterinary/disease/ailments</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tongue/mouth disease and lactation problem</td><td>2 each</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Stomach worm, cough, diarrhoea, cuts and wounds, fatigueness/weakness and appetiser</td><td>1 each</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par16">Among the documented species, 92 species were used to cure multiple problems, while the rest were used to cure single disease each (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Similar observation was also reported by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The fungus <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> is used for asthma and lung problem. It also lowers cholesterol. According to the respondents, <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> is used to treat almost all diseases and mainly is used as an appetiser and to cure gastroenteritis, jaundice, liver, pneumonia, cough and cold. The maximum number of 12 diseases/ailments was cured by <italic>Melia azedarach</italic> followed by <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> and <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> which were used to cure 11 diseases/ailments each.</p><p id="Par17">The majority of the plant species (108) had more than one part that was medicinally important (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) as was also documented by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The indigenous communities mainly used the leaf of the plant for their ethnomedicinal uses as this part was maximum used with 83 species followed by the fruit (55 species), and least was the seed with four species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The leaves of the ethnomedicinal plants were also documented to be used by the majority of remedies in traditional medicines in several reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The fruit was also reported as dominant and widely used part for traditional medicines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The other parts used were branch (32 species), stem (28 species), bark (26 species), flower (23 species) and rhizome/tuber (eight species). The whole plant of 24 species was used for ethnomedicinal purposes. Destructive harvesting is done when the whole plant is used. Even the sap, latex, resin and pulp of the plant species were also used. Harvesting patterns of the leaves or foliage, root, rhizomes and tubers indicate their possibility of vulnerability for becoming endangered as was earlier observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">Proper selection of species, parts, as well as preparation and administration methods were very important in traditional healthcare systems. Ethnomedicinal formulations were administered both externally (skin, nasal, eye and dental) and internally as oral doses (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) as was also observed by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Most of the preparations were a mixture of different plant species, and in few cases, only one plant species was used. Different parts of a single species were also used to cure different diseases. Almost all plant parts were used to prepare different medicinal formulations: roots, rhizomes, tubers, bark, leaves, flowers, fruit, seeds, young shoots, whole plants, and gum and latex. Doses of these preparations were not standardised but administered on the basis of age, physical appearance and intensity of the illness. Children were usually administered with smaller doses than adult. The course of frequency of treatment is decided by the type of disease and its severity.</p><p id="Par19">Mode of preparation included juice, paste, decoction, powder, infusion and chewing raw plant parts. The administration of the therapy is raw, dried form in small pieces or powdered, solution or mixed with water/milk/honey and paste/lotion. Generally, fresh part of the plant is used for the preparation of medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The majority of formulations were prepared as juice followed by paste and decoction. Usually, the underground parts were used in dried form as was also earlier reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The preference for roots and rhizomes to prepare traditional remedies follows the scientific basis that roots generally contain high concentrations of bioactive compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. There are several reports on the administration of ethnomedicine by various authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. It was also observed that herbal treatment is still preferred by the residents for bone fracture and dislocation over modern treatment. Senior citizens trust more upon traditional treatment system over the modern methods as they believe no side effect with the traditional ethnomedicine. Similar observations were also documented by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The present study documented 140 ethnomedicinal plant species from North Bengal, of which 62 species were also reported in earlier studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] from north India with similar ethnomedicinal uses. The medicinal uses of the species also reported from north India is compared with our study and is presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Medicinal uses of the species in present study versus north Indian studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scientific name</th><th>North Indian studies</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Abroma augusta</italic> (L.) L.f.</td><td>Urinary infection, bronchitis, diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Areca catechu</italic> L.</td><td>Boils and skin eruptions, diarrhoea and dysentery, bleeding from nose, chest pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> (L.) Delile</td><td>Jaundice, burns, headache, cholera, diarrhoea, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Acorus calamus</italic> L.</td><td>Dysentery and diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) Corr&#x000ea;a</td><td>Fever, diarrhoea, dysentery, gastroenteritis, sun burn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ageratum conyzoides</italic> L.</td><td>Muscular pain, cuts, wounds, stop bleeding, piles, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aloe vera</italic> L. Burm.f.</td><td>Stomach ache, piles, intestinal worms, eye disease, skin disease, tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Alstonia scholaris</italic> (L.) R. Br.</td><td>malaria, pneumonia, stomach a<break/>che [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]; bark to treat snake bite, asthma and cardiac troubles, latex is applied to ulcers, sores and tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm.f.) Wall. ex Nees</td><td>Malaria, fever, stomach problems, worms, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Annona squamosa</italic> L.</td><td>Diarrhoea, dysentery, indigestion, dandruff, lice, spinal problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]; Constipation and abdominal swelling of animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Anthocephalus cadamba</italic> (Roxb.) Miq.</td><td>Cholera, dysentery, pimples [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artocarpus hetrophyllus</italic> Lam</td><td>Cough, leprosy, ulcers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Arundo donax</italic> L.</td><td>Skin disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Asparagus racemosus</italic> Willd.</td><td>Bleeding nose, epilepsy, arthritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]; fever and constipation of domestic animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss</td><td>Wounds, cold, diabetes, cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Basella alba</italic> Stewart.</td><td>Constipation, nose sorosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> L<italic>.</italic></td><td>Tooth ache, pimples, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Calotropis procera</italic> R. Br.</td><td>Pox, cholera, malaria, boils, skin disease, pregnancy, digestive tonic, indigestion of domestic animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td>Dysentery, tooth ache [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Centella asiatica</italic> (L.) Urb.</td><td>Leprosy, cough ulcer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cissus quadrangularis</italic> L.</td><td>Stem extract is used to treat broken bone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Osbeck</td><td>Fever and mouth disease of animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Clerodendrum viscosum</italic> Vent.</td><td>Tumour, malaria, snake bite, boils, burns, cut and wounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Colocasia esculenta</italic> (L.) Schott</td><td>Stop bleeding, removes redness of skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.</td><td>Cuts and wound, bone fracture, swelling, muscular or body pains, snake bite, stomach ache, blood purifier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> (L.) Pers.</td><td>Dysentery, snake bite, stop bleeding, wounds, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Datura metel</italic> L.</td><td>Asthma, boils, leprosy, diarrhoea, piles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]; cold, pneumonia of cattle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus benghalensis</italic> L.</td><td>Diabetes, hair vitalizer, stomach pain, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]; diarrhoea and dysentery of domestic animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus carica</italic> L.</td><td>Boils, skin disease, constipation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus hispida</italic> L. f.</td><td>Mouth ulcer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ficus racemosa</italic> L.</td><td>Piles, boils, diarrhoea, dysentery, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> L.</td><td>Fever, abortion, burning sensation, twitching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L.</td><td>Branches used as tooth brush to remove tooth pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> L.</td><td>Cough, bronchitis, asthma, malaria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.</td><td>Dysentery, ear ache, vomiting, heat stroke, digestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Melia azedarach</italic> L.</td><td>Skin disease, head ache, stomach worm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> L.</td><td>Dental pain, head ache, wounds placenta prolepses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Momordica dioica</italic> Roxb. ex Willd.</td><td>Diabetic, breast swelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> L.</td><td>Diarrhoea, dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]; flowers to restore health and proper urination, fruits for paralysis and diseases of the liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Morus alba</italic> L.</td><td>Fruits good for kidney and liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Murraya koenigii</italic> (L.) Sprengel</td><td>Fever, diarrhoea, dysentery, appetiser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Nyctanthes arbor-tristis</italic> L.</td><td>Fever, cough dysentery, leaves for indigestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Oroxylum indicum</italic> (L.) Benth.</td><td>Cough, mouth sore, ulcer, bronchial asthma, joint pain, appetiser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Plumbago zeylanica</italic> L.</td><td>Diarrhoea, indigestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pongamia pinnata</italic> L.</td><td>Malaria, fever, piles, cough, skin disease and boils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L.</td><td>Wounds, fever, diarrhoea ulcer, vomiting, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td>Diarrhoea, indigestion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rauvolfia serpentine</italic> (L.) Benth ex Kurz.</td><td>Insanity, blood pressure, intestinal disorder, vomiting, snake bite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L.</td><td>Wounds (human and animal), joint pain, sores, boils, burns, rheumatic swelling, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Shorea robusta</italic> Gaertn f.</td><td>Diarrhoea, dysentery, burning sensation, chest pain, pox, ear pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum khasianum</italic> C.B. Clarke</td><td>Dental pain and decay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> L.</td><td>Wound, jaundice, abdominal swellings, stomach pain, head ache, fever, gonorrhoea, piles, dysentery, boils, eye infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Syzygium cumini</italic>(L.) Skeels</td><td>Dysentery, sore throat, bronchitis, ulcers, joint pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tabernaemontana divaricata</italic> (L.) R. Br. ex Roem. &#x00026; Schult.</td><td>Eye disease, appetiser, dental pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tagetes erecta</italic> L.</td><td>Hydrophobia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tectona grandis</italic> L. f.</td><td>Bronchitis, urinary discharges, headache, swelling, stomach burning, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic> (Roxb.) Wight &#x00026;Arn.</td><td>Dysentery, tumours, asthma, fractured bones, diabetes, anaemia, hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb.</td><td>Skin disease, cold, constipation, cuts and wounds, piles, dropsy, leprosy, headache, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz.</td><td>Constipation, stomach disorder/pain, urinary problem, cold respiratory troubles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (Willd.) Miers ex Hook. f. &#x00026; Thom.</td><td>Jaundice, fever, diarrhoea, dysentery, malaria, appetiser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Trigonella foerum-graecum</italic> L.</td><td>Easier pregnancy, foot and mouth disease of animals, diarrhoea of animals, appetiser, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Vitex negundo</italic> L.</td><td>Headache, rheumatism, body swelling, joint swelling, diarrhoea of cattle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Use value</title><p id="Par20">The use value of a species indicates the ethnobotanical importance of a particular species in an area or by a community. The higher the value for a species, the higher is the importance of the species i.e. were most utilised or exploited. The use value range found was 0.01&#x02013;0.13 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) The highest use value of 0.13 was estimated for <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, followed by <italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic> and <italic>Oroxylum indicum</italic> each with 0.09; <italic>Musa</italic> sp<italic>.</italic>, <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> and <italic>Leucas aspera</italic> each with 0.08; and <italic>Dillenia indica</italic> with use value of 0.07. Use values of 0.05 were found for <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic>, <italic>Mangifera indica</italic>, <italic>Diplazium esculentum</italic>, <italic>Dioscorea belophylla</italic> and <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic>, while <italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic>, <italic>Morus alba</italic>, <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic>, <italic>Cynodon dactylon</italic> and <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> had a use value of 0.06. Use value on medicinal ethnobotanical plants was also earlier reported and similar conclusions made [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. These species were utilised because of their therapeutic uses in multiple diseases and were abundantly available in wild and were also all grown in the home gardens.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Conservation status</title><p id="Par21">Various authors have feared that these ethnomedicinal species are disappearing from the wild due to unsustainable exploitation of these species and destruction of habitat of these species due to deforestation. Workers had reported the conservation status of medicinal plants of the Terai region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] and Darjeeling Himalayas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] of West Bengal. In this study, the documented plant species were compared with these reports for the conservation status of these plant species. It was found that 38 ethnomedicinal plant species documented in this study were reported of their conservation status from Darjeeling Himalayas also (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). According to the Darjeeling studies, plant species were classified as abundant, common, endangered, frequent, planted, rare and sparse and the number of documented species falling in these categories were four, five, three, five, five, three and 13, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Another study from the Terai region of West Bengal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] also classified the plant species in terms of conservation status like rare, frequent and sparse, and 31 ethnomedicinal plant species documented in this study (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were categorised according to their conservation status in the Terai study.</p><p id="Par22">Many plants growing wild and traditionally used are endemic and have become rare, threatened or endangered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], so they need to be conserved. Reserves of ethnomedicinal plants in developing countries are diminishing and in danger of extinction as a result of growing trade demands for cheaper products and new plant-based therapeutic markets in preference to more expensive target-specific drugs and biopharmaceuticals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Genetic biodiversity of ethnobotanic plants is continuously under the threat of extinction as a result of commercial exploitation, grazing, environment-unfriendly harvesting techniques, loss of growth habitats and unmonitored trade of medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] This is because ethnomedicinal plants were freely harvested by users from their immediate environment either for their own use or traded domestically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. The harvesting of these multiple use species can put them under threat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] but can also lead to better chances for their conservation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] especially through home gardens.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par23">The Chilapatta Reserve Forest and its fringe areas are rich in biodiversity of ethnomedicinal plant species. A total of 140 plant species represented by 116 genera and 65 families were documented for medicinal purpose. Majority of the plant species (108) have more than one part that was medicinally important. The indigenous communities mainly used the leaf of the plant for their ethnomedicinal uses. The curing of 58 human diseases from these documented plant species itself explains the importance of this area in national and international interest. Gastric problem is common in this area and 40 plant species were used for the treatment of this disease. <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> and <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> were the most valuable species in terms of its maximal use with higher use value. Comparison with the previous regional ethnomedicinal studies, we observed that 30 plant species documented in the present study were not having earlier reports. This means that the use of 30 plant species have been reported for the first time from this area for ethnomedicinal use. It was found that 38 ethnomedicinal plant species documented in this study were earlier reported for their conservation status from adjoining areas including endangered, frequent, planted, rare and sparse. The communities should be encouraged with improved cultivation techniques of commercially viable ethnomedicinal species through capacity building, timely policy intervention along with strong market linkage. This will ensure income generation and livelihood improvement and ultimate conservation of these species. The present information may serve as a baseline data to initiate further research for newly reported species for new compounds and biological activities which can be of immense value for societies to survive.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank all the participants in the study for providing ethnomedicinal information.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par24">This study is self-financed.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par25">The data and material is available from the corresponding author.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>SB, NP, GS, and V designed the study, collected the data and developed the manuscript. MK, SC, RWB and AJR improved the manuscript and restructured the data analysis. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par26">Prior oral informed consent was obtained from the local communities as well as from all individual participants.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par27">All participants gave consent for publication.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par28">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par29">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Merwea</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Swana</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Botha</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of ethnoveterinary medicinal plants in cattle by Setswana-speaking people in the Madikwe area of the North West Province of South Africa</article-title><source>J S Afr Vet Assoc</source><year>2001</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12219913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Elwin Lewis</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Medical botany plants affecting human health</source><year>2003</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>812</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>African medicinal plants in the search for new drugs based on ethnomedicinal leads</article-title><source>Ethnobotany and the search for new drugs</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild edible plants of Chandrapur district, Maharashtra, India</article-title><source>Indian J Nat Prod Resour</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payyappallimana</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadeeva</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><source>Traditional knowledge and biodiversity</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Yokohama</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United Nations University-IAS</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narzary</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brahma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Basumatary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild edible vegetables consumed by <italic>Bodo</italic>Tribe of Kokrajhar District (Assam), North-East India</article-title><source>Arch Appl Sci Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baheti</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandelwal</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of medicinal plants among tribes in Satpuda region of Dhule and Jalgaon districts of Maharashtra&#x02014;an ethnomedicinal survey</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>157</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeyaprakash</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyanar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Geetha</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional uses of medicinal plants among the tribal people in Theni districts (Western Ghats), Southern India</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>S20</fpage><lpage>S25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(11)60115-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pushpangadan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacological approaches to wound healing&#x02014;exploring medicinal plants of India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.08.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17884316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plant use of Chilapatta reserved forest in West Bengal</article-title><source>Indian Forester</source><year>2012</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>1124</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswakarma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pala</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional application of ethnomedicinal plants in Naxalbari area of West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Int J Usufruct Manag</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswakarma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pala</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Documentation and utilization pattern of ethnomedicinal plants in Darjeeling Himalayas, India</article-title><source>Int J Usufruct Manag</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Saharia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild edible plants sold in the local market of Garo hills, Meghalaya</article-title><source>J Frontline Res Arts Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Suresh CP, Bhutia KD, Shukla G, Pradhan K, Chakravarty S. Free list of wild edible fruit species of Sikkim Himalayas and their uses. Proceedings of the Second International Symposium on Minor Fruits and Medicinal Plants for Better Lives 2013; pp.17-37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranjitkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional knowledge and its transmission of wild edibles used by the Naxi in Baidi Village, northwest Yunnan province</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0082-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26846564?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26846564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeido</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zoo therapeutics utilized by residents of the community PocoDantas, Crato-CE, Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-5-21</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19656376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19656376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvez-Durand</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative ethnobotany and Amazonian conservation</article-title><source>Conserv Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1739.1994.08010225.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mekonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelbessa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of home garden plants in Sebeta-Awas District of the Oromia Region of Ethiopia to assess use, species diversity and management practices</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0049-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26296364?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26296364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvaiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal studies of aquatic plants of district Sialkot, Punjab (Pakistan)</article-title><source>J Med Plants Stud</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amjad</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Qureshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal inventory and folk uses of indigenous plants from PirNasoora National Park, Azad Jammu and Kashmir</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(15)30011-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamidou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boube</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahamane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahamane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellefontaine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uses and preferences of woody species in two protected forests of Dan Kada Dodo and Dan Gado in Niger</article-title><source>J Hortic For</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/JHF2014.0374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Food or medicine? The food&#x02013;medicine interface in households in Sylhet</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.09.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25240587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25240587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study on wild plants used by Lhoba people in Milin County, Tibet</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0009-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25879656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25879656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00141;uczaj</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stawarczyk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosiek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kujawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild food plants and fungi used by Ukrainians in the western part of the Maramure&#x0015f; region in Romania</article-title><source>Acta Soc Bot Pol</source><year>2015</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5586/asbp.2015.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of plants of Raigarh area, Chhattisgarh, India</article-title><source>Int Res J Biol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Deborah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enumeration of wild edible fruits from Boda hills and Kolli hills</article-title><source>Int J Appl Biol Pharm Technol</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiracko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Owuor</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gakuubi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanzala</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of ethnobotany of the AbaWanga people in Kakamega county, western province of Kenya</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunn</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunn</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introduction</article-title><source>Landscape ethnoecology: concepts of biotic and physical space</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>New York and Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Berghahn Books 9</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sticher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zapotec and Mixe use of tropical habitats for securing medicinal plants in Mexico</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02866601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finerman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using home gardens to decipher health and healing in the Andes</article-title><source>Med Anthropol Q</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/maq.2003.17.4.459</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14716919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14716919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000f5;ukand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal landscape: the perception of the landscape as a source of medicinal plants</article-title><source>Trames</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><issue>64/59</issue><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3176/tr.2010.3.01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agelet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonet</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vall&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Home gardens and their role as a main source of medicinal plants in mountain regions of Catalonia (Iberian Peninsula)</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02864783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepp</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moerman</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of weeds in ethnopharmacology</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-8741(00)00385-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11282438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandebroek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goetghebeur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Douterlungne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arr&#x000e1;zola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation between accessibility, diversity and indigenous valuation of vegetation in the Bolivian Andes</article-title><source>J Arid Environ</source><year>2009</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2009.03.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethno-medicobotanical investigation among Rava tribe of Jalpaiguri district .NBU</article-title><source>J Plant Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>65</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-veterinary medicinal usage of flora of greater Cholistan desert (Pakistan)</article-title><source>Pak Vet J</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvaraju</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyanar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathinakumar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used in ethno-veterinary medicine by Malayali tribals in Salem district of Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>Med Plants</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devendrakumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anbazhagan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnoveterinary medicinal plants used in Perambalur District, Tamil Nadu</article-title><source>Res Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal study of plants used for the treatment of livestock diseases in Tikamgarh District of Bundelkhand, Central India</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>S460</fpage><lpage>S467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12980/APJTB.4.2014C1067</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25183130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25183130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uprety</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Poudel</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chettri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional use and management of NTFPs in Kanchenjunga Landscape: implications for conservation and livelihoods</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0089-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27142597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27142597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bose</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh Roy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Das Mahapatra (Sarkar)</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Das Mahapatra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used by tribals in Jalpaiguri district, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>J Med Plants Stud</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyanar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>SankaraSivaraman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical investigations among tribes in Madurai district of Tamil Nadu (India)</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-2-25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16689985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rokaya</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprety</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Poudel</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Timsina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nzbergov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Asselin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigdel</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional uses of medicinal plants in gastrointestinal disorders in Nepal</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2014.10.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25456430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25456430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trials in bad taste</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/372410a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal study of medicinal plants in Sonebhadra district of Uttar, Pradesh, India with reference to their infection by foliar fungi</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2727</fpage><lpage>2746</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical studies of the Terai region of Kumaun, Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnoveterinary value of some plant species utilized by rural people of Jhansi district, Bundelkhand region</article-title><source>Res J Agri Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>324</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medico-ethnomedicinal inventory of Renukoot forest division of district Sonbhadra, Uttar Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Indian J Nat Prod Resour</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>457</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phondani</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooquee</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vishvakarma</surname><given-names>SCR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical uses of plants among the Bhotiya tribal communities of Niti valley in Central Himalaya, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17348/era.8.0.233-244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gairola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Painuli</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The treatment of jaundice with medicinal plants in indigenous communities of the sub-Himalayan region of Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2012.06.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22759701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22759701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gairola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Painuli</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants used for treating epilepsy by indigenous communities of sub-Himalayan region of Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2013.08.052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24029249?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24029249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gairola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqi</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Painuli</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used for treatment of dysentery and diarrhoea by the Bhoxa community of district Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2013.08.052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biomass production and vegetation analysis of Chilapatta reserve forest ecosystem of West Bengal</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Pundibari West Bengal</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ph. D. Thesis. Uttar Banga Krishi Viswavidyalaya</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chhetri</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Basnet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalikotay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhetri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parajuli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current status of ethnomedicinal plants in the Darjeeling Himalaya</article-title><source>Curr Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yonzone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhujel</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic resources, current ecological status and altitude wise distribution of medicinal plants diversity of Darjeeling Himalaya of West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>S439</fpage><lpage>S445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(12)60203-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation of biodiversity: present status &#x00026; future strategy</article-title><source>Taxonomy and biodiversity</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Delhi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CBS Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhujel</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Studies on the dicotyledonous flora of Darjeeling district. Ph. D. Thesis</source><year>1996</year><publisher-loc>Siliguri</publisher-loc><publisher-name>North Bengal University</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farooquee</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation and utilization of medicinal plants in high hills of Central Himalaya</article-title><source>Environ Conserv</source><year>1996</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0376892900038273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge of Bhotia tribal community on wool dying and its present status in the Garhwal Himalaya, India</article-title><source>Curr Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>817</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Nautiyal</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Semwal</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge of medicinal plant and wild edibles among the three tribal sub-communities of the Central Himalaya, India</article-title><source>Indigenous Knowl Dev Monit</source><year>2000</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants used in West Rahrr region of West Bengal</article-title><source>Nat Prod Radiance.</source><year>2008</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>465</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhillion</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Salleh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation needs and regulations for locally managed forests in the highlands of Dolakha district, Nepal</article-title><source>Environmental and development aspects of natural resource management in mountains</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Pelanduk Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etkin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local knowledge of biotic diversity and its conservation in rural Hausaland, Northern Nigeria</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2002</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1663/0013-0001(2002)056[0073:LKOBDA]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants of Tehrathum District, Eastern Nepal</article-title><source>Our Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wild edible plants of Koch Bihar district, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Nat Prod Radiance</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Azizullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name><name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal assessment of plant resources of Banda Daud Shah, District Karak, Pakistan</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24267174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24267174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanghi</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of some ethno-veterinary medicinal plants of Tendukheda, district Narsinghpur, Madhya Pradesh</article-title><source>Life Sciences Leaflets</source><year>2014</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takhar</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folk herbal veterinary medicines of southern Rajasthan</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>418</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Verma P, Mathur AK, Jain SP, Mathur A. In vitro conservation of twenty-three over exploited medicinal plants belonging to the Indian sub continent. Sci World J. 2012;12 10.1100/2012/929650.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhetri</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnoveterinary practices of some plant species by ethnic people of Parbat district, Nepal</article-title><source>Kathmandu Univ J Sci Eng Technol</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chettri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moktan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal studies on the tea garden workers of Darjeeling Hills</article-title><source>Pleione</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padal</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Satyavathi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal investigation of medicinal plants used by the tribes of PedabayaluMandalam, Visakhapatnam District, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Comput Eng Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yonzone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhujel</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal and aromatic plant diversity and resources of Darjeeling district of eastern Himalaya in India</article-title><source>Int J Adv Pharm Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>871</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yonzone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhujel</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of ethnobotanical and medicinal plants resources of Darjeeling district, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Int J Adv Pharm Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>729</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge and uses of medicinal plants in Macchegaun, Nepal</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptations of culturally and nutritionally important traditional foods in Eastern Himalaya: a case study with Adi women of Arunachal Pradesh</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>633</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of traditional medicinal plants used by tribe of Guna District, Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Curr Microbiol App Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>471</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal survey of medicinal plants used in Terai forest of western Nepal</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-8-19</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22591592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22591592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simbo</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal survey of medicinal plants in Babungo, Northwest Region, Cameroon</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-6-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20156356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20156356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanungo</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal survey of Surguja district with special reference to plants used by Uraon tribe in treatment of diabetes</article-title><source>Int J Herb Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization and conservation of wild plants by the tribal communities of Tripura</article-title><source>Indian Forester</source><year>2012</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Guria</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional herbal remedies for various ailments within the rural communities in the district of Bankura and Purulia, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Pharm Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>198</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of traditional medicinal plants used by indigenous people in North Kerala</article-title><source>Indian J Appl Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Majumdar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal uses of some plants by Tripuri and Reang tribes of Tripura</article-title><source>Nat Prod Radiance</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>180</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of Rajasthan&#x02014;an update</article-title><source>Am-Eurasian J Bot</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinhababu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-botanical study of medicinal plants used by tribals of Bankura district, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>J Med Plants Stud</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>104</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation strategies of medicinal plants with reference to North Bengal for a better tomorrow</article-title><source>J Todays Biol Sci Res Rev</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Samanta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal survey on medicinal plants of Ghatal block, West Midnapur District, West Bengal, India</article-title><source>Int J Curr Res Biosci Plant Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achar</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Somashekhara Boosanur</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivanna</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-medico-botanical knowledge of Tipturtaluk in Tumkur district of Karnataka, India</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>154</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konsam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thongam</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Handique</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of wild leafy vegetables traditionally consumed by the ethnic communities of Manipur, northeast India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0080-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26822996?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26822996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Avasthe</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical edible plant biodiversity of Lepcha tribes</article-title><source>Indian Forester</source><year>2012</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>803</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of wild plants used for starting fermented beverages in Shui communities of southwest China</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-015-0028-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26017691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ti&#x00163;&#x00103;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogo&#x0015f;anu</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ti&#x00163;&#x00103;</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal inventory of medicinal plants from the south-west of Romania</article-title><source>Farmacia</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>