<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3900687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24466308</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-38420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086995</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Metagenomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Community Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Community Structure</subject><subject>Species Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbial Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Metagenomics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Entomology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metamorphosis of a Butterfly-Associated Bacterial Community</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Microbiota of <italic>Heliconius erato</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>Tobin J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>W. Owen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>Noah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology and Cooperative Institute for Research in Environmental Sciences, University of Colorado at Boulder, Boulder, Colorado, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, Panama City, Republic of Panama</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Smagghe</surname><given-names>Guy</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Ghent University, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>tobin.hammer@colorado.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TJH WOM NF. Performed the experiments: TJH. Analyzed the data: TJH NF. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: WOM NF. Wrote the paper: TJH NF.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e86995</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 Hammer et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hammer et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Butterflies are charismatic insects that have long been a focus of biological research. They are also habitats for microorganisms, yet these microbial symbionts are little-studied, despite their likely importance to butterfly ecology and evolution. In particular, the diversity and composition of the microbial communities inhabiting adult butterflies remain uncharacterized, and it is unknown how the larval (caterpillar) and adult microbiota compare. To address these knowledge gaps, we used Illumina sequencing of 16S rRNA genes from internal bacterial communities associated with multiple life stages of the neotropical butterfly <italic>Heliconius erato</italic>. We found that the leaf-chewing larvae and nectar- and pollen-feeding adults of <italic>H. erato</italic> contain markedly distinct bacterial communities, a pattern presumably rooted in their distinct diets. Larvae and adult butterflies host relatively small and similar numbers of bacterial phylotypes, but few are common to both stages. The larval microbiota clearly simplifies and reorganizes during metamorphosis; thus, structural changes in a butterfly's bacterial community parallel those in its own morphology. We furthermore identify specific bacterial taxa that may mediate larval and adult feeding biology in <italic>Heliconius</italic> and other butterflies. Although male and female <italic>Heliconius</italic> adults differ in reproductive physiology and degree of pollen feeding, bacterial communities associated with <italic>H. erato</italic> are not sexually dimorphic. Lastly, we show that captive and wild individuals host different microbiota, a finding that may have important implications for the relevance of experimental studies using captive butterflies.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>T.J.H. was supported by a Chancellor's Fellowship from the University of Colorado. The National Science Foundation provided grants to W.O.M. (DEB-640279 and IOS-1052541) and N.F. (NSF-CAREER 0953331). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Butterflies are important herbivores and pollinators and are used as model systems in a variety of ecological and evolutionary fields <xref rid="pone.0086995-Boggs1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Like all animals, butterflies also host internal communities of microorganisms, yet their associations with these symbionts remain poorly understood. This knowledge gap persists despite a large and rapidly growing body of work on other insect groups demonstrating that microbes can have important effects on host nutrition, digestion, detoxification, and defense from predators, parasites, and pathogens <xref rid="pone.0086995-Douglas1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0086995-Engel1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Studies of butterfly-associated microorganisms therefore have the potential to advance our understanding of the biology of butterflies and their ecological and evolutionary interactions with plants and natural enemies.</p><p>Unfortunately, even basic information on butterfly microbial symbionts is lacking, making it difficult to identify the potential impacts that these microbes may have on butterfly ecology and evolution. While various bacteria have been isolated from the adult butterfly intestinal tract <xref rid="pone.0086995-Steinhaus1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, and the presence of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and <italic>Spiroplasma</italic> has been reported in the adults of some species <xref rid="pone.0086995-Tagami1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0086995-Russell1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, there are no community-level descriptions of the dominant microbial taxa present. Kingsley <xref rid="pone.0086995-KingsleyV1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> cultured multiple bacterial populations from the gut of newly emerged adult monarch butterflies, but such cultivation-based surveys are well known to misrepresent the community structure <italic>in situ</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0086995-Pace1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. To our knowledge, there have been no previous culture-independent studies of microbial communities associated with adult butterflies.</p><p>Additionally, while the larval gut microbiota of a handful of butterfly species have been described <xref rid="pone.0086995-Broderick1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, it is not known how microbial communities associated with larvae compare with those in the adult stage, nor how they may change during metamorphosis. In fact, this question has not been addressed in any lepidopteran since the advent of molecular tools for characterizing microbial diversity. Kingsley's survey of monarch gut bacteria <xref rid="pone.0086995-KingsleyV1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> included multiple developmental stages, but owing to a dependence on culturing and physiology-based taxonomic assignments, it is uncertain whether those findings are generalizable. We do know from work on other holometabolous insect groups that larvae may have few or no microbial symbionts <xref rid="pone.0086995-Lauzon1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Martinson1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, different microbiota <xref rid="pone.0086995-Vasanthakumar1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0086995-Brucker1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, or similar microbiota as adults <xref rid="pone.0086995-AriasCordero1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Colman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. We expected that butterfly larvae and adults would host distinct bacterial communities owing to the radical switch in diet from the larval to the adult stage of butterflies, as well as the changes in internal morphology and physicochemical conditions that accompany metamorphosis. Diet is a major factor structuring microbiota across animal taxa <xref rid="pone.0086995-Muegge1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Russell2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, and diet shifts may also underlie patterns of microbial variation across developmental stages of a single host. For example, nutritional or chemical differences between the diets of larvae and adults may differentially select for microbial taxa best able to grow at each stage. Conversely, those particular microbial taxa may aid the host in utilizing life-stage-specific resources by providing functions related to digestion, detoxification, and/or nutrient supplementation.</p><p>Perhaps the most striking contrast in feeding biology between butterfly larvae and adults is in the neotropical genus <italic>Heliconius</italic>. <italic>Heliconius</italic> larvae consume leaves and stems of cyanogenic glycoside-rich passion-flower vines <xref rid="pone.0086995-EnglerChaouat1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, while adults visit flowers to feed on pollen as well as nectar. Among butterflies, pollen feeding is an evolutionary innovation unique to <italic>Heliconius</italic>, and has led to major changes in reproductive biology and life history traits <xref rid="pone.0086995-Gilbert1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. We therefore focused on <italic>Heliconius</italic> to test for a possible differentiation in microbial community structure between the larval and adult stages. Additionally, <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies represent an ideal model system for microbial symbiosis research as they are collectable in the wild and experimentally tractable, and as a wide array of relevant ecological, evolutionary, and genomic information is available <xref rid="pone.0086995-The1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Werren1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In contrast, almost nothing is known about their microbiota, besides the sporadic presence of <italic>Wolbachia</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0086995-Werren1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Muoz1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Given their distinctive larval and adult diets, <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies also provide an opportunity to test whether associations with microbial symbionts have been important in the evolution of host traits related to herbivory and pollen feeding.</p><p>In addition to investigating how <italic>Heliconius</italic>-associated microbial communities change across different life stages, we also wanted to determine how wild and captive <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies may differ with respect to their microbiota. Many experimental studies of <italic>Heliconius</italic> (and other butterflies) have used lab- or insectary-reared subjects. Evidence from moth larvae <xref rid="pone.0086995-Xiang1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Belda1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> and other insects <xref rid="pone.0086995-Lehman1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Chandler1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> suggests that symbiont community structure can change when hosts are brought from the wild into captivity, an effect possibly mediated by artificial diets or selection history. Testing whether captive and wild butterflies are different in terms of their microbiota is important not only for future microbial investigations, but also for other types of studies on captive butterflies where the phenomena under question may be influenced by microbial symbionts (including, but not limited to, host plant use and defense against parasites or parasitoids).</p><p>We used a high-throughput DNA sequencing-based approach to characterize internal bacterial communities associated with the butterfly <italic>Heliconius erato</italic>, thus providing a foundation for future studies of microbial symbiosis in <italic>Heliconius</italic> and other butterflies. To test the hypothesis that the microbiota varies across the butterfly life cycle, we compared bacterial community structure in replicate larvae, pupae, newly emerged adults, and mature adults of <italic>H. erato</italic>. We also assessed variation in bacterial community diversity and composition between wild adults sampled from the field, wild adults maintained in an insectary, and the reared adult offspring of the latter to determine whether captive butterflies harbor bacterial communities representative of their wild counterparts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Insect collection and rearing</title><p>In April and May 2012, adult <italic>Heliconius erato</italic> butterflies were collected from a wild population as they visited flowers in Parque Nacional Soberan&#x000ed;a, Panama (9&#x000b0;7&#x02032;20&#x02033;N, 79&#x000b0;42&#x02032;54&#x02033;W), for which permission was provided by the Panamanian Environmental Authority (ANAM) under permit #SE/A-92-11. Voucher specimens have been deposited at the Fairchild Invertebrate Museum of the University of Panama. Thirteen individuals (nine males and four females) were stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C directly after field collection. All samples described below were preserved in the same manner.</p><p>We relocated nine additional wild-caught females to a nearby insectary, where they were housed under semi-natural conditions in separate mesh cages. They were supplied with flowers frequently visited by wild <italic>H. erato</italic> in this area (<italic>Psychotria elata</italic>, <italic>Lantana camara</italic>), and with an autoclaved sucrose and honeybee pollen solution. Potted <italic>Passiflora biflora</italic>, the main host plant of the specialist <italic>H. erato</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0086995-Smiley1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, were placed in the cages to elicit oviposition. Eggs were removed and placed individually in plastic cups. The parental females were sampled after a sufficient number of eggs were obtained, corresponding to appx. 2&#x02013;4 weeks in captivity. Given that females of <italic>H. erato</italic> only very rarely mate more than once in the wild <xref rid="pone.0086995-Walters1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, it is likely that the individuals in each brood are full siblings.</p><p>We reared larvae on plant material collected from potted <italic>P. biflora</italic> grown in an open-air greenhouse near the forest. One larva per brood was sampled two days into the fifth stadium, while it was actively feeding, as was the frass it had produced that day. Pupae were sampled midway through the pupal stage. Newly emerged adults were sampled immediately after they had excreted meconium. The rest of the adults were kept under identical conditions as described above for wild-caught parental females. One male and one female per brood were sampled four days after eclosion, by which point both sexes of this species have reached sexual maturity.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Sample processing</title><p>We used whole, surface-sterilized insects to describe the dominant bacterial taxa associated with the internal portion of the body. Insects were rinsed in sterile molecular-grade water (Sigma-Aldrich), soaked in 70% ethanol for 30 s followed by 10% bleach for 30 s, and rinsed again in sterile water. For adults, wings were clipped where they met the thorax prior to sterilizing the body. After surface sterilization the samples were ground under liquid N<sub>2</sub> with single-use, sterile mortar and pestles (Fisher Scientific). Frass samples were not surface sterilized.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>DNA sequencing and data processing</title><p>Bacterial communities were characterized using barcoded Illumina sequencing of 16S rRNA genes. Total DNA was extracted from homogenized material using the MoBio PowerSoil kit as described previously <xref rid="pone.0086995-Fierer1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. We used the primer pair 515F/806R to amplify the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene, and PCR conditions followed those described previously <xref rid="pone.0086995-Caporaso1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Amplicons were sequenced on the Illumina MiSeq platform, resulting in an average of 1779 150-bp reads per sample after filtering with default parameters for sequence length and minimum quality score in QIIME v. 1.6.0 <xref rid="pone.0086995-Caporaso2" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Sequences were clustered into operational taxonomic units (hereafter, &#x0201c;phylotypes&#x0201d;) at the 97% similarity level by reference-based picking with the QIIME implementation of UCLUST <xref rid="pone.0086995-Edgar1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> against the October 2012 release of the Greengenes database <xref rid="pone.0086995-McDonald1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> with remaining sequences clustered <italic>de novo</italic>. The Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) classifier <xref rid="pone.0086995-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> set at a minimum confidence level of 0.5 was used to assign taxonomy to the phylotypes. The centroid (seed sequence) used by UCLUST was chosen as the representative sequence for each phylotype. With representative sequences from the 10 most abundant phylotypes across all <italic>H. erato</italic> samples, we used SeqMatch to find the best high-quality matches &#x02265;1200 bp in the curated RDP 16S database <xref rid="pone.0086995-Cole1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p><p>Because this primer set can amplify non-bacterial rRNA gene sequences, phylotypes identified by the RDP classifier as chloroplast or mitochondrial 16S rRNA (which represented 24% of the sequences on average) were removed prior to downstream analyses. In order to standardize sequencing effort, all samples were rarefied by randomly selecting 500 sequences per sample. As the samples from which we obtained fewer than 500 bacterial sequences were excluded from further analysis, there are fewer replicates for pupae than were initially collected. This sequencing depth has been shown to be sufficient for detecting biological patterns in insect-associated bacterial communities <xref rid="pone.0086995-Jones1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> and other community types <xref rid="pone.0086995-Kuczynski1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Amplicon sequences and associated metadata from this study are publicly available in the EMBL-EBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/</ext-link>) under accession number ERP003400.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>We used nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis tests in R v. 3.0.0 <xref rid="pone.0086995-R1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> to determine whether there were significant differences in community richness or the relative abundances of individual bacterial taxa (families or phylotypes) with a Bonferroni correction applied to account for multiple comparisons. The family-level tests were conducted only on dominant families, defined as those contributing at least a median 2% of the sequences within any of the factor levels. To compare community composition between sample types, we used vegan <xref rid="pone.0086995-Oksanen1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref> to compute a Bray-Curtis dissimilarity matrix after Hellinger transformation of the phylotype count data. Subsequent multivariate analyses were conducted in PRIMER <xref rid="pone.0086995-Clarke1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Variation among samples in their bacterial taxonomic composition was visualized using constrained principal coordinates analyses <xref rid="pone.0086995-Anderson1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. We used Mantel tests to determine whether patterns of compositional dissimilarities among larvae were correlated with dissimilarities among their frass. Permutational multivariate ANOVA tests <xref rid="pone.0086995-Anderson2" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> were used to assess differences in bacterial community composition associated with several sample categories, with tests of life stage or frass versus larvae run using sample type as a fixed effect. Variation in the dissimilarity matrix linked to the level of relatedness among captive adults was tested using family as a random effect. Lastly, for all adult butterflies, a two-factor design was used to test the effects of captivity/rearing status and sex (both fixed).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Bacterial community dynamics across the life cycle</title><p>Bacterial phylotype richness varied among life stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086995-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). Median richness was similar between larvae and mature adults with 39 and 43 phylotypes per individual, respectively. In contrast, pupae and newly emerged adults were associated with roughly half as many phylotypes (median 17 and 22 phylotypes, respectively). Nearly identical patterns were observed when diversity was measured using the Shannon index, which takes relative abundances into account (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s001">Fig. S1</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). A comparison restricted to only the numerically dominant phylotypes&#x02013;those contributing at least 5 sequences per sample (1%)&#x02013;produced a similar pattern: median richness of dominant phylotypes was 12 in both larvae and mature adults, and 4 and 5.5 in pupae and newly emerged adults, respectively.</p><fig id="pone-0086995-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086995.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Bacterial community dynamics across <italic>H. erato</italic> larvae, pupae, newly emerged adults, and mature adults.</title><p>A. Boxplot of community phylotype richness. B. Constrained principal coordinates analysis showing variation in community composition over the life cycle. CAP1 and CAP2 are the canonical axes in principal coordinate space that best discriminate among life stages. Arrows indicate significant pairwise differences in composition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0086995.g001"/></fig><p>Bacterial community composition also varied across life stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086995-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.001). In agreement with the pattern shown in the constrained ordination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086995-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>), all pairwise comparisons were significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 except that between pupae and newly emerged adults. On average, only 13% of the phylotypes present in either the larva or mature adults of each replicate brood were present in both stages.</p><p>Communities from frass samples and the individual larvae that produced them were not significantly different in composition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s002">Fig. S2</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.16). Additionally, variation in community composition among larvae was reflected in their frass (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s002">Fig. S2</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, Mantel rho &#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.47).</p><p>The four life stages of <italic>H. erato</italic> analyzed here were dominated by six bacterial families: the Acetobacteraceae (Alphaproteobacteria), Moraxellaceae and Enterobacteriaceae (Gammaproteobacteria), Enterococcaceae and Streptococcaceae (Firmicutes), and an unclassified family in the Bacteroidetes phylum (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). Although family-level bacterial community composition varied substantially between individuals of the same life stage in some cases, all of these families excluding the Enterococcaceae and Enterobacteriaceae shifted significantly in relative abundance across the life cycle (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s003">Fig. S3</xref>, Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p><p>The 10 most abundant phylotypes present across all <italic>H. erato</italic> samples are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0086995-t001">Table 1</xref>. The split between larval and adult communities appears to be driven by the higher relative abundance of <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> in the larvae and of <italic>Asaia</italic>, <italic>Lactococcus</italic>, and an unclassified Bacteroidetes phylotype in the mature adults. Most of these phylotypes matched at 98&#x02013;100% identity to named isolates in the RDP database. Two phylotypes had highest similarity to sequences obtained from uncultured bacteria in ground beetle and honeybee digestive tracts.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0086995-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086995.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>
<bold>Dominant bacterial phylotypes in </bold>
<bold><italic>H. erato</italic></bold>
<bold>.</bold>
</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0086995-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0086995.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taxonomic classification</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larvae (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pupae (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New adults (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mature adults (18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parental adults (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild adults (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Best-scoring RDP match</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% ID</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Firmicutes (Enterococcaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Enterococcus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Proteobacteria&#x02021; (Enterobacteriaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Enterobacter</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Proteobacteria (Enterobacteriaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Enterobacter</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteroidetes** (Unclassified)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified (honeybee gut)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Proteobacteria&#x02020; (Orbaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Orbus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Firmicutes** (Streptococcaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Lactococcus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Proteobacteria&#x02021; (Acetobacteraceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Commensalibacter</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Proteobacteria** (Moraxellaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Acinetobacter</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Proteobacteria* (Acetobacteraceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Asaia</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Proteobacteria (Pseudomonadaceae)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified (ground beetle gut)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>The 10 most abundant bacterial phylotypes (by percent of total sequences) across all <italic>H. erato</italic> samples, with phylum (or class for Proteobacteria) and family-level classification. The number of specimens sequenced per sample type is indicated in parentheses. Mean percent relative abundances are shown for each life stage and adult group. The genus-level taxonomic identification of the best match for each phylotype, using the RDP SeqMatch tool, is shown along with its percent sequence identity. If the best match is unclassified, the habitat from which it was sequenced is given.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Asterisks indicate significantly different relative abundances across life stages (Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;*0.01, **0.001). The &#x02020; symbols indicate significantly different relative abundances across adult groups (Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;&#x02020;0.01, &#x02021;0.001).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Factors structuring adult-associated microbiota</title><p>Bacterial phylotype richness did not differ between wild, captive wild-caught (parental), and reared mature adult butterflies (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.24), although each group hosted bacterial communities distinct in composition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086995-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.001; all pairwise comparisons significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). Despite compositional differences, all adults clustered together to the exclusion of reared larvae (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s004">Fig. S4</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0086995-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086995.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Bacterial community variation associated with captivity and rearing.</title><p>Constrained principal coordinates analysis showing differences in community composition between adults sampled directly from the wild, wild-caught females kept in an insectary (&#x0201c;Parental&#x0201d;), and their reared adult offspring (&#x0201c;Mature adults&#x0201d;). CAP1 and CAP2 are the canonical axes in principal coordinate space that best discriminate among adult groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0086995.g002"/></fig><p>Four of the six dominant adult-associated bacterial families differed in relative abundance between the three groups we analyzed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s005">Fig. S5</xref>, Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05). Specifically, an increase in Streptococcaceae and reduction in an unclassified Gammaproteobacterial family were associated with captivity, whereas an increase in Enterobacteriaceae and reduction in Acetobacteraceae were associated with rearing. Among all adult butterflies, sex did not have an effect on community composition (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.80), and there was no interaction between sex and captivity/rearing status (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.33). Among the butterfly individuals with known relatedness (i.e., captive females and their mature adult offspring), variation between families was not greater than variation within families (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.78).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Overall structure of the Heliconius erato microbiota</title><p>
<italic>Heliconius erato</italic> larvae and adult butterflies host relatively simple bacterial communities, in agreement with previous reports of low diversity in other lepidopterans <xref rid="pone.0086995-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Broderick2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Zaspel1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref> and other insect orders <xref rid="pone.0086995-Colman1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Jones1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> relative to vertebrate-associated and free-living microbiota. The uneven structure of these communities is illustrated by the observation that the 10 most abundant phylotypes contributed more than 65% of the sequences from all <italic>H. erato</italic> samples. The majority of these dominant phylotypes were highly similar to sequences from genera known to colonize the gut of lepidopterans and other insects. The phylotype with the highest abundance across all <italic>H. erato</italic> samples matched most closely to isolates in the genus <italic>Enterococcus</italic>. Enterococci are commonly present in the intestinal tract of lepidopteran larvae <xref rid="pone.0086995-Broderick1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Broderick2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Brinkmann1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> and other insects <xref rid="pone.0086995-Martin1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, but are also found free-living in a variety of environmental habitats <xref rid="pone.0086995-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Evidence from other lepidopterans that enterococci in the larval gut can persist through metamorphosis <xref rid="pone.0086995-Bucher1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> is supported by our finding that <italic>Enterococcus</italic> is prevalent in all stages of <italic>H. erato</italic>.</p><p>A phylotype matching with 100% sequence identity to an <italic>Orbus</italic> clone in the Orbaceae was also abundant. Although the natural history of this family is not well known, one member has been isolated from a butterfly gut <xref rid="pone.0086995-Kim1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, and two others are associated with the gut of honeybees <xref rid="pone.0086995-Kwong1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Engel2" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Another phylotype classified as <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> was variably present across life stages, but at highest relative abundance in the larvae. <italic>Acinetobacter</italic> sequences have been reported from the larval midgut of a number of insect species including cabbage white butterflies <xref rid="pone.0086995-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> and saturniid moths <xref rid="pone.0086995-PintoToms1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, although their possible role in host herbivory is not well understood.</p><p>Phylotypes belonging to the bacterial family Acetobacteraceae were overrepresented in mature adults relative to earlier stages (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). Bacteria in this family are commonly associated with the intestinal tract of insects with sugar-rich diets, such as adult mosquitoes, bees, fruit flies, and sugarcane mealybugs <xref rid="pone.0086995-Crotti1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. We discovered two dominant Acetobacteraceae phylotypes in <italic>H. erato</italic>, one of which matches to <italic>Asaia sp.</italic>, which in other insects can form biofilms on the midgut epithelium and colonize egg surfaces and reproductive structures <xref rid="pone.0086995-Crotti2" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. As members of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> gut flora, acetic acid bacteria have been shown to prevent colonization by pathogens <xref rid="pone.0086995-Ryu1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, affect development and insulin signaling <xref rid="pone.0086995-Shin1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, and influence dietary carbohydrate utilization <xref rid="pone.0086995-RidleyE1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. Such bacteria are likely to be broadly associated with nectar- and fruit-feeding adult butterflies, in which they may have similar functions, and their role in the biology of <italic>Heliconius</italic> clearly warrants further investigation.</p><p>Another dominant phylotype in the adult stage, a member of the Bacteroidetes phylum, appears to be only distantly related to taxa reported from insects or other habitats. Interestingly, its closest match was to a clone from honeybee intestines <xref rid="pone.0086995-Babendreier1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. We do not know if this phylotype is uniquely associated with <italic>Heliconius</italic>, but given that a similar bacterium has been found in honeybees, which also feed on pollen, it is possible that this taxon is involved in <italic>Heliconius</italic> pollen feeding. For example, certain honeybee gut bacteria can produce enzymes that degrade pectin, a major structural component of pollen walls <xref rid="pone.0086995-Engel3" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. In <italic>Heliconius</italic>, which digest pollen grains attached to the proboscis using exuded saliva <xref rid="pone.0086995-Eberhard1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, symbionts with similar functions could reside in the salivary gland.</p><p>Because we sampled the entire internal portion of the insect, the exact location of these taxa within the host is unknown. Bacteria could reside in other structures besides the gut, such as reproductive organs and the salivary gland. However, the observation that frass samples were not different in composition from the whole larvae that produced them indicates that, for the larval stage at least, we have primarily sequenced gut bacteria. Likewise, previous studies have found that communities from whole homogenized insects can closely resemble those sampled from the gut alone <xref rid="pone.0086995-Sudakaran1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Sabree1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Effects of captivity and rearing on adult butterfly microbiota</title><p>Studies of microbial symbionts in Lepidoptera and other insects commonly use hosts reared in the laboratory where they are often maintained for multiple generations on artificial diets. We found that <italic>H. erato</italic> butterflies sampled directly from the wild were different in bacterial community composition from individuals from the same population housed in an insectary for 2&#x02013;4 weeks. Although the reasons for this microbial community shift remain unknown, altered adult diet&#x02013;specifically, access to artificial sucrose/pollen solution, and the absence of certain flowers normally visited by <italic>H. erato</italic> in the wild&#x02013;could underlie this difference, as could altered exposure to microbial inocula from their environment.</p><p>Reared four-day-old adult offspring were also different in composition from their wild-caught mothers, despite being maintained under identical conditions in the insectary. Although the average age of the wild-caught group is unknown, a difference in adult age could be partly responsible for these differences. As the wild-caught mothers spent all of the larval stage and some period of the adult stage in the wild prior to capture, there could be additional effects of diet and exposure to microbial inocula in both stages.</p><p>Generally, these results support previous findings of captive-wild differences in insect-associated microbial communities <xref rid="pone.0086995-Xiang1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0086995-Chandler1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and they suggest that caution should be taken when inferring evolutionary history or ecological function from microbiota associated with captive insects without an explicit comparison to wild populations. Altered bacterial community composition in captive individuals may also affect host nutrition, detoxification, and defense from natural enemies, as these traits can be mediated by microbial symbionts. The use of captive experimental subjects may consequently render studies of these phenomena less relevant to natural conditions. Although not tested here, these changes in the microbiota could partly account for the observations that reared <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies exhibit lower success in courtship and pollen collection compared with wild-caught individuals <xref rid="pone.0086995-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Community dynamics across metamorphosis</title><p>Bacterial diversity dropped by approximately 50% from the larval to the pupal stage, remained low in the newly emerged adults, and redoubled in the mature adults after feeding. Likewise, bacterial communities changed in composition from the larval to the pupal stage, remained similar in the newly emerged adults, and changed again in the mature adults. Thus, butterfly-associated bacterial communities appear to both simplify and reorganize over metamorphosis, a pattern that can be explained by multiple possible mechanisms. The reduction in richness during metamorphosis could be due to larval voiding of the gut prior to pupation <xref rid="pone.0086995-Nijhout1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref> and/or secretion of antibacterial proteins into the pupal gut lumen <xref rid="pone.0086995-Russell3" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>, both of which could selectively eliminate or reduce the abundance of gut-associated bacteria. Degeneration of the larval gut and its contents, in tandem with the development of a morphologically distinct adult gut <xref rid="pone.0086995-Judy1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0086995-Lowe1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref> and new structures such as the adult salivary gland and reproductive organs, could also facilitate the successional patterns observed here. After adult emergence, feeding by the host might stimulate the growth of bacteria persisting through the pupal stage, or add new taxa sourced from the diet, restoring community richness&#x02013;though not composition&#x02013;to pre-metamorphosis levels.</p><p>Differences in diet presumably drive the remarkable difference in bacterial community composition between <italic>H. erato</italic> larvae and adults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0086995-g001">Figs. 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0086995.s004">S4</xref>). Diet could directly impact life-stage-specific microbiota as an inoculum, as a resource supporting the differential growth of resident bacteria, and as a source of chemical compounds with selective antimicrobial activity. Diet may also directly affect the environmental conditions within the host&#x02013;for example, by inducing gut pH changes <xref rid="pone.0086995-Schultz1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Appel1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. Additionally, diet could indirectly impact the microbiota through the morphological and biochemical adaptations hosts have evolved to utilize different resources in different life stages (here, foliage versus nectar and pollen).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Impact of holometaboly on insect microbiota</title><p>The spectacular success of the Holometabola, of which the Lepidoptera are one of the most diverse groups <xref rid="pone.0086995-Kristensen1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, has been attributed to the differentiation in form and function between larvae and adults <xref rid="pone.0086995-Hennig1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. This divergence enables specialization on different diets in the larval and adult stages and reduces competition between immature and mature conspecifics for resources <xref rid="pone.0086995-Whiting1" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0086995-Grimaldi1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>. We propose that the evolutionary innovation of holometaboly also created distinct niches for colonization by distinct microbial symbionts. Over the holometabolous host life cycle, variation in diet and internal physicochemical conditions could support communities functionally specialized for a particular life stage. It remains to be determined whether holometabolous species&#x02013;especially those whose adults feed, and on diets distinct from the larvae&#x02013;are thus associated with more diverse microbial symbiont communities than other insects.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We have identified a relatively simple bacterial community associated with <italic>H. erato</italic> that differs in composition between larvae and adults. This difference in taxonomic membership may reflect divergent functional roles in life-stage-specific resource use. These results will be valuable in designing genomic studies and experimental manipulations to test how <italic>Heliconius</italic>-associated bacteria may be involved in their host's distinctive feeding biology. Additionally, the overall compositional similarity between frass and whole larvae, as well as the finding that community differences among larvae are maintained in their frass, indicate that frass could be used in the future as a way to sample the larval gut microbiota nondestructively. As with temporal surveys of the human gut <xref rid="pone.0086995-Costello1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, this would allow an analysis of gut communities from the same individual over larval development and into the adult stage.</p><p>Furthermore, we found that both captivity and rearing are associated with a compositional change in the microbiota from wild <italic>H. erato</italic> individuals of the same population. This change could be partly responsible for observed differences in performance between wild-caught and captive butterflies, and has implications not only for future studies of butterfly symbionts, but also for other kinds of studies on captive butterflies where microbial differences may influence experimental results.</p><p>We have demonstrated that the internal bacterial community of <italic>H. erato</italic> simplifies and reorganizes across host development. Presumably, different life stages represent habitats that selectively favor the growth of certain bacterial taxa. This ability of the microbiota to undergo a structural &#x0201c;metamorphosis,&#x0201d; in tandem with its host, might entail an overall greater diversity in microbial community form and function within a given holometabolous species relative to other insect groups.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0086995.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Changes in bacterial community diversity across life stages.</bold> Boxplot of Shannon Diversity Index values from <italic>H. erato</italic> larvae, pupae, newly emerged adults, and mature adults, standardized at 500 sequences per sample.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0086995.s001.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0086995.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Clustering patterns of larval and frass communities.</bold> Principal coordinates analysis of bacterial communities in whole larvae and their frass, colored by individual, showing clustering by individual rather than sample type.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0086995.s002.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0086995.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Dynamics of bacterial families across life stages.</bold> Relative abundances of the six dominant bacterial families among <italic>H. erato</italic> life stages, defined as those with a median abundance over 2% within any life stage. Points represent individual samples and are laterally jittered to display within-stage variability more clearly. Bars show median relative abundances. Asterisks indicate bacterial families whose relative abundances differed significantly across life stages.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0086995.s003.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0086995.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Clustering pattern of bacterial communities from multiple adult groups and reared larvae.</bold> Constrained principal coordinates analysis of bacterial community composition in <italic>H. erato</italic> larvae and all adult groups. CAP1 and CAP2 are the axes in principal coordinate space that best discriminate among sample types.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0086995.s004.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0086995.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Dynamics of bacterial families across wild, captive, and reared adults.</bold> Relative abundances of the six dominant bacterial families among <italic>H. erato</italic> adult groups, defined as those with a median abundance over 2% within any group. Points represent individual samples and are laterally jittered to display within-group variability more clearly. Bars show median relative abundances. Asterisks indicate bacterial families whose relative abundances differed significantly across groups.</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0086995.s005.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank the Panamanian Environmental Authority (ANAM) for permission to collect butterflies (permit #SE/A-92-11). We also acknowledge Adriana Tapia and Moises Abanto for advice and assistance with butterfly collection and rearing, and Jessica Henley for help with molecular work. Ed Connor, Deane Bowers, and two anonymous reviewers provided valuable comments on earlier drafts of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0086995-Boggs1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boggs CL, Watt WB, Ehrlich PR (2003) Butterflies: ecology and evolution taking flight. The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Douglas1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Douglas AE (2009) The microbial dimension in insect nutritional ecology. Funct. Ecol. <volume>23</volume>: , 38&#x02013;47.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Brownlie1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brownlie JC, Johnson KN (2009) Symbiont-mediated protection in insect hosts. Trends Microbiol. <volume>17</volume>: , 348&#x02013;354.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Feldhaar1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Feldhaar H (2011) Bacterial symbionts as mediators of ecologically important traits of insect hosts. Ecol. Entomol. <volume>36</volume>: , 533&#x02013;543.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Engel1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Engel P, Moran NA (2013) The gut microbiota of insects - diversity in structure and function. FEMS Microbiol. Rev. (doi:10.1111/1574-6976.12025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Steinhaus1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Steinhaus EA (1941) A study of the bacteria associated with thirty species of insects. J. Bacteriol. <volume>42</volume>: , 757&#x02013;790.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Kim1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kim JY, Lee J, Shin N-R, Yun J-H, Whon T-W, <etal>et al</etal>. (2013) <italic>Orbus sasakiae</italic> sp. nov., a bacterium isolated from the gut of the butterfly <italic>Sasakia charonda</italic>, and emended description of the genus <italic>Orbus</italic> Int. J. Syst. Evol. Micr. <volume>63</volume>: , 1766&#x02013;1770.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Tagami1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Tagami Y, Miura K (2004) Distribution and prevalence of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in Japanese populations of Lepidoptera. Insect Mol. Biol. <volume>13</volume>: , 359&#x02013;364.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Narita1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Narita S, Nomura M, Kato Y, Fukatsu T (2006) Genetic structure of sibling butterfly species affected by <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection sweep: evolutionary and biogeographical implications. Mol. Ecol. <volume>15</volume>: , 1095&#x02013;1108.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Russell1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russell JA, Funaro CF, Giraldo YM, Goldman-Huertas B, Suh D, <etal>et al</etal>. (2012) A veritable menagerie of heritable bacteria from ants, butterflies, and beyond: broad molecular surveys and a systematic review. PLoS ONE <volume>7</volume>: , e51027.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-KingsleyV1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kingsley V V. (1972) Persistence of Intestinal Bacteria in the Developmental Stages of the Monarch Butterfly (<italic>Danaus plexippus</italic>). J. Invertebr. Pathol. <volume>20</volume>: , 51&#x02013;58.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Pace1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pace NR (1997) A molecular view of microbial diversity and the biosphere. Science <volume>276</volume>: , 734&#x02013;740.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Broderick1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Broderick NA, Robinson CJ, McMahon MD, Holt J, Handelsman J, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) Contributions of gut bacteria to <italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic>-induced mortality vary across a range of Lepidoptera. BMC Biol. <volume>7</volume>: , 11.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Robinson1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Robinson CJ, Schloss P, Ramos Y, Raffa K, Handelsman J (2010) Robustness of the bacterial community in the cabbage white butterfly larval midgut. Microb. Ecol. <volume>59</volume>: , 199&#x02013;211.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Lauzon1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lauzon C, McCombs S, Potter S, Peabody N (2009) Establishment and vertical passage of <italic>Enterobacter (Pantoea) agglomerans</italic> and <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> through all life stages of the mediterranean fruit fly (Diptera: Tephritidae). Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am. <volume>102</volume>: , 85&#x02013;95.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Martinson1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martinson VG, Moy J, Moran NA (2012) Establishment of characteristic gut bacteria during development of the honeybee worker. Appl. Environ. Microb. <volume>78</volume>: , 2830&#x02013;2840.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Vasanthakumar1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Vasanthakumar A, Handelsman J, Schloss PD, Bauer LS, Raffa KF (2008) Gut microbiota of an invasive subcortical beetle, <italic>Agrilus planipennis</italic> Fairmaire, across various life stages. Environ. Entomol. <volume>37</volume>: , 1344&#x02013;1353.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Wong1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wong CNA, Ng P, Douglas AE (2011) Low-diversity bacterial community in the gut of the fruitfly <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> Environ. Microbiol. <volume>13</volume>: , 1889&#x02013;1900.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Brucker1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brucker RM, Bordenstein SR (2012) The roles of host evolutionary relationships (genus: <italic>Nasonia</italic>) and development in structuring microbial communities. Evolution <volume>66</volume>: , 349&#x02013;362.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-AriasCordero1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Arias-Cordero E, Ping L, Reichwald K, Delb H, Platzer M, <etal>et al</etal>. (2012) Comparative evaluation of the gut microbiota associated with the below- and above-ground life stages (larvae and beetles) of the forest cockchafer, <italic>Melolontha hippocastani</italic> PLoS ONE <volume>7</volume>: , e51557.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Colman1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Colman DR, Toolson EC, Takacs-Vesbach CD (2012) Do diet and taxonomy influence insect gut bacterial communities? Mol. Ecol. <volume>21</volume>: , 5124&#x02013;5137.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Muegge1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Muegge BD, Kuczynski J, Knights D, Clemente JC, Gonz&#x000e1;lez A, <etal>et al</etal>. (2011) Diet drives convergence in gut microbiome functions across mammalian phylogeny and within humans. Science <volume>332</volume>: , 970&#x02013;974.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Russell2"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russell JA, Moreau CS, Goldman-Huertas B, Fujiwara M, Lohman DJ, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) Bacterial gut symbionts are tightly linked with the evolution of herbivory in ants. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA <volume>106</volume>: , 21236&#x02013;21241.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-EnglerChaouat1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Engler-Chaouat HS, Gilbert LE (2007) De novo synthesis vs. sequestration: negatively correlated metabolic traits and the evolution of host plant specialization in cyanogenic butterflies. J. Chem. Ecol. <volume>33</volume>: , 25&#x02013;42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Gilbert1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Gilbert LE (1972) Pollen feeding and reproductive biology of <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA <volume>69</volume>: , 1403&#x02013;1407.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Brown1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brown KS (1981) The biology of <italic>Heliconius</italic> and related genera. Annu. Rev. Entomol. <volume>26</volume>: , 427&#x02013;456.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-The1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">The Heliconius Genome Consortium (2012) Butterfly genome reveals promiscuous exchange of mimicry adaptations among species. Nature <volume>487</volume>: , 94&#x02013;98.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Werren1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Werren JH, Windsor D, Guo L (1995) Distribution of <italic>Wolbachia</italic> among neotropical arthropods. Proc. R. Soc. B <volume>262</volume>: , 197&#x02013;204.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Muoz1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Mu&#x000f1;oz AG, Baxter SW, Linares M, Jiggins CD (2011) Deep mitochondrial divergence within a <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterfly species is not explained by cryptic speciation or endosymbiotic bacteria. BMC Evol. Biol. <volume>11</volume>: , 358.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Xiang1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Xiang H, Wei G-F, Jia S, Miao X-X, Zhou Z, <etal>et al</etal>. (2006) Microbial communities in the larval midgut of laboratory and field populations of cotton bollworm (<italic>Helicoverpa armigera</italic>). Can. J. Microbiol. <volume>52</volume>: , 1085&#x02013;1092.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Belda1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Belda E, Pedrola L, Peret&#x000f3; J, Mart&#x000ed;nez-Blanch JF, Montagud A, <etal>et al</etal>. (2011) Microbial diversity in the midguts of field and lab-reared populations of the European corn borer <italic>Ostrinia nubilalis</italic> PLoS ONE <volume>6</volume>: , e21751.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Lehman1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lehman RM, Lundgren JG, Petzke LM (2009) Bacterial communities associated with the digestive tract of the predatory ground beetle, <italic>Poecilus chalcites</italic>, and their modification by laboratory rearing and antibiotic treatment. Microb. Ecol. <volume>57</volume>: , 349&#x02013;358.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Chandler1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Chandler JA, Lang JM, Bhatnagar S, Eisen JA, Kopp A (2011) Bacterial communities of diverse <italic>Drosophila</italic> species: ecological context of a host&#x02013;microbe model system. PLoS Genet. <volume>7</volume>: , e1002272.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Smiley1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Smiley J (1978) Plant chemistry and the evolution of host specificity: new evidence from <italic>Heliconius</italic> and <italic>Passiflora</italic> Science <volume>201</volume>: , 745&#x02013;747.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Walters1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Walters JR, Stafford C, Hardcastle TJ, Jiggins CD (2012) Evaluating female remating rates in light of spermatophore degradation in <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies: pupal-mating monandry versus adult-mating polyandry. Ecol. Entomol. <volume>37</volume>: , 257&#x02013;268.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Fierer1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fierer N, Hamady M, Lauber CL, Knight R (2008) The influence of sex, handedness, and washing on the diversity of hand surface bacteria. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA <volume>105</volume>: , 17994&#x02013;17999.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Caporaso1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Caporaso JG, Lauber CL, Walters WA, Berg-Lyons D, Huntley J, <etal>et al</etal>. (2012) Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms. ISME J. <volume>6</volume>: , 1621&#x02013;1624.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Caporaso2"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Caporaso JG, Kuczynski J, Stombaugh J, Bittinger K, Bushman FD, <etal>et al</etal>. (2010) QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data. Nat. Methods <volume>7</volume>: , 335&#x02013;336.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Edgar1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Edgar RC (2010) Search and clustering orders of magnitude faster than BLAST. Bioinformatics <volume>26</volume>: , 2460&#x02013;2461.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-McDonald1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">McDonald D, Price MN, Goodrich J, Nawrocki EP, DeSantis TZ, <etal>et al</etal>. (2012) An improved Greengenes taxonomy with explicit ranks for ecological and evolutionary analyses of bacteria and archaea. ISME J. <volume>6</volume>: , 610&#x02013;618.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Wang1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Wang Q, Garrity GM, Tiedje JM, Cole JR (2007) Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy. Appl. Environ. Microb. <volume>73</volume>: , 5261&#x02013;5267.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Cole1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Cole JR, Wang Q, Cardenas E, Fish J, Chai B, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) The Ribosomal Database Project: improved alignments and new tools for rRNA analysis. Nucleic Acids Research <volume>37</volume>: , D141&#x02013;D145.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Jones1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Jones RT, Sanchez LG, Fierer N (2013) A cross-taxon analysis of insect-associated bacterial diversity. PLoS ONE <volume>8</volume>: , e61218.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Kuczynski1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kuczynski J, Costello EK, Nemergut DR, Zaneveld J, Lauber CL, <etal>et al</etal>. (2010) Direct sequencing of the human microbiome readily reveals community differences. Genome Biology <volume>11</volume>: , 210.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-R1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team (2013) R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation Statistical Computing. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Oksanen1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oksanen J, Blanchet FG, Kindt R, Legendre P, Minchin PR, <etal>et al</etal>. (2013) vegan: Community Ecology Package. R package version 2.0-7. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan">http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan</ext-link>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Clarke1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clarke KR, Gorley RN (2006) PRIMER v6. PRIMER-E, Plymouth, UK.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Anderson1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anderson MJ, Willis TJ (2003) Canonical analysis of principal coordinates: a useful method of constrained ordination for ecology. Ecology <volume>84</volume>: , 511&#x02013;525.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Anderson2"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Anderson MJ (2001) A new method for non-parametric multivariate analysis of variance. Austral Ecology <volume>26</volume>: , 32&#x02013;46.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Broderick2"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Broderick NA, Raffa KF, Goodman RM, Handelsman J (2004) Census of the bacterial community of the gypsy moth larval midgut by using culturing and culture-independent methods. Appl. Environ. Microb. <volume>70</volume>: , 293&#x02013;300.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Zaspel1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Zaspel JM, Hoy MA (2008) Microbial diversity associated with the fruit-piercing and blood-feeding moth <italic>Calyptra thalictri</italic> (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae). Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am. <volume>101</volume>: , 1050&#x02013;1055.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Brinkmann1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Brinkmann N, Martens R, Tebbe CC (2008) Origin and diversity of metabolically active gut bacteria from laboratory-bred larvae of <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> (Sphingidae, Lepidoptera, Insecta). Appl. Environ. Microb. <volume>74</volume>: , 7189&#x02013;7196.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Martin1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Martin JD, Mundt JO (1972) Enterococci in insects. Appl. Microbiol. <volume>24</volume>: , 575&#x02013;580.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Fisher1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Fisher K, Phillips C (2009) The ecology, epidemiology and virulence of <italic>Enterococcus</italic> Microbiology <volume>155</volume>: , 1749&#x02013;1757.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Bucher1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Bucher GE (1963) Survival of populations of <italic>Streptococcus faecalis</italic> Andrewes and Horder in the gut of <italic>Galleria mellonella</italic> (Linnaeus) during metamorphosis, and transmission of the bacteria to the filial generation of the host. J. Insect Pathol. <volume>5</volume>: , 336&#x02013;343.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Kwong1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kwong WK, Moran NA (2013) Cultivation and characterization of the gut symbionts of honey bees and bumble bees: description of <italic>Snodgrassella alvi</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a member of the family Neisseriaceae of the Betaproteobacteria, and <italic>Gilliamella apicola</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a member of Orbaceae fam. nov., Orbales ord. nov., a sister taxon to the order &#x02018;Enterobacteriales&#x02019; of the Gammaproteobacteria. Int. J. Syst. Evol. Micr. <volume>63</volume>: , 2008&#x02013;2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Engel2"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Engel P, Kwong WK, Moran NA (2013) <italic>Frischella perrara</italic> gen. nov., sp. nov., a gammaproteobacterium isolated from the gut of the honey bee, <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>. Int. J. Syst. Evol. Micr. (doi:10.1099/ijs.0.049569-0).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-PintoToms1"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Pinto-Tom&#x000e1;s AA, Sittenfeld A, Uribe-Lorio L, Chavarria F, Mora M, <etal>et al</etal>. (2011) Comparison of midgut bacterial diversity in tropical caterpillars (Lepidoptera: Saturniidae) fed on different diets. Environ. Entomol. <volume>40</volume>: , 1111&#x02013;1122.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Crotti1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Crotti E, Rizzi A, Chouaia B, Ricci I, Favia G, <etal>et al</etal>. (2010) Acetic acid bacteria, newly emerging symbionts of insects. Appl. Environ. Microb. <volume>76</volume>: , 6963&#x02013;6970.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Crotti2"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Crotti E, Damiani C, Pajoro M, Gonella E, Rizzi A, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) <italic>Asaia</italic>, a versatile acetic acid bacterial symbiont, capable of cross-colonizing insects of phylogenetically distant genera and orders. Environ. Microbiol. <volume>11</volume>: , 3252&#x02013;3264.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Ryu1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ryu J, Kim S-H, Lee H-Y, Bai J-Y, Nam Y-D, <etal>et al</etal>. (2008) Innate immune homeostasis by the homeobox gene <italic>caudal</italic> and commensal-gut mutualism in <italic>Drosophila</italic> Science <volume>319</volume>: , 777&#x02013;782.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Shin1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Shin SC, Kim S-H, You H, Kim B, Kim AC, <etal>et al</etal>. (2011) <italic>Drosophila</italic> microbiome modulates host developmental and metabolic homeostasis via insulin signaling. Science <volume>334</volume>: , 670&#x02013;674.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-RidleyE1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Ridley E V, Wong AC-N, Westmiller S, Douglas AE (2012) Impact of the resident microbiota on the nutritional phenotype of <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> PLoS ONE <volume>7</volume>: , e36765.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Babendreier1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Babendreier D, Joller D, Romeis J, Bigler F, Widmer F (2007) Bacterial community structures in honeybee intestines and their response to two insecticidal proteins. FEMS Microbiol. Ecol. <volume>59</volume>: , 600&#x02013;610.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Engel3"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Engel P, Martinson VG, Moran NA (2012) Functional diversity within the simple gut microbiota of the honey bee. P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, <volume>109</volume>: , 11002&#x02013;11007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Eberhard1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Eberhard SH, Hikl AL, Boggs CL, Krenn HW (2009) Saliva or regurgitated nectar? What <italic>Heliconius</italic> butterflies (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae) use for pollen feeding. Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am. <volume>102</volume>: , 1105&#x02013;1108.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Sudakaran1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sudakaran S, Salem H, Kost C, Kaltenpoth M (2012) Geographical and ecological stability of the symbiotic mid-gut microbiota in European firebugs, <italic>Pyrrhocoris apterus</italic> (Hemiptera, Pyrrhocoridae). Mol. Ecol. <volume>21</volume>: , 6134&#x02013;6151.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Sabree1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Sabree ZL, Hansen AK, Moran NA (2012) Independent studies using deep sequencing resolve the same set of core bacterial species dominating gut communities of honey bees. PLoS ONE <volume>7</volume>: , e41250.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Nijhout1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Nijhout HF, Williams CM (1974) Control of moulting and metamorphosis in the tobacco hornworm, <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> (L.): growth of the last-instar larva and the decision to pupate. J. Exp. Biol. <volume>61</volume>: , 481&#x02013;491.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Russell3"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Russell V, Dunn PE (1996) Antibacterial proteins in the midgut of <italic>Manduca sexta</italic> during metamorphosis. J. Insect Physiol. <volume>42</volume>: , 65&#x02013;71.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Judy1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Judy KJ, Gilbert LI (1969) Morphology of the alimentary canal during the metamorphosis of <italic>Hyalophora cecropia</italic> (Lepidoptera: Saturniidae). Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am. <volume>62</volume>: , 1438&#x02013;1446.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Hakim1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Hakim RS, Baldwin K, Smagghe G (2010) Regulation of midgut growth, development, and metamorphosis. Annu. Rev. Entomol. <volume>55</volume>: , 593&#x02013;608.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Lowe1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Lowe T, Garwood RJ, Simonsen TJ, Bradley RS, Withers PJ (2013) Metamorphosis revealed: time-lapse three-dimensional imaging inside a living chrysalis. J. R. Soc. Interface <volume>10</volume> , 20130304.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Schultz1"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Schultz JC, Lechowicz MJ (1986) Hostplant, larval age, and feeding behavior influence midgut pH in the gypsy moth (<italic>Lymantria dispar</italic>). Oecologia <volume>71</volume>: , 133&#x02013;137.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Appel1"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Appel HM, Maines LW (1995) The influence of host plant on gut conditions of gypsy moth (Lymantria dispar) caterpillars. J. Insect Physiol. <volume>41</volume>: , 241&#x02013;246.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Kristensen1"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Kristensen NP (1999) Phylogeny of endopterygote insects, the most successful lineage of living organisms. Eur. J. Entomol. <volume>96</volume>: , 237&#x02013;253.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Hennig1"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hennig W (1981) Insect phylogeny John Wiley &#x00026; Sons.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Whiting1"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Whiting MF (2003) Phylogeny of the holometabolous insects: the most successful group of terrestrial organisms. In: Assembling the Tree of Life (eds Cracraft J, Donoghue MJ), pp. 345&#x02013;361. Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Grimaldi1"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Grimaldi D, Engel MS (2005) Evolution of the Insects Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0086995-Costello1"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Costello EK, Lauber CL, Hamady M, Fierer N, Gordon JI, <etal>et al</etal>. (2009) Bacterial community variation in human body habitats across space and time. Science <volume>326</volume>: , 1694&#x02013;1697.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>