<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.4.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art540.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.4.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_IMR243 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Integr Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Integr Med Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Integrative Medicine Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2213-4220</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-4239</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5478250</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2213-4220(16)30175-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imr.2017.03.001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants used for snakebite in India: a brief overview</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Upasani</surname><given-names>Sughosh V.</given-names></name><email>upasanisughosh@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beldar</surname><given-names>Vishal G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tatiya</surname><given-names>Anil U.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Upasani</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Surana</surname><given-names>Sanjay J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>Divyata S.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>R.C. Patel Institute of Pharmacy, Shirpur, India</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of Pharmacognosy, R.C. Patel Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and Research, Shirpur, India</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>H.R. Patel Institute of Pharmacy, Shirpur, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label><italic>Corresponding author.</italic> R.C. Patel Institute of Pharmacy, Karwand Naka, Shirpur, Dhule, Maharashtra 425405, India.R.C. Patel Institute of PharmacyShirpurIndia <email>upasanisughosh@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 Korea Institute of Oriental Medicine. Published by Elsevier.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0005"><p>The result of human interface and assortment of the most desirable, influential, and successful plant species found in the immediate environment at a precise circumstance is attributable to indigenous knowledge of plant species. India has a rich variety of medicinal plants growing under different geographical and ecological conditions; 1500 out of 15,000 privileged plant species have been reported to have medicinal uses. Snakebite is a severe medical, social, and economic problem in many parts of the world, chiefly in tropical and subtropical nations where majority of the world&#x02019;s dangerous snakes are found and where access to treatment is limited. In India, a range of medicinal plants are used as antidotes for snakebites, used either singly or in combination with other agents. The present study makes an effort to assemble information on medicinal plants that are grown and used for snakebite treatment in India. From a range of literature sources, data have been compiled with emphasis on the plants, family, parts used, etc., depending on the availability of information. This paper enumerates 523 plant species belonging to 122 families that act as antidotes against snakebites. We believe this study of herbal antidotes against snake venom is of substantial significance to society.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>ethanobotany</kwd><kwd>ethnomedicine</kwd><kwd>India</kwd><kwd>medicinal plants</kwd><kwd>snakebite</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Historically, humans have depended on nature to provide for their fundamental needs, namely food, clothing, medicines, and natural healing remedies. This reliance led the aboriginal people living in synchronization with nature to develop a system of knowledge about plants, which play several important functions in human life.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> The result of human interface and assortment of the most desirable, influential, and successful plant species found in the immediate environment during specific events is attributable to the indigenous knowledge of plant species.<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> The World Health Organization estimates that about 80% of the world&#x02019;s population in developing countries depends on plants for the management of a variety of diseases, because of the lack of modern healthcare services.<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Ethnobotany</title><p>Ethnobotany is the field of science that deals with the associations between plants and humans. An ethnobotanical survey encompasses discussion with local natives, use of accessible data in the literature, and the folklore of each area.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Documentation of indigenous medicinal knowledge of plant species has contributed to a number of modern drug formulations for basic healthcare.<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Medicinal plants are an important source of bioactive compounds that assist directly in the handling of ophidian envenomation, or ultimately, as supplements to conventional serum therapy. Thus, plant extracts are a valuable substitute, used either alone or in combination with other agents, when antisera are not available in emergency situations. Exploration on the traditional use of medicinal plants has attained significant consideration within the scientific community in recent years; about 25% of the drugs prescribed worldwide come from plants.<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The conventional system of medicine could not be the entire solution for miscellaneous human pathological conditions,<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> whereas drug discovery through ethnobotanical study has been found to be one of the most reliable approach and even today this area holds promise for its considerable potential.<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Since ancient times, plants have been used for treatment of various diseases. The traditional systems of medicine, together with folklore systems, continue to serve a large portion of inhabitants, particularly in rural and tribal areas despite the advent of modern medicine.</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><label>3</label><title>India</title><p>India has a rich variety of medicinal plants growing under different geographical and ecological conditions; 1500 species out of about 15,000 privileged plants species in India have been reported to have medicinal uses.<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> India is composed of 29 states and seven union territories comprising a total area of 3,287,263&#x000a0;km<sup>2</sup>. Indians speak a variety of languages, which include 23 regional languages (Assamese, Bengali, Bodo, Dogri, Gujrathi, Kannada, Kashiri, Kokborok, Konkani, Maithili, Malayalam, Manipuri, Marathi, Mizo, Nepali, Odia, Punjabi, Sanskrit, Santali, Sindhi, Tamil, Telugu, and Urdu). Moreover, there are many more local or tribal dialects spoken by Indians. India is home to different ethnic groups comprising 5.4 crores of indigenous peoples living in various territories, having diverse cultures, religious rites, and food traditions that separate them from each other. These people also have a healthy awareness of traditional medicine,<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> especially herbal and folk medicine for treatment in snakebites. Traditional herbalists operate closer to the people, taking advantage of the biodiversity of plant species in such areas to cure various diseases and ailments.<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>4</label><title>Snake and snake venoms</title><p>Snakes have been used to symbolize war and peace, love and hate, God and devil, as well as life and death; many times they have been used as contradictory symbols within the same civilization.<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Snakebites represent a severe medical, social, and economic challenge in many parts of the world, chiefly in tropical and subtropical nations. Majority of the world&#x02019;s dangerous snakes are found in developing countries, where access to treatment is limited. It is estimated that about 2 million people are bitten annually, resulting in up to 125,000 deaths, and 400,000 permanent disabilities from severe complications, which may lead to amputation.<xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Snake venoms are one of the most intense &#x0201c;mysterious&#x0201d; biological fluids within class Mammalia, having complex medical effects owing to the presence of complex mixtures of proteins and peptides and they contain at least 25 enzymes.<xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> There are many prospective effects in humans following envenoming by snakes, but just a few broad categories are of major clinical significance such as systemic myolysis flaccid paralysis, coagulopathy and hemorrhage, cardiotoxicity, renal damage and failure, and local tissue injury at the bite site. Sometimes, it causes secondary effects such as potential morbidity and mortality.<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>5</label><title>Snakebites treatment</title><p>Snakebites are commonly treated by parenteral administration of horse or sheep-derived polyclonal antivenoms aimed at neutralization of toxins. However, despite the widespread success of traditional therapy, it is still important to search for other different venom inhibitors, either synthetic or natural, that could complement or substitute for the action of the traditional antivenom. Even if in a variety of cases the effectiveness of some traditional courses of therapy is not particularly apparent, conventional herbal medicine is easily available in the countryside for snakebite treatment. Some of the methods used to treat snakebites include topical application of plant leaves&#x02013;juice&#x02013;paste, etc.; chewing of leaves and plant parts; and drinking plant extracts or decoctions. In India as well as in other parts of the world, medicinal plants are used as antidotes for snakebites, administered either singly or in combination with other antisnake venoms or supportive plants. Thus, in the management of snakebite, the study of herbal antidotes against snake venom is of considerable significance to society.<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>6</label><title>Procedure for review&#x02014;methodology</title><p>In this systematic review, we compile information on medicinal plants that are grown and utilized in various parts of India for treatment of snakebites. As this is a detailed &#x0201c;scrutiny,&#x0201d; we also carried out an appraisal of plants used in treatment of snakebite poisoning throughout India. This paper helps readers to find out more about these plants by including their local names from local inhabitants. The appropriate literature was reviewed such as technical studies published in journals, books, theses, and reports, and we searched for relevant information through various electronic databases (Science Direct, NISCAIR, MEDLINE, Scopus, Scirus and Google Scholer) using keywords such as &#x0201c;medicinal plants&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;snakebite&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;ethnobotany or ethnopharmacology or indigenous or Indian&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;survey&#x0201d;. It is not possible to incorporate all the information about use of medicinal plants for snakebite treatment; so we chose to focus on information that is easily accessible to researchers. In the past few decades; different tribal communities have tried to record traditional and tribal knowledge related to medicinal plants. However; in most cases; this information has yet to be made available to the modern world.</p><p>A list of medicinal plants was produced, showing biological source(s), Family, local name(s) part(s) used, method of preparation, and reference(s). In this review, the precision of botanical identification of plants are obtained from the original sources (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of medicinal plants used for treatment of snakebite in India.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0040">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Biological source</th><th align="left">Family</th><th align="left">Local names</th><th align="left">Part used</th><th align="left">Method of administration</th><th align="left">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Abrus precatorius</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Kundumani, Sonakaich, Takharichum, Gunj</td><td align="left">Seed, leaf, root</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;g of fresh leaves or roots with seeds are made into paste and consumed along with cold water or cow&#x02019;s milk. (Two times a day for 5&#x02013;7 d to cure any poisonous bite, as well as root powder applied topically.)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acalypa indica</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left">Kuppi (Indian acalypha), Kuppe gida, Muktajuri, Kuppimeni</td><td align="left">Leaf, Whole plant</td><td align="left">Leaf paste applied over the bitten part or paste smeared on spot of bite (3&#x02013;4 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acanthus ilicifolius</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left">Maranda,<break/>Maraneli,<break/>Kazhimulli</td><td align="left">Fruit</td><td align="left">For dressing snakebite crushed fruits are used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Achyranthes aspera</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Amaranthaceae</td><td align="left">Apamarg, Khoruch, Puth Kanda, Apang, Ola kanta, Kutri, Puthkanda, Adhajhara, Latjira, Chirchiti Kutri, Chirchita, Valiya kadaladi, Kempu Uttarani, Uttarane, Kakralata, Adhijhara, Nayuruvi</td><td align="left">Root, seeds, whole plant, leaf, stem</td><td align="left">The whole plant extract or root extract is given orally as well as the paste obtained from the root has been used (for 3 wk)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aconitum balfourii</italic> (Bruhl) Muk.</td><td align="left">Ranunculaceae</td><td align="left">Meetha</td><td align="left">Root, tuber</td><td align="left">Tuber paste used externally and internally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">81</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aconitum ferox</italic></td><td align="left">Ranunculaceae</td><td align="left">Bikh, Bish</td><td align="left">Tuberous roots</td><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr"><sup>82</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Acorus calamus</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Araceae</td><td align="left">Vekhand, Ghorbach, Bach, Bojo, Shyoiako, Vasamboo</td><td align="left">Rhizome</td><td align="left">Rhizomes are crushed to paste and given with warm water as well as applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">86</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Adiantum lunulatum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Adiantaceae</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">Rhizome</td><td align="left">Rhizome powder used for snake bite</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr"><sup>87</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Adiantum philippense</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Adiantaceae</td><td align="left">Kalijhant</td><td align="left">Rhizome</td><td align="left">Powder of rhizome is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0445" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>, <xref rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr">90</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Caladium bicolor</italic> Vent.</td><td align="left">Araceae</td><td align="left">Rudra chama</td><td align="left">Tuber</td><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr"><sup>88</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (Linn.) Correa</td><td align="left">Rutaceae</td><td align="left">Bel, Vilvam</td><td align="left">Fruit, leaves, root bark</td><td align="left">Decoction/extract (twice a day upto 5 d) of the leaves is given orally or root bark extract is administered internally for every 4&#x000a0;h up to 3 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aerva lanata</italic> (L.) Juss. ex Schult</td><td align="left">Amaranthaceae</td><td align="left">Kannu peelai, Poolapo</td><td align="left">Whole plant, rhizome, root</td><td align="left">Juice is prepared and taken orally (for 11 d)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>, <xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ageratum conyzoides</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Asteraceae</td><td align="left">Khoobi, Sahdevi, Kynbatblu myngai, Ajgandha, Sadevi Uchunti</td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">Paste of leaf with rhizome of <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>, <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Alangium salvifolium</italic> (Linn.f) Wang.</td><td align="left">Alangiaceae</td><td align="left">Ankol, Ankula, Alangi, Aankla</td><td align="left">Whole plant, root, leaf, stem bark,</td><td align="left">About 15&#x000a0;g of bark, ground with 10&#x02013;12 black peppers and mixed with 60&#x000a0;g animal fat, is given every 2&#x000a0;h to cure snakebite.<break/>Root bark decoction is given internally to treat.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Albizia lebbeck</italic> (Linn). Benth.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Siris, Kala Siris, Segta/Siris, Hombage, bhandi</td><td align="left">Leaves, bark, flower, whole plant, root</td><td align="left">Paste of bark is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Liliaceae</td><td align="left">Piyaz, Venkayam</td><td align="left">Skin bulb</td><td align="left">Paste taken from fresh skin bulb for external application (5 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Allium sativum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Liliaceae</td><td align="left">Rosun</td><td align="left">Bulbs</td><td align="left">Bulb is made into paste and given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Alstonea scholaris</italic> (Linn.) R.Br.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Saptparni, Chatni, Satina, Barap lei, Lawthong</td><td align="left">Leaf, bark</td><td align="left">Bark decoction given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Alstonia venenata</italic> R.Br.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Analivegham, Elaipalai, Analivegham</td><td align="left">Stem, bark root</td><td align="left">Tablets made from paste of stem bark are taken with cow&#x02019;s urine.<break/>Decoction also taken orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Alternanthera sessilis</italic> (Linn.) R. Brown ex DC</td><td align="left">Amaranthaceae</td><td align="left">KandiliJari</td><td align="left">Stem, leaf</td><td align="left">External application of stem and leaf paste is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Amaranthus spinosus</italic> Linn</td><td align="left">Amaranthaceae</td><td align="left">Kateli, Mullikeerai, Kateli Chaurai, Kanta-bhaji, Kateli-chaulai</td><td align="left">Roots, leaf, whole plant</td><td align="left">Paste of leaves is applied locally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Amaranthus viridis</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Amaranthaceae</td><td align="left">Khutora, Chaulai</td><td align="left">Leaf, stem</td><td align="left">Leaves/stem paste are applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ammannia baccifera</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Lythraceae</td><td align="left">Neerumulli</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">Whole plant powder mixed with hot cow&#x02019;s milk to drink.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Andrographis echioides</italic> Nees</td><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left">Nadnaur, Gusum puru, Gopuranthangi</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">Paste of whole plant is given orally with water. It is also applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Andrographis lineate Wallich</italic> ex</td><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left">Siriyanangai, Periyanangai, Malaiveempu</td><td align="left">Whole plant, leaves</td><td align="left">Paste of leaves is applied externally.<break/>About 30&#x000a0;g of whole plant paste is directly administered orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm f) Wall. Ex. Nees.</td><td align="left">Acantheceae</td><td align="left">Kalmegh, Bhumi neem, Neelaveppu, Nilavaembu, Chirianangai, Sirianangai, Periyanangai</td><td align="left">Leaf, leaves, whole plant</td><td align="left">A decoction of the leaves with the leaves of <italic>Andrographis alata</italic> is given.<break/>Decoction or extract is applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Argemone mexicana</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Papaveraceae</td><td align="left">Sialkatahi, Datturi, Pilikateli, Bharbhand, Brahmathandu</td><td align="left">Leaf, Seed, root</td><td align="left">Leaf/seed decoction given orally (7 d).<break/>Root paste is also used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Arisaema tortuosum</italic> (Wall.) Schott</td><td align="left">Araceae</td><td align="left">Haap roodakaro, Halida, Kotukand, Chambus, Chakrata</td><td align="left">Tuber, bulb</td><td align="left">Paste of the tuber in applied.<break/>Infusion of fresh bulb is taken orally thrice a day.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aristolochia bracteolate</italic> Lamk.</td><td align="left">Aristolochiaceae</td><td align="left">Kalipad, Aduthinnapalai</td><td align="left">Leaves, root</td><td align="left">Leaves paste applied externally as well as infusion is taken orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aristolochia indica</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Aristolochiaceae</td><td align="left">Sapasan, Cheriya eswaramulla, Garalika, Garudi, Nagbel, Arkamul, Birthwort, Ishwarmul, Bhedi-Janete, Karalakam, Kaliparh, Kaligulesar, Issavari, Eashwari, Eshwarballi, Eshwari gida, Perumarindu, Karuda kodi, Garudakodi, Thalaisuruli</td><td align="left">Root, entire plant</td><td align="left">Fresh roots are grounded along with rouwalfia serpentina mixed in water taken twice daily (3 d).<break/>Root powder is snuffed; root juice is given orally and root paste applied locally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aristolochia tagala</italic> Cham</td><td align="left">Aristolochiaceae</td><td align="left">Samta, Valiya Eswaramulla, Perumarunt Hukodi</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">Crushed, mixed with water and drunk as well as fresh roots are grounded and applied externally on affected portion.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss</td><td align="left">Meliaceae</td><td align="left">Vembu, Veempu, Neem</td><td align="left">Flower, bark, leaf, fruit</td><td align="left">Decoction/paste is prepared and given orally (7 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Bacopa monnieri</italic> (Linn) Pennell</td><td align="left">Scrophulariaceae</td><td align="left">Brahmisak, Nirbirami, Neeripirami, Brahmi</td><td align="left">Bark, leaf, whole plant</td><td align="left">Juice mixed with castor oil is applied externally to treat.<break/>Leaf powder decoction mixed with hot cow&#x02019;s milk taken orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Barleria cristat</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left">Kali Brenkad</td><td align="left">Leaves, roots, seed</td><td align="left">Leaf juice is applied.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Boerhaavia diffusa</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Nyctaginaceae</td><td align="left">Punarnawa, Dabbal bhaji, Chotwa bhaji, Patharchatta, Biskhapara, Ittsitt</td><td align="left">Leaf, whole plant</td><td align="left">Leaf juice is also applied locally and taken orally for 7 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Bombaceae</td><td align="left">Ilavu, Kate savar, Semal, Simul, Semar, Phunchawng, Simbal, Pikriisii</td><td align="left">Flowers, roots, bark, seed</td><td align="left">Paste of flowers/fruits/leaves is applied on the bitten spot.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Buchanania lanzan</italic> Spr.</td><td align="left">Anacardiaceae</td><td align="left">Char, Chironji, Achar, Chironji, Chirongi, Pial</td><td align="left">Bark</td><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Butea monosperma</italic> (Lamk.) Taub.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Palash, Dhak, Parsa, Plash</td><td align="left">Bark, leaf, flower, gum, seed, stem bark, resin, latex</td><td align="left">Bark paste applied on swelling.<break/>Paste of one seed in 10&#x000a0;mL lemon juice is given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Caesalpinia bonduc</italic> (Linn.) Roxb.</td><td align="left">Caesalpiniaceae</td><td align="left">Poonainagam, Karanj</td><td align="left">Seeds</td><td align="left">Seeds paste applied externally (2 wk).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Calotropis gigantea</italic> (L.) R. Br</td><td align="left">Asclepiadaceae</td><td align="left">Dev rui, Aak, Ekke, Akanda, Erukku, Aakdo, Safedaakdo, Gadsa, Akanda, Erukku</td><td align="left">Roots, latex</td><td align="left">Root bark is ground into paste and made into pills n given orally.<break/>Leaf latex is applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Calotropis procera</italic> (Ait.) R. Br.</td><td align="left">Asclepiadaceae</td><td align="left">Rui, Rai, Aakori: Aakra, Biliekke, Ekka (Safed Ak), Rakta arka, Vellerukku, Akra, Aak, Madar, Safed Madar, Gadsa, Akwan</td><td align="left">Latex, root, young buds</td><td align="left">Leaf latex is applied on bitten area.<break/>Root is crushed and given to drink and applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Carica papaya</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Caricaceae</td><td align="left">Papita, Amrurbhanda, Papita</td><td align="left">Fruit, seed, latex</td><td align="left">Unripped fruit of <italic>Carica papaya</italic> is taken and the skin is removed by slicing. Salt is then rubbed over it. The fruit is then placed over the bite with sliced portions in contact with the bite and bandaged.<break/>Few drops of latex are applied to wound due to snakebite for quick healing.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cassia alata</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Caesalpiniaceae</td><td align="left">Senna, Khor-pat, daopata, Seemaiyagathi</td><td align="left">Leaf</td><td align="left">Paste of leaves is applied externally as well as given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cassia fistula</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Caesalpiniaceae</td><td align="left">Amaltash, Dhanba, Amaltas, Sonarkhi, Kakke</td><td align="left">Fruit pulp, seed, leaf, stem, roots, bark</td><td align="left">The paste and decoction of root bark with black pepper is given orally.<break/>Paste of stem bark applied on bitten place.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Caesalpiniaceae</td><td align="left">Kasaundi, Kasondi, Peeperambi, Thagarai</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">Oral administration of root paste.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cassia tora</italic> Linn</td><td align="left">Caesalpinaceae</td><td align="left">Takala, Sickle senna, Chakawad, Chakunda, Tagarai, Bon medelwa</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">Root paste and leaf decoction is applied externally (14 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cissampelos pareira</italic> Linn</td><td align="left">Menispermaceae</td><td align="left">Patha, Patindu, Batindu, Patha, Urikkakodi, Chokipar, Tijumala Ekladi, Poa</td><td align="left">Tuber, root</td><td align="left">Root paste with long pepper is prescribed once daily for 5 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> (Linn) Schrad.</td><td align="left">Cucurbitaceae</td><td align="left">Kadva inravarna, Tumba, Gadumba, Tumbo, Indrayan</td><td align="left">Seed, root, fruit</td><td align="left">Seeds oil used externally as well as root is crushed and given to drink.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Clitoria ternatea</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Ruhu tuhu, Aparajita, Syahiful, Aparajita, Gokarni, Aparajita, Bili Shankhapushpa</td><td align="left">Roots</td><td align="left">The root extract is taken with the root of <italic>A. indica</italic> and <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic>.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cocculus villosus</italic> DC.</td><td align="left">Menispermaceae</td><td align="left">Nagdun, Vachan, karalla</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">The root bark extract is given internally and applied.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Corallocarpus epigaeus</italic> (Rottl. &#x00026; Willd.) Hook. f.</td><td align="left">Cucurbitaceae</td><td align="left">Aathalai, Marsikand, Kollan, Kova killangu</td><td align="left">Root, tuber</td><td align="left">Root decoction given internally 3&#x02013;7 times.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Costus speciosus</italic> (Koen) Sm</td><td align="left">Costaceae</td><td align="left">Keon Kanda, Kebuk, Mahalakri, Jamlakhuti, Pewa, Jamlakhuti, Khongbam Takhelei, Sumbul, Jomalkhuti, Myonpobap</td><td align="left">Root, rhizome</td><td align="left">Rhizome and root paste is used internally and externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Curculigo orchioide</italic> Gaertn.</td><td align="left">Amaryllidaceae</td><td align="left">Nilapanai, Nela tengu, Kali musli</td><td align="left">Root, tuber</td><td align="left">Root paste use topicaly</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Zingiberaceae</td><td align="left">Manchal</td><td align="left">Rhizome</td><td align="left">Rhizome paste is applied externally (3 wk).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cyperus rotundus</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Cyperaceae</td><td align="left">Motha, Nagar Motha, Musta, Lavhala, Koraipullu</td><td align="left">Whole plant, root, tuber, rhizome</td><td align="left">Decoction of root/tubers/rhizome given orally (7 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Datura metel</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Solanaceae</td><td align="left">Kala Dhatura, Dhutura</td><td align="left">Seeds, root, leaf</td><td align="left">Extract of roots are taken with garlic.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium gangeticum</italic> (Linn.) DC.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Kareti, Salparni</td><td align="left">Roots</td><td align="left">Half-cup root decoction is taken orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr"><sup>73</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Drymaria cordata</italic> (L.) Willd. Ex Roem. &#x00026; Schult.</td><td align="left">Caryophyllaceae</td><td align="left">Mecanachil, Theiphelwang, Kynbat thalap</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">Whole plant is used (crushed, paste applied).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr"><sup>97</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Eclipta alba</italic> (Linn.) Hassk.</td><td align="left">Asteraceae</td><td align="left">Manchal, karisalankanni, Bhringraj, Maka</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">Whole plant juice is given orally (14 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Eclipta prostrata</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Asteraceae</td><td align="left">Karisalankanni, Bhingraj</td><td align="left">Leaf</td><td align="left">Leaf paste is applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Elaeodendron glaucum</italic> Pers.</td><td align="left">Celastraceae</td><td align="left">Ratangaur, Bhairao, Niuri, Mamri, Jamrasi, Mukarthi (Bhutphal)</td><td align="left">Bark, root</td><td align="left">Roots and bark of plant made into paste taken orally with cow&#x02019;s milk.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Emblica officinalis</italic> Gaertn.</td><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left">Amla, Avala, Nelli</td><td align="left">Stem, leaves, fruit, roots</td><td align="left">Root extract is given orally along with black pepper.<break/>Leaf juice as well as stem infusion is given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Euphorbia hirta</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left">Ammanpacharisi</td><td align="left">Latex, whole plant</td><td align="left">Latex or whole plant, decoction given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Euphorbia neriifolia</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left">Mausa sij, Dudhbol, Thor, Thundar, Manasa</td><td align="left">Latex, root</td><td align="left">Latex is applied locally.<break/>Root is used with black pepper.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ficus religiosa</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Moraceae</td><td align="left">Peepal</td><td align="left">Leaf, bark, fruit</td><td align="left">25&#x000a0;g stem bark and 8&#x02013;10 cloves are pounded with animal fat (pure ghee) and given 4&#x02013;6 times a day.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Gloriosa superb</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Liliaceae</td><td align="left">Vadhavadiyo, Vach Nag, Nagardi, Gowri Huvu, Kalihari, Kalihari, Karianaga, Agnishikha, Kariyari, Kalappa, Kilangu</td><td align="left">Tuber, root, rhizome, seed</td><td align="left">Root paste or tuber paste is applied externally (2&#x02013;5 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Gymnema sylvestre</italic> (Retz.) R. Br.</td><td align="left">Asclepiadaceae</td><td align="left">Dudhkhuri, Sirukurinchan, Gurmar, Afumari, Gurmarbooti, Sirukurinjan</td><td align="left">Leaf, root</td><td align="left">Root Tincture or leaf powder taken orally (4 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Helicteres isora</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Sterculiaceae</td><td align="left">Hateri, Murud sheng, Maror Phali</td><td align="left">Bark, root</td><td align="left">Bark power is given in snakebite.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Heliotropium indicum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Boraginaceae</td><td align="left">Nakkipoo</td><td align="left">Leaf</td><td align="left">The leaf juice mixed with hot water is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Hemidesmus indicus</italic> (Linn.) R. Br.</td><td align="left">Asclepiadaceae</td><td align="left">Suganti Jad, Anantmul, Choti dudhia, Anantamul, Analsing, Nannari, Anantamul</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">Aqueous extract of root is prepared in water and given orally, and root paste is applied two or three times a day.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Holarrhena antidysentrica</italic> wall</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Kurwa, Dudhkhuri, Koraya</td><td align="left">Bark, root</td><td align="left">The root is crushed and applied as well as paste is taken orally with water.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Holarrhena pubescens</italic> (Buch.-Ham.) Wall. ex G.Don</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Pandhara Kula, Bolmatra</td><td align="left">Seeds, root, stembark</td><td align="left">Paste is applied on the bitten area two times a day</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Lantana camara</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Verbenaceae</td><td align="left">Ragadd, Gajukampa, Arippu</td><td align="left">Roots, flower, stem, leaf, whole plant</td><td align="left">Decoction of roots, flower and stem are used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">96</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Lantana indica</italic> Roxb.</td><td align="left">Verbenaceae</td><td align="left">Siruunnichedi</td><td align="left">Leaf</td><td align="left">Leaf decoction externally used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Leucas cephalotes</italic> (Roth) Spreng</td><td align="left">Lamiaceae</td><td align="left">Goma, Gumbi, Gumma</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">Decoction of whole plant (twice a day for 6 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Luffa acutangula</italic> (Linn.) Roxb.</td><td align="left">Cucurbitaceae</td><td align="left">Torai, Peerkan, Jangli Torai</td><td align="left">Fruit, tendril, seed</td><td align="left">Tendrils and seed paste is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Madhuca indica</italic> (Koenig.) macbride Gmel</td><td align="left">Sapotaceae</td><td align="left">Mahua, Mahuwa, Madgi, Mahua, Dori, Mahuda, Saathikkai</td><td align="left">Flower, leaves, bark, seeds</td><td align="left">Bark paste is externally applied (2&#x02013;3 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> Linn</td><td align="left">Mimosaceae</td><td align="left">Lajwanti, Thotta Sinungi, Uskadpoda, Chhuimui/Lajwanti, Thottal surungi, Thottalvadi, Thottasiniki</td><td align="left">Root, leaf, whole plant</td><td align="left">Whole plants are made extract in drinking water and shaken well and filtered. Extract of whole plant is given twice a day in 1 d only.<break/>Leaves are ground and made into paste and applied over affected area.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Mitragyna parvifolia</italic> (Roxb.) Korth.</td><td align="left">Rubiaceae</td><td align="left">Neer-kadamba, Kadamba</td><td align="left">Bark, fruit</td><td align="left">Unknown.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Momordica charantia</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Cucurbitaceae</td><td align="left">Karela, Pakakai</td><td align="left">Whole plant, Shoot or root</td><td align="left">Juice of tender shoot or root is applied.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam</td><td align="left">Moringaceae</td><td align="left">Sajina, Nugge, Sahigan, Mungna, Sainjna, Sahjan, Sainjnad, Murungaih</td><td align="left">Root, seed, whole plant, stem bark, leaf</td><td align="left">Fresh extract of bark is taken orally.<break/>Bark, root tincture applied externally (3 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Mucuna pruriens</italic> (Linn.) DC</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Kevach, Konch</td><td align="left">Seed, fruit, root</td><td align="left">Aqueous extract of root is given orally for twice a day.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Murraya paniculata</italic> (Linn.) Jack.</td><td align="left">Rutaceae</td><td align="left">Gandhela, Angarapputhalai</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">Infusion prepared from shadily dried root/leaf powder and administered orally for every 1&#x000a0;h up to 2 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Musa paradisiaca</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Musaceae</td><td align="left">Vazhai, Valaimaram Valai</td><td align="left">Bark, stem, skin bark</td><td align="left">A plant extract is given orally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Nerium indicum</italic> Mill. Gard.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Kaner, Kaner/Kanail, Lal kanher</td><td align="left">Leaf, bark, root</td><td align="left">The root is crushed with roots of <italic>Capparis sepiaria</italic> and <italic>Datura innoxia</italic>, and paste applied externally thrice for 5 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Nerium oleander</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Alari, Aralli, Bogakorobi</td><td align="left">Seeds</td><td align="left">Seeds paste applied externally (14 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Solanaceae</td><td align="left">Tambakhu, Pukhaielai</td><td align="left">Leaf</td><td align="left">Leaves decoction given orally (3 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Lamiaceae</td><td align="left">Barpai, Tulasi</td><td align="left">Leaf, root, whole plant</td><td align="left">A paste of ocimum leaf with the rhizome of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. (Zingiberaceae) is applied externally.<break/>Leaf juice, oral (8 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ophiorrhiza mungos</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Rubiaceae</td><td align="left">Havina gedde, Pambupoo, Keeripundu</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">Root juice is given (twice a day for 6 days).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Opuntia dillenii</italic> (Ker-Gawl) Haw</td><td align="left">Cactaceae</td><td align="left">Sappathikali</td><td align="left">Stem bark, fruit, entire plant</td><td align="left">The fruits paste is applied.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Oxalis corniculata</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Oxalidaceae</td><td align="left">Simejar, Chhota Tangesi, Ambuti, Kaitka, Sohdkhiew</td><td align="left">Whole plant, leaves</td><td align="left">Whole plant is crushed and paste is tied on the specific spot of bite, the juice is also drunk.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">97</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pergularia daemia</italic> (Forrsk.) Chiov.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Veliparuthi</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">The decoction of the leaves is used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Piper longum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Piperaceae</td><td align="left">Pipla</td><td align="left">Roots</td><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr"><sup>73</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Piperaceae</td><td align="left">Bolkaalu, Menasina kaalu, Maricha, Kali-mirch, Milagu</td><td align="left">Flower, seed, fruit</td><td align="left">Seed powder mixed with butter is given orally against snakebite.<break/>Flower paste with ghee given orally (4 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>, <xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">94</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Plumbago zeylanica</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Plumbaginaceae</td><td align="left">Koduveli</td><td align="left">Whole plant, root</td><td align="left">Whole plant paste is given internally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Radermachera xylocarpa</italic> (Roxb.) K.Schum.</td><td align="left">Bignoniaceae</td><td align="left">Tetu</td><td align="left">Fruit, seed</td><td align="left">Fruit paste applied and taken internally as well as pulp of seeds with little water is taken.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr"><sup>92</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (Linn.) Benth. ex Kurz.</td><td align="left">Apocyanaceae</td><td align="left">Nagbel, Bhuin karuan, Patal-garuda, Bhuikurma, Sarpagandha, Keramaddinagaddi, Sutranabhi, Sarpagandha, Lairusich, Sarpagandha</td><td align="left">Leaf, root</td><td align="left">Leave juice used as antidote.<break/>Roots and leaf buds crushed with milk and make into paste used both internally and externally on affected area.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>, <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rhinacanthus nasutus</italic> (L.) Kurz</td><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left">Nagamalli</td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">Fresh leaves are taken orally as well as the paste of the leaf is applied externally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Sauromatum venosum</italic> (Ait.) Kunth</td><td align="left">Araceae</td><td align="left">Halida, Samp ki dawa</td><td align="left">Tuber</td><td align="left">The paste of tuber is applied on the affected part.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Semicarpus anacardium</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Anacardiaceae</td><td align="left">Cashew nut</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">Root is taken orally (7 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Solanum xanthocarpum</italic> Schard &#x00026; Wendl</td><td align="left">Solanceae</td><td align="left">Bhui ringani, Bhat kataiyan, Choti kateli</td><td align="left">Leaves, root</td><td align="left">Fresh leaves extract (paste or decoction) of this species is given.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Soymida febrifuga</italic> A. Juss.</td><td align="left">Meliaceae.</td><td align="left">Rohina</td><td align="left">Stem bark, bark, root</td><td align="left">Fresh bark of this plant together with root of H. pubescens (1:1) are made into paste, and mixed with drinking water, given orally three times a day for 3 d.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Strychnos nux-vomica</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Loganiaceae</td><td align="left">Kajara, Kaasarka, Kanjiram, Vishamushti, Etti, Visakkotai, Yeti</td><td align="left">Root, seed</td><td align="left">Root bark juice in cow's milk is externally rubbed 3&#x02013;4 times a day, to treat.<break/>The seed powder is also used.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tabernaemontana divaricata</italic> (Linn.) R.Br.</td><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left">Nanjatte, Maddarasa, Kathona, Amli, Tengtere, Tetul</td><td align="left">Root, leaf, seed</td><td align="left">The extract of the seed is given as well as crushed, paste applied on bitten area.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tamarindus indica</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Caesalpiniaceae</td><td align="left">Puli</td><td align="left">Seed, root</td><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tephrosia purpurea</italic> (L.) Pers.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Sarphankha, Sarphonk, Dhamaso, Kolingi, Wild indigo</td><td align="left">Root</td><td align="left">Root decoction along with black pepper is prepared and taken orally (7 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic> (DC) Wight &#x00026; Arn.</td><td align="left">Combertaceae</td><td align="left">Arjun, Marutham, Vellamarthu</td><td align="left">Bark</td><td align="left">Bark paste applied externally (5 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic> (Willd) Miers ex Hook f. &#x00026; Thoms</td><td align="left">Menispermaceae</td><td align="left">Gulvel, Limbvel, Amrutha balli, Guduchi, Gulanchi</td><td align="left">Leaf, root, stem</td><td align="left">Stem juice or leaf juice along with garlic paste is applied on the spot and also taken orally (3&#x02013;4 d).</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tridax procumbens</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Asteraceae</td><td align="left">Munya arxa, Dagad Ful.</td><td align="left">Leaves</td><td align="left">The leaves are crushed and the juice is dripped on the wound of snakebite.<break/>Juice is taken orally after its dilution with some quantity of water.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tylophora indica</italic> (Burm. f.) Merr.</td><td align="left">Asclepiadaceae</td><td align="left">Nangilai, Asthamakodi</td><td align="left">Leaf, root</td><td align="left">Paste of leaf and root is mixed with equal amount of root paste of <italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> and applied externally on the spot as well as leaf juice alone is also taken internally.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Uraria picta</italic> Desv.</td><td align="left">Fabaceae</td><td align="left">Prasniparni, Dabara, Mahadevjata, Ishwarjata</td><td align="left">Root, leaf</td><td align="left">Leaf paste or root decoction is given twice daily.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">98</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Verbascum Thapsus</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Scrophulariaceae</td><td align="left">Jangli tambaku, Kukalenga, Koti</td><td align="left">Whole plant</td><td align="left">The infusion of whole plant is given.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">77</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Vitex negundo</italic> Linn.</td><td align="left">Verbenaceae</td><td align="left">Nukki, Lakkigida, Karinochi, Notchi, Nishindi, Shet nishinda</td><td align="left">Bark, root, leaf, seed</td><td align="left">Leaf paste applied over the bitten area (5 d) as well as root extract is given with warm water.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Vitex penduncularis</italic> Wall</td><td align="left">Verbenaceae</td><td align="left">Charaigorh</td><td align="left">Bark</td><td align="left">Decoction of the bark is given orally at 30-min interval.</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>While preparing the list of medicinal plants, the following points were considered: biological source(s), family, local name(s) part(s) used, method of preparation, and reference(s). The methodology of preparations depends on the availability of plant part(s) and urgency of utilization. Often, the preparation is done by crushing the plant with the help of stones or a wooden piece, and making juice or paste that will be applied on the affected area; sometimes they are also given orally. If we consider their popularity on the basis of more than five plants used from one family, then there are 29 families. The widely used families are Acanthaceae, Araceae, Fabaceae, and Rubiaceae (&#x0003e;22%). They are followed by Apocynaceae (&#x0003e;20%), Euphorbiaceae (&#x0003e;19%), and Lamiaceae (&#x0003e;18%). A recent study revealed that rich ethnomedicinal knowledge from community members should be recognized, documented, and preserved appropriately so future generations can benefit. Predominantly, it is required that ethnomedicinal plants used by local groups and tribes of people be comprehensively studied to determine the value of these plant species so that they can be managed and conserved for the welfare of mankind.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>7</label><title>Indian Vaidya concept</title><p>In India, there is a group of people known as &#x0201c;Vaidya&#x0201d; (a doctor of herbs, compounder of medicinal preparations such as Churna, Pills, Syrup, Asava, Aristha, Taila), and elderly persons with folk knowledge about the uses of various household spices and herbs. Their native beliefs, skills, and cultural practices concerned with people&#x02019;s health are useful in curing various diseases. Some elderly women with expertise in delivering babies have proficient knowledge about folk medicines for facing day-to-day health problems, especially among puberty girls, lactating mothers, and pregnant women. As per Indian beliefs, Mother Nature nurtures us. Hippocrates also stated that &#x0201c;Nature cures, not the physician.&#x0201d; Plants are rich sources of medicinal compounds by which we can cure a variety of diseases, as well as maintain and improve our health.<xref rid="bib0490" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref> Ayurveda states that each and every plant has medicinal use; you just need to find the right person to show that. Owing to the various undesirable effects of some modern-day drugs, an increasing number of people from both developed and developing countries have turned to medicinal plants.<xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr"><sup>98</sup></xref></p><p>There is an extraordinary thinking that understanding knowledge is the key for any revolution. India is a megadiverse nation, home to approximately 10% of the world's species. For the past several thousands of years, India has nurtured a rich cultural heritage, and large numbers of Indians have used a variety of plants through their rituals and cultural activities. Unfortunately, because of the sudden huge increase in population, negligent behavior toward environmental care guidelines, and global climate change, so many species are now on the verge of vanishing. This has had a strong effect on the food chain, standard of living, and cultural practices&#x02014;rituals&#x02014;of thousands of Indians. To maintain biodiversity, many conservation organizations in India are working to alleviate this trend.</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><label>8</label><title>Review findings</title><p>The present review is an attempt to compile information about traditional/ethnobotanical medicinal plants used in various parts of India for snakebite treatment. This study will help future researchers understand various approaches to treat snakebites. Data obtained from the present investigation are presented in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (the plant species are arranged in alphabetical order). A total of 523 plant species belonging to 122 families have been reported for the treatment of snakebite. However, this appraisal applies only to a small compilation of essential plants that are frequently used in snakebite poisoning in India. Acanthaceae, Amaranthaceae, Apocynaceae, Araceae, Asteraceae, Caesalpiniaceae, Cucurbitaceae, Euphorbiaceae, Fabaceae, Lameaceae, Moraceae, Rubiaceae, Rutaceae, and Zingiberaceae are the most significant families from which a variety of plants are used. The local names of these plants are given in brackets, and for a better understanding, we also included the actual meanings of these names as well as descriptions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>9</label><title>Local names of plants with meanings</title><p>The following list includes the plants that are most frequently used in snakebite treatment in India:<list list-type="simple"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Abrus precatorius</italic> Linn. (<italic>Gunj</italic>)&#x02014;Two or three grams of fresh leaves or roots of the plant with seeds are made into paste and consumed along with cold water or cow&#x02019;s milk. (Two times a day for 5&#x02013;7&#x000a0;days to cure any poisonous bite, as well as root powder applied topically.)</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Achyranthes aspera</italic> Linn. (<italic>Apamarg</italic>)&#x02014;&#x0201c;Apamarg&#x0201d; means to cure in a &#x0201c;wrong way.&#x0201d; The whole plant&#x02019;s extract and/or root&#x02019;s extract is given orally. The paste obtained from the root is also used for 3 weeks. <italic>Achyranthes bidentata</italic> Blume and <italic>Achyranthes porphyristachya</italic> W are also significant in snakebite treatment.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Acorus calamus</italic> Linn. (<italic>Vekhand</italic>)&#x02014;The term &#x0201c;vekhand&#x0201d; is regularly used by Indian women to describe anti-inflammatory, expectorant in infants. The rhizomes are crushed to paste and given with warm water as well as applied externally on affected area.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Alangium salvifolium</italic> (Linn.f) Wang. (<italic>Ankol</italic>)&#x02014;About 15&#x000a0;g of bark, ground with 10&#x02013;12 black peppers and mixed with 60&#x000a0;g animal fat, is given every 2&#x000a0;hours to cure snakebite. Root bark decoction is given internally to treat.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Albizia lebbeck</italic> (Linn). Benth. (<italic>Shirish</italic>)&#x02014;Paste of bark is used.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0030"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (Burm F) Wall. Ex. Nees. (<italic>Kalmegh</italic>)&#x02014;A decoction of the leaves with the leaves of <italic>Andrographis alata</italic> is given. Decoction or extract is applied externally. <italic>Andrographis affinis</italic> Nees., <italic>A. alata</italic> Nees, <italic>Andrographis echioides</italic> Nees, <italic>Andrographis lineata</italic> Wallich Ex, <italic>Andrographis macrobotrys</italic> Nees, <italic>Andrographis neesiana</italic> Wight., <italic>Andrographis ovate</italic> C.B. Clarke, and <italic>Andrographis serpyllifolia</italic> (Vahl.) Wights are other species that are significant in antiophidian cure.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0035"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Aristolochia indica</italic> Linn. (<italic>Nagvel</italic>)&#x02014;The term <italic>Nagvel</italic> is coined from two words&#x02014;&#x0201c;Nag&#x0201d;, meaning snake, and &#x0201c;Vel&#x0201d;, meaning creeper. Fresh roots are ground along with rouwalfia serpentina mixed in water and taken twice daily (3 days). Root powder is snuffed; root juice is given orally and root paste is applied locally. Another species, <italic>Aristolochia bracteolate</italic>&#x02019;s leaves are turned into paste and applied externally; infusion is taken orally.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0040"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Bacopa monnieri</italic> (Linn) Pennell (<italic>Brahmi</italic>)&#x02014;Juice mixed with castor oil is applied externally to treat. Leaf powder decoction mixed with hot cow&#x02019;s milk and taken orally.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0045"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Boerhaavia diffusa</italic> Linn. (<italic>Punarnawa</italic>)&#x02014;It is also well known as Hog Weed. &#x0201c;Punarnawa&#x0201d; means making new. Basically, it is diuretic and an expectorant, given for abdominal pain. The juice taken from leaves is applied locally and taken orally for 7 days. <italic>Boerhaavia repens</italic> Linn is also useful.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0050"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Bombax ceiba</italic> Linn. (<italic>Simul</italic>)&#x02014;The paste of flowers/fruits/leaves is applied on the bitten spot.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0055"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Buchanania lanzan</italic> Spr. (<italic>Chironji</italic>)&#x02014;A range of research and review articles mentioned it as commonly beneficial, but the method of preparation and parts used is unknown.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0060"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Butea monosperma</italic> (Lamk.) Taub (<italic>Palas</italic>)&#x02014;Traditionally, leaves of this plant are used to make ecofriendly plates for serving food items. The paste prepared from bark is applied on the swelling. Paste of one seed in 10&#x000a0;mL lemon juice is given orally.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0065"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Calotropis gigantea</italic> (L.) R. Br (<italic>Dev Rui</italic>)&#x02014;It is holy plant whose leaves and flowers are used to offer to a supernatural being, Hanuman (monkey-faced Hindu deity). The hanuman is well known for his intelligence, physical strength, loyalty, politeness, etc. The root or bark is ground into paste and made into pills and given orally for relief. This plant&#x02019;s leaf latex is applied on bitten area. Another species, <italic>Calotropis procera</italic> (<italic>Ark</italic>, <italic>Rui</italic>), is also useful in healing.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0070"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Cassia fistula</italic> Linn. (<italic>Amaltas</italic>)&#x02014;The paste and decoction of root bark along with black pepper is given orally. Also, the paste of stem bark is applied on the bitten area. <italic>Cassia alata</italic>, <italic>Cassia obtusifolia</italic>, <italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic>, <italic>Cassia sophera</italic>, <italic>Cassia tora</italic>, and <italic>Cassia glauca</italic> are also used in snakebite treatment.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0075"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Cissampelos pareira</italic> Linn (<italic>Patha</italic>)&#x02014;The term &#x0201c;Patha&#x0201d; means a way. Usually, paste of roots along with long pepper is recommended to be used once daily for 5 days.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0080"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Clitoria ternatea</italic> Linn. (<italic>Aparajit</italic>)&#x02014;&#x0201c;Aparajit&#x0201d; means undefeated. The root extract is taken with the root of <italic>A. indica</italic> and <italic>Rauwolfia serpentina</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0085"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Corallocarpus epigaeus</italic> (Rottl. &#x00026; Willd.) Hook. F. (<italic>Killangu</italic>)&#x02014;The decoction made up from roots is given internally three to seven times.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0090"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Curculigo orchioide</italic> Gaertn (<italic>Klimoosali</italic>)&#x02014;The paste of roots is applied topically on the affected site.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0095"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Gloriosa superb</italic> Linn. (<italic>Vachnag</italic>, <italic>Kalihari</italic>)&#x02014;It has a versatile local name; &#x0201c;Vachnag&#x0201d; means controlling snake and &#x0201c;Kalihari&#x0201d; means prolonging death. The root paste or tuber paste is applied externally on the bitten area for 2&#x02013;5&#x000a0;days or until relief.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0100"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Gymnema sylvestre</italic> (Retz.) R. Br. (<italic>Gurmar</italic>)&#x02014;The most common antidiabetic medicinal plant also used in antiophidian treatment. Its local name, &#x0201c;Gurmar,&#x0201d; means destroying sweet. The tincture of root or leaf powder is taken orally for 4 days.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0105"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Hemidesmus indicus</italic> (Linn.) R. Br. (<italic>Anantmool</italic>)&#x02014;&#x0201c;Anantmool&#x0201d; means life-saving root. The aqueous extract of root is prepared in water and given orally, and root paste is applied two or three times a day.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0110"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Leucas aspera</italic> Spreng. (<italic>Thumbhai</italic>)&#x02014;The leaf and root are useful. Leaf paste or crushed leaf is taken both externally on the bitten site and orally to treat. The root juice is mixed with goat&#x02019;s milk three times a day for 4 days.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0115"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> Linn (<italic>Lajwanti</italic>)&#x02014;The whole plant is useful. Extract of the whole plant is given twice a day in 1&#x000a0;day only. Leaves are ground and made into paste and applied over the affected area.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0120"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam (<italic>Sahigan</italic>)&#x02014;Bark and roots are used. Fresh extract of bark is taken orally, whereas the tincture of bark and root is applied externally for about 3 days.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0125"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Musa paradisiaca</italic> Linn. (<italic>Valai</italic>)&#x02014;A plant extract is given orally.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0130"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Piper nigrum</italic> Linn. (<italic>Kali Mirch</italic>)&#x02014;Seed powder mixed with butter is given orally against snakebites. Flower paste with ghee is given orally (4 days).</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0135"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Rauvolfia serpentina</italic> (Linn.) Benth. ex Kurz. (<italic>Sarpgandha</italic>)&#x02014;The Rawolf denotes a snakelike structure. The rauvolfia has about 86 different species, but the most frequently used and compelling, antiophidian, plant in the India is <italic>R. serpentina</italic>. The local name, &#x0201c;Sarpgandha,&#x0201d; means smelling like snake, and shows comprehensive observations of local Vaidya (Doctors), tribal peoples of the surrounding habitat. Its leaves and roots used as antidote. Roots and leaf buds are crushed with milk and made into paste; used both internally and externally on the affected area.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0140"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Strychnos nux-vomica</italic> Linn. (<italic>Vishmushti</italic>)&#x02014;The local name is coined from two terms; &#x0201c;Vish,&#x0201d; means poison, and &#x0201c;Mushti&#x0201d; means relief from. The root bark juice in cow's milk is externally rubbed three to four times a day, to treat. The seed powder is also used. <italic>Strychnos colubrina</italic> and <italic>Strychnos potatorum</italic> Linn. are also useful.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0145"><label>&#x02022;</label><p><italic>Vitex negundo</italic> Linn. (<italic>Nishindi</italic>)&#x02014;The root extract is given orally, and leaf paste is applied on the bitten area.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>10</label><title>Statistical study</title><p>When considering the parts used, the most widely used (in descending order) parts are roots (28%), leaves (23%), bark (11%), whole plant (10%), seed (7%), fruit (5%), stem (4%), other parts such as latex, rhizomes, bulbs, tubers, gums, and flowers (12%) (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The preparation method of medication sometimes varies from vaidus (local medicine man) to vaidus. The popular forms are decoction, juice, extract, powder, fresh part, and paste. The duration of treatment varies, depending on the type of snakebite. The various preparations are frequently prepared by using a single plant part or a blend of more than a few plant parts. Occasionally, a mixture of two or more different plant species is also applied. The study revealed that medicinal plants still play a vital role in the primary healthcare of tribal Indians, and the knowledge received from them will be very useful for researchers in ethnobotany and pharmacology.<xref rid="bib0495" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref> The valuable knowledge about their uses is important as some of these plants are on the verge of vanishing. This review is an attempt to compile comprehensive data from various resources and make them available into one organized, ready-to-use, compilation.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Plant parts used in treatment of snakebite.</p><p>Bk, bark; Lv, leaves; Fr, Fruit; Ot, other parts; Rt: root, Sd, seed; St, Stem; Wp, whole plant.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0055"><label>11</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>One valuable gift to human health is provided by nature in the form of medicinal plants in the locality and one of the significant ways in which humans directly reap the benefits provided by biodiversity. India has long history of medicinal plant utilization in traditional and tribal culture. From the present review, a total of 523 species from 122 plant families have been used against snakebites, as reported by different ethnobotanical investigations mostly carried out during the past few years in India (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). In this review, we focused on the collection of data for the most frequently used plants in snakebite treatment. This work tried to be the most comprehensive review to date, and it shows striking similarities between medicinal plant uses in different nations. Thus, by triangulation, it is probably still possible to document most of the knowledge, but further research should continue, especially in areas within nations that have received less attention. Ethnobotanical investigation of drug discovery has been found to be one of the most reliable approaches toward use of medicinal plans for treatment of various conditions, and even now, there are still many more things for us to discover.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Graphical representation showing number of plants according to various families.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasab</surname><given-names>F.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosravi</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants of Sirjan in Kerman Province, Iran</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>154</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24746480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ody</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The complex medicinal herbal</chapter-title><year>1993</year><publisher-name>Dorling Kindersley Limited</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayub</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinally important shrubs and trees of Himalayan region of Azad Jammu and Kashmir, Pakistan</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>166</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25814319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkataswamy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamad Mubarack</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukumar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by Malasar tribals in Coimbatore district of Tamil Nadu (SouthIndia)</article-title><source>Asian J Exp Biol Sci</source><volume>1</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>392</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lulekal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelbessa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>VanDamme</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal study of plants used for human ailments in Ankober District, North Shewa Zone, Amhara Region, Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><volume>63</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calixto</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twenty five years of research on medicinal plants in Latin America: a personal review</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>100</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16006081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>WHO</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Traditional medicine strategy 2002&#x02013;2005. WHO/EDM/TRM/2002.1</chapter-title><year>2002</year><publisher-name>World Health Organisation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will tribal knowledge survive the millennium</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>287</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical uses of medicinal plants in the highlands of Soan Valley, Salt Range, Pakistan</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>155</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rates</surname><given-names>S.M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants as source of drugs</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>39</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11072038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jabbar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaseen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthelmintic activity of <italic>Chenopodium album</italic> (L) and <italic>Caesalpinia crista</italic> (L) against trichostrongylid nematodes of sheep</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>114</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17826017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Red&#x0017e;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecological aspect of ethnobotany and ethnopharmacology of population in Bosnia and Herzegovina</article-title><source>Coll Antropol</source><volume>31</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18041402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabricant</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnsworth</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of plants used in traditional medicine for drug discovery</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect (Suppl)</source><volume>109</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosalge</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fursule</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of ethnomedicinal claims of some plants used by tribals of Satpuda Hills in India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>121</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19100321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One hundred useful raw drugs of the Kani tribes of Trivandrum forest division, Kerala</article-title><source>Int J Crude Drug Res</source><volume>22</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pushpangadan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atal</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedico-botanical investigation in Kerala: I. Some primitive tribals of Western Ghats and their herbal medicine</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>11</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6471881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anuradha</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumbhojkar</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vartak</surname><given-names>V.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on wild plants used in folk medicine in the rural areas of the Kolhapur district</article-title><source>Anc Sci Life</source><volume>6</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22557559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harsha</surname><given-names>V.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebbar</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedge</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shripathi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedical knowledge of plants used by Kunabi tribe of Karnataka in India</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>73</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12234569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parinitha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasa</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivanna</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant wealth of local communities in some villages in Shimoga Distinct of Karnataka, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>98</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15814264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional antidotes of snake poison in Northern India</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>61</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants with a reputation against snake bite</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>30</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1440620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osibogun</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flowering plants used against snakebite</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>39</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8331959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Milestones and future prospects in snake venom research</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>62</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22995211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant-based treatment of snakebites</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><volume>14</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>573</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelanis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashima</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unraveling snake venom complexity with &#x02018;omics&#x02019; approaches: challenges and perspectives</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>87</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24878375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Snake venom poisoning</series><volume>18</volume><year>1980</year><publisher-name>J.B. Lippincott</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>234</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Snake venoms: general background and composition</chapter-title><source>Venoms: chemistry and molecular biology</source><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Jon Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Snake venoms and coagulopathy</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><volume>45</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samy</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thwin</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopalakrishnakone</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of folk plants for the treatment of snakebites in Southern part of Tamilnadu, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>115</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhandary</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaveriappa</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of Gowlis of Uttara Kannada District, Karnataka</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>12</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yabesh</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by traditional healers in silent valley of Kerala, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>154</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24832113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lija</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auxillia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of Kani tribes in Thoduhills of Kerala, South India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>152</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24393788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vikneshwaran</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakshmi</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of the ethnomedicinal flora of the Sirumalai hills, Dindugul District, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Leaflets</source><volume>12</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>953</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajadurai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidhya</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno-medicinal plants used by the traditional healers of pachamalai hills, Tamilnadu, India</article-title><source>Ethno-med</source><volume>3</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>V.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajesh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Athiperumalsami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants of the Tirunelveli district, Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Leaflets</source><volume>12</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Devanna</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used by ethnic people in West and South district of Tripura, India</article-title><source>J For Res</source><volume>22</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>426</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingaiah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used by traditional healers of Adilabad district, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Bull Pure Appl Sci Bot</source><volume>31</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunitha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant resources of Rudrakod sacred grove in Nallamalais, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>J Biodivers</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mamidala</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey in different mandals of Adilabad district, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Sci</source><volume>2</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayagiri</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamidala</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical investigations among traditional healers in Warangal district of Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Pharmacogn J</source><volume>4</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0205"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagaraju</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>K.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of plant crude drugs of Rayalaseema, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>29</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2374428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0210"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno medicinal plants used by gonds of Adilabad district, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Life Sci</source><volume>3</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2034</fpage><lpage>2043</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0215"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiremath</surname><given-names>V.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taranath</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional phytotherapy for snake bites by tribes of Chitradurga District, Karnataka, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Leaflets</source><volume>14</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0220"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kshirsagar</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some less known ethnomedicinal uses from Mysore and Coorg districts, Karnataka state, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>75</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11297857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0225"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jitin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnomedicinal survey of Orchha Wildlife Sanctuary region of Tikamgarh District, Madhya Pradesh, India</article-title><source>J Bot Res</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0230"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of plant biodiversity of Hazaribag district Jharkhand India and its medicinal uses</article-title><source>Biosci Disc</source><volume>3</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0235"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devendra</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijaykumar</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seetharam</surname><given-names>Y.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folklore medicinal plants of Gulbarga District, Karnataka, India</article-title><source>eJIM-eJ Indian Med</source><volume>3</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0240"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahishi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasa</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shivanna</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant wealth of local communities in some villages in Shimoga District of Karnataka, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>98</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15814264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0245"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thirumalai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elumalai</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Therasa</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of folklore plants for the treatment of jaundice and snakebites in Vellore districts of Tamilnadu, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot leaflets</source><volume>14</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>536</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0250"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mythili</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravinder</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murali</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants in Khammam District, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Appl Biol Pharm Technol</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0255"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants in Sonebhadra District of Uttar, Pradesh, India with reference to their infection by foliar fungi</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res</source><volume>6</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2727</fpage><lpage>2746</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0260"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chellappan</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal studies of Pichavaram mangroves of East coast, Tamil Nadu</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><volume>4</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>411</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0265"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mashih</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observation on ethnomedicinal herbs of Dantewada, Chattishgarh, India</article-title><source>Int J Drug Discov Herbal Res</source><volume>3</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0270"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalkho</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on ethnomedicinal uses and formulation of herbal drugs from medicinal plants of Ranchi District&#x02014;a survey</article-title><source>Am J Ethnomed</source><volume>2</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0275"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masih</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants used in the healthcare systems of tribes of Dantewada, Chhattisgarh India</article-title><source>Am J Plant Sci</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1632</fpage><lpage>1643</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0280"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunjam</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jadhav</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional herbal medicines for the treatment of snake bite and scorpion sting by the tribes of South Surguja, Chhattisgarh, India</article-title><source>Med Aromat Plants</source><volume>2</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0285"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional medicinal practices among the tribal people of Raigarh (Chhatisgarh), India</article-title><source>Indian J Nat Prod Resour</source><volume>1</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0290"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeetendra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno medicinal plants used by tribal communities for the treatment of snakebite in West Nimar, MP, India</article-title><source>ISCA J Biol Sci</source><volume>1</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0295"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choyal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional phytotherapy for snake bites by the local rural people of Hamirpur district in Himachal Pradesh (India)</article-title><source>Biol Forum</source><volume>4</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0300"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhakat</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>U.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethno medicinal plant conservation through sacred groves</article-title><source>Tribes Tribals</source><volume>2</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0305"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhellum</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manhas</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants of Kathua district, J &#x00026; K, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>171</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26023030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0310"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal practices in different communities of Uttara Kannada district of Karnataka for treatment of wounds</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>143</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0315"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajith</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicines of Kurichyas, Kannur district, Western Ghats, Kerala</article-title><source>Indian J Nat Prod Resour</source><volume>1</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>253</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0320"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhadange</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Harnessing plant biodiversity of forests of Akola and Washim District of Maharashtra for medicinal use</article-title><source>Int J Adv Biotechnol Res</source><volume>2</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>356</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0325"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alagesaboopathi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plants used for the treatment of snake bites by Malayali tribals and rural people in Salem district, Tamilnadu, India</article-title><source>Int J Biosci</source><volume>3</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0330"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Q.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal cure for poisons and poisonous bites from Western Uttar Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Asian Pacific J Trop Dis</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>S116</fpage><lpage>S120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0335"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional phytotherapy of some medicinal plants used by the Tharus of the Nainital District, Uttar Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Pharmacogn</source><volume>32</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0340"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkhel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of folklore plants used in treatment of snakebite in Paschim Medinipur district, West Bengal</article-title><source>Asian Pacific J Trop Biomed</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>420</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0345"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkhel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used in treatment of snakebite by the tribal communities of Paschim Medinipur district, West Bengal</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Life Sci</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>3172</fpage><lpage>3177</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0350"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basha</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional use of plants against snakebite in Sugali tribes of Yerramalais of Kurnool district, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Asian Pacific J Trop Biomed</source><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>S575</fpage><lpage>S579</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0355"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of plant crude drugs of Anantapur district, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><volume>27</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0360"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvanayagam</surname><given-names>Z.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnanavendhan</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishna</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antisnake venom botanicals from ethnomedicine</article-title><source>J Herbs Spices Med Plants</source><volume>2</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0365"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical studies of the Tarai region of Kumaun, Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><volume>11</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0370"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and status of ethno-medicinal plants of Almora district in Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>Int J Biodivers Conserv</source><volume>3</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>326</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0375"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batish</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohli</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used by Gujjar Community of Trikuta Hills in Jammu and Kashmir, India</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res</source><volume>7</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2111</fpage><lpage>2121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0380"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on the traditional phytotherapy among the inhabitants of Parvati valley in western Himalaya, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>92</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15137998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0385"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on native medicine of Jaunsari tribe of Dehradun district, Uttar Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Pharmacogn</source><volume>35</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0390"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phondani</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An inventory of indigenous knowledge and cultivation practices of medicinal plants in Govind Pashu Vihar Wildlife Sanctuary, Central Himalaya, India</article-title><source>Int J Biodivers Sci Ecosyst Serv Manage</source><volume>6</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0395"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vashishtha</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional healthcare practices among the villages of Rawain valley, Uttarkashi, Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><volume>10</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>537</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0400"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0400"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangwal</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gairola</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Faith herbal healer knowledge document of Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve, Uttarakhand, India</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><volume>12</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0405"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0405"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nautiyal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dasila</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal plant uses in a small tribal community in a part of central Himalaya, India</article-title><source>J Hum Ecol</source><volume>14</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0410"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0410"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used by ethnic and rural people in eastern Sikkim Himalayan region</article-title><source>Afr J Basic Appl Sci</source><volume>4</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0415"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0415"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aboriginal uses and management of ethnobotanical species in deciduous forests of Chhattisgarh state in India</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><volume>5</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19128461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0420"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0420"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marandi</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arulappan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antivenom herbal formulations used against snakebites by the Oroan tribals of Latehar, Jharkhand</article-title><source>World J Pharmaceut Res</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1971</fpage><lpage>1982</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0425"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0425"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharati</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used as ethnoveterinary medicines in Sikkim Himalayas</article-title><source>Ethnobot Res Appl</source><volume>10</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>356</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0430"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0430"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saklani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical observations on plants used in Northeastern India</article-title><source>Int J Crude Drug Res</source><volume>27</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0435"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0435"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padal</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional uses of Plants by the tribal communities of Salugu Panchayati of Paderu Mandalam, Visakhapatnam, District, Andhra Pradesh, India</article-title><source>Int J Comput Eng Res</source><volume>3</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>103</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0440"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0440"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirsat</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal uses of some common bryophytes and pteridophytes used by tribals of Melghat region (Ms), India</article-title><source>Ethnobot Leaflets</source><volume>12</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>692</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0445"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0445"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malviya</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some ethno-medicinal plants used by Baiga Tribes from Amarkantak, India</article-title><source>Adv Life Sci Technol</source><volume>4</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0450"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0450"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicinal uses of pteridophytes of Amarkantak, Madhya Pradesh</article-title><source>Indian J Tradit Knowl</source><volume>4</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>395</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0455"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref0455">Barla S. Ethno-Medicinal Beliefs And Practices Among Tribals Of Jharkhand. 221-240. Atat&#x000fc;rk Culture, Language And History Higher Organization Website. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Http://Www.Ayk.Gov.Tr/Wp-Content/Uploads/2015/01/Barla-S.-J.-Emmanuel-Ethno-Medicinal-Beliefs-And-Practices-Among-Tribals-Of-Jharkhand.Pdf" id="intr0005">Http://Www.Ayk.Gov.Tr/Wp-Content/Uploads/2015/01/Barla-S.-J.-Emmanuel-Ethno-Medicinal-Beliefs-And-Practices-Among-Tribals-Of-Jharkhand.Pdf</ext-link>. Accessed September 05, 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0460"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0460"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamble</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bipinraj</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagtap</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used by the Thakar tribes of Raigad district, Maharashtra for the treatment of snake-bite and scorpion-bite</article-title><source>Int J Phytother Res</source><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0465"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0465"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayyanar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants commonly used by Kani tribals in Tirunelveli hills of Western Ghats, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>134</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21291981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0470"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0470"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandikumar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chellappandian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutheeswaran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Consensus of local knowledge on medicinal plants among traditional healers in Mayiladumparai block of Theni District, Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>134</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0475"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0475"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vashistha</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Floristic and ethno botanical survey of Ambala District, Haryana</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Bio Sci</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>360</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0480"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0480"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neogi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotany of some weeds of Khasi and Garo hills, Meghalaya, Northeastern India</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><volume>43</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>479</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0485"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0485"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of Tapkeshwari Hill, Bhuj, Kachchh, India</article-title><source>Life Sci Leaflets</source><volume>2</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0490"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0490"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puttaiah</surname><given-names>E.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananth</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethonobotanical studies of some plants included in folk medicines of Goa</article-title><source>Int J Basic Appl Sci</source><volume>3</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0495"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0495"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagtap</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deokule</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhosle</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some unique ethnomedicinal uses of plants used by the Korku tribe of Amravati district of Maharashtra, India</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>107</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713158</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors extend their thanks to Dr N.G. Haswani, HOD (R.C. Patel Institute of Pharmacy, Shirpur), Dr M.G. Kalaskar, Mr M.V. Girase, and Mr J.J. Lamale (Department of Pharmacognosy) for encouragement and suggestions from time to time.</p></ack></back></article>