<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IPHB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">iphb20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmaceutical Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1388-0209</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1744-5116</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6130550</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28262031</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880209.2017.1296470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1296470</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antifungal and antioxidant activities of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> against skin diseases</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">O. O. Fajinmi et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fajinmi</surname><given-names>Olufunke O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000fa;z</surname><given-names>Ji&#x00159;&#x000ed;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tarkowski</surname><given-names>Petr</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>Manoj G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Finnie</surname><given-names>Jeffrey F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>Johannes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><label>a</label><institution>Research Centre for Plant Growth and Development, School of Life Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal Pietermaritzburg</institution>, Scottsville, <country>South Africa</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>b</label><institution>Laboratory of Growth Regulators and Department of Chemical Biology and Genetics, Centre of the Region Han&#x000e1; for Biotechnological and Agricultural Research, Faculty of Science, Palack&#x000fd; University and Institute of Experimental Botany</institution>, Olomouc, <country>Czech Republic</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>c</label><institution>Centre of the Region Han&#x000e1; for Biotechnological and Agricultural Research, Central Laboratories and Research Support, Faculty of Science, Palack&#x000fd; University</institution>, Olomouc, <country>Czech Republic</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>d</label><institution>Centre of the Region Han&#x000e1; for Biotechnological and Agricultural Research, Department of Genetic Resources for Vegetables, Medicinal and Special Plants, Crop Research Institute</institution>, Olomouc, <country>Czech Republic</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT <addr-line>Johannes Van Staden</addr-line><email>rcpgd@ukzn.ac.za</email><institution>Research Centre for Plant Growth and Development, School of Life Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal Pietermaritzburg</institution>, Scottsville, <country>South Africa</country></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="160">1249</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s).</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="iphb-55-1296470.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Context:</bold><italic>Coleonema album</italic> (Thunb) Bart. &#x00026; H. L. Wendl (Rutaceae) has been used in the formulation of skincare products, and the <italic>Khoisan</italic> people rub it on their skin to add luster. <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> I. Williams has received less attention in the South African traditional medicine.</p><p><bold>Objective:</bold> This study investigates the antifungal and antioxidant activities of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> essential oil (EO) and leaf extracts; and analyzes the chemical components of their EOs.</p><p><bold>Materials and methods:</bold> Antifungal activity of leaf extracts was determined using the microdilution method with griseofulvin and ketoconazole as controls. Antifungal capacity of EO was investigated using the &#x02018;Volatile release plate method&#x02019;. <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> (ATCC 28188) and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> (ATCC 9533) mycelia (0.3&#x02009;cm diameter) were placed on fresh yeast malt agar in Petri dishes with filter paper (impregnated with 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of EO) on the lid for direct exposure to EO volatiles while plates without EO were used as controls. The incubation time was seven days. Antioxidant activities of the leaf extracts were determined.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> Methanol leaf extract of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> inhibited the growth of three fungi tested with MIC values of 195, 391 and 49&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL for <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic>, <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic> and <italic>Microsporum gypseum,</italic> respectively. Terpenes formed the major components of the EO. The EO from both plants inhibited the growth of <italic>T. rubrum in vitro.</italic></p><p><bold>Discussion and conclusion:</bold> This study revealed the therapeutic value of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic>. <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> should be considered as potential plants for skin ointment from natural origin.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Atopic dermatitis</kwd><kwd><italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport of the Czech Republic</named-content></funding-source><award-id>LO1204</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>J.G. and P.T. acknowledges the support of the Ministry of Education, Youth and Sport of the Czech Republic (Grant LO1204 from the National Program of Sustainability).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="7317"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Fungal infections of the skin and nails represent a major group of mycoses (Havlickova et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and are among the most common skin disease manifestation in HIV/AIDS patients. They can occur at any stage of the disease and some of the dermatoses are unique to HIV infection while others are common conditions, which also occur in HIV-negative individuals (National Aids and STI Control Program <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Patients with HIV infection exhibit a wide range of skin pathology which includes bacterial, fungal and viral infections; skin tumours; inflammatory and eczematous eruptions; and drug rashes (Rudikoff <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). In a study involving 186 HIV positive patients, 175 (94%) suffered from one or more cutaneous disorders (Ho &#x00026; Wong <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Dermatophytoses manifests as an opportunistic infection which is four times more prevalent in Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) patients (Goodman et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>).</p><p>The frequently isolated species are <italic>Trichophyton rubrum, T. mentagrophytes</italic> and <italic>Epidermophyton floccosum</italic> (Fernandes et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> is a geophillic dermatophyte, which is rarely isolated from skin lesions of immunocompromised patients (Bhagra et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> may cause <italic>Tinea capitis</italic> (ringworm of the scalp and hair) and <italic>Tinea corporis</italic> (ringworm of the glabrous skin) in immunocompetent hosts (Pandey &#x00026; Pandey <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The most common skin disorder identified in HIV/AIDS individuals is fungal infection (Tse <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p><p>The increased incidence of resistance of skin fungal diseases to antibiotics is of great concern. The situation is more prominent among HIV/AIDS individuals, thus adding to the burden of skin diseases in Africa as a region. Owing to the high incidence of HIV/AIDS in South Africa, there is an urgent need for the development of new medicines to cure various HIV/AIDS opportunistic infections, especially skin diseases. The improvement of previously used antibiotics, and the introduction of a new range of antibiotics for the treatment of skin diseases of fungal origin, has not been able to significantly solve the problem of the increasing incidence of skin diseases resistant to antibiotics. Hence, the search for an effective antifungal skin ointment of natural origin could present a lasting solution to the shortcomings of the various antibiotics used in clinical practice. Rutaceae plants are known to be a source of coumarins, terpenes, flavonoids and other therapeutic agents that have been reported to be effective in the treatment of skin diseases and alleviation of oxidative stress and inflammation. Scientific literature has shown a link between inflammation and oxidative stress as it plays a crucial role in the pathogenesis of chronic inflammatory diseases such as atopic dermatitis (AD) (eczema/ringworm).</p><p>Restoration of the redox balance through the use of antioxidants from natural origin could be a ground-breaking approach in the treatment of inflammatory skin conditions. Natural products offer a variety of anti-inflammatory (Yasser &#x00026; Nabil <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and antioxidant agents (Kostova <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), which can counter the oxidative stress, dryness, scaling, and inflammations that comes into play during the pathogenesis of skin diseases.</p><p>A combination of inflammatory conditions and an overwhelmed antioxidant system could result in pathological levels of Reactive Oxidative Species (ROS) and thus, oxidative stress aggravates the disease state (Wagener et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Kruk and Duchnik (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) reported how oxidative stress plays a crucial role in the pathogenesis of dermatologic diseases through the disruption of the defensive systems against ROS/RNS (Reactive Nitrogen Species). ROS are produced during normal metabolic processes and are an integral part of the normal cellular function, usually of little harm as the body&#x02019;s defence system reduces their damaging effects (Trouba et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). A higher percentage of oxidative stress in AD is caused as a result of the increase in lipid peroxidation and decreased levels of antioxidants (Sivaranjani et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Antioxidants shield the body from the damaging effects of ROS and can inhibit and/or reverse several processes that contribute to epidermal toxicity and skin diseases (Trouba et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p><p><italic>Coleonema</italic> (Rutaceae) is a genus of flowering plants, and all eight known species are endemic to the Cape region of South Africa, but they have been domesticated in some other countries such as Australia. All the species of the genus are characterized with dotted oil glands on their leaves. The main chemical components of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> (Thunb) Bart. &#x00026; H. L. Wendl oil are myrcene, phellandrene, pinene, ocimene, and germacrene-D (Ba&#x0015f;er et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). A wide range of coumarin derivatives have been isolated from <italic>C. album</italic> (Dreyer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">1972</xref>; Gray <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>). Pharmacological activities of <italic>C. album</italic> have been attributed to its terpenes and coumarins (and coumarin derivatives). These include: antithrombotic and antiplatelet (Hoult &#x00026; Paya <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>), antimicrobial (Kayser &#x00026; Kolodziej <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Laurin et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Lis-Balchin &#x00026; Hart <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Okunade et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2006a</xref>; Liebenberg <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and antioxidant (Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2006b</xref>; Liebenberg <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) activities.</p><p>A tincture made from <italic>C. album</italic> and marketed as &#x02018;<italic>Immunat</italic>&#x02019; is widely used in South Africa as an herbal remedy to build the body&#x02019;s immune system. Some compounds isolated from this plant have activity against several inflammatory mediators (Eldeen &#x00026; Van Staden <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Even though ethnobotanical work has been done on <italic>C. album</italic> (Fajinmi et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), the pharmacological activities of its sister species (<italic>C. pulchellum</italic> I. Williams) is yet to be fully explored. Fishermen traditionally rub their hands on the leaves to remove the fishy smell of bait (Van Wyk &#x00026; Gericke <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Essential oil (EO) derived from <italic>C. album</italic> is incorporated into several skin care products. Fajinmi et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) reported that there is currently an increase in demand for and utilization of <italic>C</italic>. <italic>album</italic> in South African traditional medicine. Many South African natural product companies are now pursuing export markets for <italic>C. album</italic> oil, which may put pressure on the plant&#x02019;s natural populations in the near future (Fajinmi et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>However, its sister species, <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> has received little or no attention. Apart from the development of an effective propagation technique and control of harvesting of <italic>C. album</italic> wild populations, the use of another member of the genus with the same medicinal value can help reduce the pressure on <italic>C. album</italic> plants and thus prevent the plant from becoming an endangered species in the near future. <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> have similar morphological features in the field and can only be distinguished by the colour of their flowers which are white and pink, respectively. However, some hybrids (with pink flowers) of both plants exist in gardens and nurseries in South Africa. The aim of this study was to investigate the <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaf extract, EO volatiles against three fungal strains responsible for AD, analyze the bioactive compounds present in the EO of both species and investigate the antioxidant activity of the leaf extracts.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0003"><title>Antifungal assay of leaf extracts</title><p>Leaves were sourced from the KwaZulu-Natal botanical garden (Pietermaritzburg, South Africa) in September 2014. The plant was verified by the botanical garden horticulturist (Ms Alison Young). Voucher specimen, <italic>Coleonema album</italic> O Fajinmi 01 and <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> O Fajinmi 21 have been deposited in the University of KwaZulu-Natal Herbarium. Fresh leaves were dried in an incubator at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for four days. Dried leaves were ground into powder and stored in air-tight containers at 23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the dark. Known quantities of ground leaf samples were extracted non-sequentially using 100% petroleum ether, acetone, methanol, ethanol and water. Different fractions were filtered using a B&#x000fc;chner filter and evaporated to dryness in a vacuum concentrator at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The extracts were poured into pill vials, left to dry under a fan at room temperature and stored in a sterile container in a walk-in fridge before use. Antifungal activity was determined using the microdilution method as described by Clinical Laboratory Standards (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) (Reference method for broth dilution antifungal susceptibility testing of filamentous fungi. Approved standard M38-A. National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards) with modifications. The dried extracts (25&#x02009;mg each) were weighed into separate Eppendorfs and dissolved in 1&#x02009;mL of 70% ethanol, sonicated and then used for antifungal bioassays. <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> (ATCC 28188), <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> (ATCC 9533) and <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> (ATCC 24102) were purchased from Quantum Biotechnologies, Randburg, South Africa. They were grown on yeast malt agar (Y3127). A small portion of a seven-day-old culture was scraped with a scalpel into McCartney bottles containing yeast malt broth (Sigma Y3752) and incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 2 (<italic>M. gypseum</italic>) and 7&#x02009;days (<italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic>), respectively. The suspension was adjusted using a spectrophotometer to an absorbance of between 0.25 and 0.28 at 530&#x02009;nm. The fungal inoculum was prepared with 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> Colony Forming Units (CFU) in the suspension. Susceptibility testing was carried out using the micro-dilution method. Distilled water (100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) was pipetted into each of the 96 wells in a microtitre plate and 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of the diluted leaf extract were added to the 1st well of the column and then serially diluted down the wells. The diluted fungal suspension (100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) was added to each of the 96 wells. The microtitre plates were subsequently incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02009;h after which 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of <italic>p</italic>-iodonitrotetrazolium violet (INT) (Sigma 58030-1G-F) indicator was added to each well to determine growth inhibition. The microtitre wells were observed 30&#x02009;min to 1&#x02009;h after the indicator was added. The lowest concentration of clear wells was regarded as the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) values. Broth (50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) was added to each well immediately after the readings were taken. The microtitre wells were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02009;h and then observed in order to determine the minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC). The assay was repeated three times in order to ensure consistency of results.</p></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Analysis and antifungal assay of essential oil (EO)</title><p>Leaves of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> were sourced (in September 2015) from the South African National Biodiversity Institute, Kirstenbosch. The leaves were freeze-dried and stored in sealed plastic bags. Essential oil was extracted from 20&#x02009;g of freeze-dried leaves using hydrodistillation method. The extraction of oil was done according to the Czech Pharmacopeia. The EO derived was subjected to analysis using Gas Chromatography Mass Spectrometry (GCMS) (Agilent 5975C, Palo Alto, CA). Sample injection volume was 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;L at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min, increased to 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at 2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min, held at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min (injection at 220&#x02009;&#x000b0;C; column HP-5, 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;250&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m; carrier gas He 1&#x02009;mL/min; MS detection). The major constituents (&#x02265;1.5%) were recorded individually while the minor constituents (&#x02264;1.5%) were recorded as &#x02018;others&#x02019;.</p><p>The antifungal activity of the EO derived from the leaves of the plants was analyzed using the volatile release plate method. This method was adopted to determine if gradual exposure to EO volatiles can effectively inhibit the growth of the fungi mycelia. Essential oil naturally is composed of several volatile components which evaporate under different temperatures. A variety of these components have been reported to inhibit the growth of infectious pathogens <italic>in vitro</italic>. <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> (ATCC 28188) and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> (ATCC 9533) were grown in yeast malt broth for one week and the fungal suspensions were subcultured on fresh yeast malt agar for one week. Mycelia of 0.3&#x02009;cm diameter were taken from plates with good mycelia growth. The agar supporting the mycelia was sliced off and the mycelia were placed on fresh agar plates. Filter paper was placed on the upper lid of Petri dishes with fresh agar. The filter paper was impregnated with 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of EO in such a way that the mycelia placed on the agar plate were directly exposed to the EO volatiles. Plates with similar diameter (0.3&#x02009;cm) of <italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> without EO were used as controls. The plates were incubated for a week and the diameter of the mycelia was recorded after seven days of incubation. A formula, Fungal Growth Index (FGI) was used to calculate the increase in the size of the mycelia in order to be able to determine the extent of the inhibition of the fungi by the EO volatiles.
<disp-formula id="M0001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IPHB_A_1296470_M0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="ID0EAAABBDBA"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>FGI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Final&#x000a0;diameter&#x000a0;of&#x000a0;mycelia</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Initial&#x000a0;diameter&#x000a0;of&#x000a0;mycelia</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Initial&#x000a0;diameter&#x000a0;of&#x000a0;mycelia</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>The mycelia from each Petri dish were subcultured on fresh agar plates and incubated for another seven days at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in order to determine if the treatments had a fungistatic or fungicidal effect.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Determination of oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC)</title><p>Fresh plant material (leaves) was sourced from the South African National Biodiversity Institute, Kirstenbosch. The sample was freeze-dried, ground into powder and stored in air-tight containers at 23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The sample (100&#x02009;mg) was dissolved in 1&#x02009;mL of 80% methanol and sonicated for 30&#x02009;min. It was subsequently filtered using a syringe filter. The antioxidant activity of the leaf extracts was determined using the ORAC method according to Ou et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Briefly, 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 500&#x02009;nM fluorescein and 25&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of diluted extracts were pipetted into each working well of a microplate preincubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Then, 25&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 250&#x02009;mM 2,2&#x02032;-azobis(2-amidinopropane) dihydrochloride (AAPH) was added and the microplate was shaken for 5&#x02009;s on a shaker. The fluorescence (Ex. 485&#x02009;nm, Em. 510&#x02009;nm) was read every 3&#x02009;min for 90&#x02009;min. Net area under the curve was used to calculate antioxidant capacity which was expressed as Trolox equivalents.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0006"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0007"><title>Antifungal assay of leaf extracts</title><p>The methanol extract of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> (195&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL), and methanol and acetone extracts of <italic>C. album</italic> (781&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL) exhibited the best activity against <italic>T. rubrum</italic>, while the methanol extracts of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> (391&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL) exhibited the best activity against <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> and <italic>C. album</italic> methanol extracts (49 and 195&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively) showed the best antifungal activity against <italic>M. gypseum</italic> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Extracts with good antifungal activities against <italic>M. gypseum</italic> include: <italic>C. album</italic> acetone and ethanol extracts (391&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL), <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> acetone and ethanol extracts (781&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL). The methanol extract of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> inhibited the growth of all the tested fungal strains with MIC values of 195, 391 and 49&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL for <italic>T. rubrum</italic>, <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> and <italic>M. gypseum</italic>, respectively. The levels of antifungal activities recorded above are noteworthy as the values are less than 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, similar to the MIC values of the antibiotics ketoconazole and griseofulvin used in this study. The water extracts of the leaves gave very high MIC values (results not shown). None of the extracts tested had a fungicidal effect.</p><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Antifungal activity of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaf extracts against <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic>, <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> and <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic>.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="center">Petroleum ether (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center">Acetone (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center">Methanol (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center">Ethanol (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Fungal strain</th><th align="center">Plant species/test compound</th><th align="center">MIC</th><th align="center">MFC</th><th align="center">MIC</th><th align="center">MFC</th><th align="center">MIC</th><th align="center">MFC</th><th align="center">MIC</th><th align="center">MFC</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left"><italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema album</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center"><bold>781</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center"><bold>781</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center">1563</td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center">3125</td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center"><bold>195</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center">1563</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Ketoconazole</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Griseofulvin</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema album</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center">1172</td><td align="char" char=".">3250</td><td align="center"><bold>391</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center">1563</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center">3125</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center"><bold>391</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center">1563</td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Ketoconazole</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Griseofulvin</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema album</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center"><bold>391</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center"><bold>195</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center"><bold>391</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="char" char=".">6250</td><td align="center"><bold>781</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td><td align="center"><bold>49</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">1563</td><td align="center"><bold>781</bold></td><td align="char" char=".">3125</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Ketoconazole</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003c;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Griseofulvin</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x0003e;1000</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>Bold values indicate the best antifungal activity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0008"><title>Analysis and antifungal assay of essential oil (EO)</title><p>Caryophyllene (24.91%), <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene (9.49%), &#x003b2;-myrcene (7.96%) and octahydro-7-methyl-3-methylene-4-(1-methylethyl)-&#x003b2;-copaene (7.53%) are the major components of <italic>C. album</italic> EO while bicyclo[3.1.0]hex-2-ene,4-methyl-1-(1-methyethyl)-&#x003b2;-phellandrene (32.04%), (+)-3-carene (10.88%), &#x003b2;-ocimene (9.46%), &#x003b3;-elemene (8.95%) and &#x003b1;-pinene (7.43%) are the major components of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO. The components of the oil greater than 1.5%, found in both EO of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> are caryophyllene, bicyclo[3.1.0]hex-2-ene,4-methyl-1-(1-methyethyl)-&#x003b2;-phellandrene, &#x003b1;-pinene, &#x003b3;-elemene and carene (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, the common bioactive compounds exist in both EO in different quantities.</p><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p><italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> essential oil bioactive compounds.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Bioactive compounds (%)</th><th align="center"><italic>Coleonema album</italic></th><th align="center"><italic>Coleonema pulchelum</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">&#x00391;-Terpineol</td><td align="char" char=".">3.69</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bicyclogermacrene</td><td align="char" char=".">5.11</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bicyclo[3.1.0]hex-2-ene,4-methyl-1-(1-methyethyl)-&#x02003;&#x003b2;-Phellandrene</td><td align="char" char=".">5.97</td><td align="char" char=".">32.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)-3-Carene</td><td align="char" char=".">5.98</td><td align="char" char=".">10.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)-4-Carene</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="char" char=".">3.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caryophyllene</td><td align="char" char=".">24.91</td><td align="char" char=".">6.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Eucalyptol</td><td align="char" char=".">2.58</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b3;-Elemene</td><td align="char" char=".">1.84</td><td align="char" char=".">8.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Myrcene</td><td align="char" char=".">7.96</td><td align="char" char=".">4.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Octahydro-7-methyl-3-methylene-4-(1-methylethyl)-&#x02003;&#x003b2;-copaene</td><td align="char" char=".">7.53</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="char" char=".">9.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1,3,6-Octatriene,3,7-dimethyl-, (Z)-&#x003b2;-ocimene</td><td align="char" char=".">2.25</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Phellandrene</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="char" char=".">1.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="char" char=".">7.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Phellandrene</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="char" char=".">3.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Pinene</td><td align="char" char=".">7.00</td><td align="char" char=".">5.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td align="char" char=".">9.49</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Others</td><td align="char" char=".">15.69</td><td align="char" char=".">5.34</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p>ND: not detected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The EO volatiles from both plants inhibited the growth of <italic>T. rubrum in vitro</italic> with final mycelia diameter of 0.3&#x02009;cm and FGI of 0% (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) each. <italic>Coleonema album</italic> EO volatile had total inhibition on both <italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic>. However, <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO volatile did not have total inhibition on the growth of <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> mycelia as the final mycelia diameter of <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> treated with the EO was 0.5&#x02009;cm resulting into a 66.67% FGI. Overall, volatiles from <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO inhibited the growth of the fungi <italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> compared to the final diameter of the mycelia controls of 2.0 and 1.0&#x02009;cm diameters, respectively.</p><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO volatiles on Fungal Growth Index (FGI) (%) of <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> as compared to the control.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Fungal strains</th><th align="center"><italic>Coleonema album</italic> oil FGI (%)</th><th align="center"><italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> oil FGI (%)</th><th align="center">Control FGI (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left"><italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> &#x02003;(diameter) cm</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">566.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic> &#x02003;(diameter) cm</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">66.7</td><td align="char" char=".">233.33</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0009"><title>Determination of ORAC</title><p>The antioxidant activity expressed as Trolox equivalents (&#x003bc;mol Trolox Equivalents/g) of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaf extracts are recorded in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The leaf extracts of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> has higher Trolox equivalents value (1126.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;68.1&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol Trolox Equivalents/g) compared to that of its sister species <italic>C. album</italic> (942.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;34.9&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol Trolox Equivalents/g).</p><table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>ORAC<sup>FL</sup> values of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> expressed as Trolox equivalents.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Plant species</th><th align="center">&#x003bc;mol Trolox Equivalents/g</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema album</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">942.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;34.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">1126.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;68.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Discussion</title><p>Several species of the Rutaceae family have been used in traditional medicine and coumarins could be responsible for a majority of their activities (Gray &#x00026; Waterman <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">1978</xref>). Extracts of <italic>C. album</italic> displayed potent and relevant pharmacological activities, with a considerable antifungal activity against several strains responsible for important infectious diseases (Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2006a</xref>). The compounds from <italic>C. album</italic> could be of great pharmaceutical interest for therapeutic application as complementary antifungal agents (Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2006a</xref>). Its sister species, <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> contains phenylpropenes, phenylpropanoids and terpenoids which exhibit antimicrobial properties (Brader et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>).</p><p>In this study, the methanol extract of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> demonstrated good <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against the three fungi tested indicating the potency of the plant against skin diseases of fungal origin. Hence, <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> (methanol extract) has good prospects for the formulation of an effective cure for skin disease. Brader et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>) attributed the observed antimicrobial activity to the reactivity of the phenolic hydroxyl group. The plant <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> contains biologically potent therapeutic phytochemicals with high antibacterial and antioxidant activities (Baskaran et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The result of this study support the report of Baskaran et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) as the leaf extracts of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> displayed a remarkable antioxidant activity much higher than that of <italic>C. album</italic> leaf extract. <italic>n</italic>-Hexadecanoic acid, a compound isolated from <italic>C. album</italic>, has been identified as one of the compounds that possess fungistatic properties against mammalian skin pathogens (Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2006a</xref>). It has been reported to possess antifungal activity against <italic>Trichophyton mentagrophytes</italic>, a zoophilic skin fungus which is responsible for athlete&#x02019;s foot (Wood &#x00026; Weldon <xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). In this study, methanol extract and EO of <italic>C. album</italic> exhibited good activity against <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> and thus confirm the reports of the cited authors.</p><p>Essential oils are known to have several properties which are of great importance in skin health (Rhind <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Such properties include skin barrier function, maintenance and restoration of texture and hydration levels, reduction of inflammation, stimulation of cell regeneration, prevention or control of infections and allergic responses, and alleviation of itching (Rhind <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Antimicrobial activities of EO have been attributed mainly to its volatile components such as monoterpenes which in many cases are the main components of EO. The EO extracted from the epicarp of <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> exhibited absolute fungitoxicity against 10 post-harvest pathogens (Sharma &#x00026; Tripathi <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). <italic>Haplophyllum tuberculatum</italic> oil affected the mycelial growth of <italic>Curvularia lunata</italic> and <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (Al Burtamani et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). In this study, the volatiles of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO displayed antifungal activity against two important skin fungi, <italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes.</italic> It is, however, not certain which component(s) of the EOs are responsible for the activity.</p><p>The major components of <italic>C. album</italic> oil are &#x003b2;-phellandrene (29.1%) and myrcene (20.5%) among the 43 components characterized (Ba&#x0015f;er et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). However, the major components of the <italic>C. album</italic> oil analyzed in this study are caryophyllene (24.91%), <italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-ocimene (9.49%), &#x003b2;-myrcene (7.96%) and octahydro-7-methyl-3-methylene-4-(1-methylethyl)-&#x003b2;-copaene (7.53%). Bicyclo[3.1.0]hex-2-ene,4-methyl-1-(1-methyethyl)-&#x003b2;-phellandrene (32.04%), (+)-3-carene (10.88%), &#x003b2;-ocimene (9.46%), &#x003b3;-elemene (8.95%) and &#x003b1;-pinene (7.43%) are the major components of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO analyzed in this study.</p><p>The literature available on the analysis of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO, however, differ from what we found in this study as bicyclo[3.1.0]hex-2-ene,4-methyl-1-(1-methyethyl)-&#x003b2;-phellandrene (32.04%) form one-third of the bioactive compound composition. Essential oil from the leaves of Australian <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> was found to consist mainly (50%) of monoterpene hydrocarbons (Brophy &#x00026; Lassak <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>). Monoterpene composition of the oil of South African <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> is more than that of the Australian sample (Brophy &#x00026; Lassak <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>). In the three oil samples of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> analyzed by Ba&#x0015f;er et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), monoterpenes dominated with 92.2%, 81.4% and 97.0%, respectively. The presence of &#x003b2;-phellandrene and sabinene as part of the major compounds was the main difference in two of the samples while &#x003b2;-pinene, linalool and &#x003b1;-pinene form part of the major components in all the three samples analyzed. Overall, monoterpenes were the major compounds of all the oils ranging from 86.5% to 97.3% (Ba&#x0015f;er et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p><p>Harvesting related factors such as season of harvest, geographical location and age of the plant at the time of harvest plays crucial roles on the EO yield and most importantly the composition of the bioactive compounds present in the oils (Preedy <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Cavacrol, the major component of oregano EO was higher during the drier and warmer season (70.75&#x02013;84.88%) while several other compounds accumulated at higher levels during the wetter and colder season along with very low levels of cavacrol (56.46&#x02013;75.12%) (Karamanos &#x00026; Sotiropoulou <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The season of harvest, plant age and geographical location could be some of the factors responsible for the chemical composition of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> EO in this study and the antioxidant activity of their leaf extracts.</p><p>There is increasing interest in the use and quantification of antioxidant capacity in the pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries (Ou et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). This interest results from the enormous evidence of the importance of reactive oxygen/nitrogen species (ROS/RNS) in aging and pathogenesis of diseases (Halliwell &#x00026; Aruoma <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Wink et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Nguyen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Stadtman <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). Natural antioxidants, such as EOs seem to have the potential to offer considerable protection against oxidative skin damage (Rhind <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Caryophyllene and limonene have been reported to display strong 5-lipoxygenase inhibitory activity (Baylac &#x00026; Racine <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>).</p><p>Several EOs have antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities, and some appear to be significant, specifically in relation to the skin as there is a possibility that antioxidant activity is linked with keratinocyte differentiation, and hence barrier function and texture (Rhind <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). This implies the crucial role oxidative stress plays in the development of AD. Antioxidant activity is one of the major and most important biological activities attributed to EOs and is at the root of many other properties which include anti-inflammatory activity (Rhind <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Essential oils have been reported to have anti-inflammatory activities and their constituents such as terpene hydrocarbons, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons and sesquiterpene alcohols have been reported to display 5-lipoxygenase inhibitory activity (Alexander <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Baylac &#x00026; Racine <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The hydrophobic nature of EO makes it difficult to determine its antioxidant activity of EO <italic>in vitro</italic>. Leaf extracts of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> were used instead of their EOs.</p><p>In this study, <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaf extracts gave higher antioxidant activity compared to <italic>C. album</italic> extract. The antioxidant activity in an array of different natural sources is often attributed to coumarins (Moure et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Heim et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). <italic>Coleonema album</italic> extracts possessed significant <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activity which could be as a result of the phenolic compounds present in the plant extract (Esterhuizen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2006b</xref>). Coumarins and flavonoids are phenolic compounds and have been demonstrated to have potent antioxidant activities as a result of their phenolic hydroxyl groups (Demmig-Adams &#x00026; Adams <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and an ideal structural chemistry for free radical scavenging activity (Rice-Evans &#x00026; Burdon <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). The phenolics have received increased attention as a result of the various scientific reports indicating a correlation between consumption of food and beverages rich in phenolics and reduced incidence of diseases linked to oxidative stress (Rice-Evans &#x00026; Burdon <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Martinez-Cayuela <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Heinecke <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Chisolm &#x00026; Steinberg <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>).</p><p>Under various pathological conditions, an oxidative cascade may be generated which can induce cytotoxicity and apoptosis and may have a significant role in inflammation, enhancing the release of cytokines and modifying lipoproteins to pro-inflammatory forms (Gutteridge <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>; Deigner &#x00026; Hermetter <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Lipid peroxidation (LPO) products react with sugars, proteins, and DNA (Niki <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The end products of LPO, such as malondialdehyde, 4-hydroxy-2-nonenal (4-HNE) and 4-hydroxy-2-hexanal (4-HEE) can damage proteins by reacting with various amino acids both <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> (Catal&#x000e1; <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Oxidative stress causing the production of lipid peroxides may thus be a major factor in the development of skin inflammatory diseases (Braconi et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Sivaranjani et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>Generally, it is recognized that a combination of environmental factors such as allergens, microbial infection and genetic factors induce the multiple immunologic and inflammatory responses seen in AD patients (L&#x000fc; et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Atopic dermatitis (eczema/ringworm) can affect any part of the human body but seems to occur more frequently on the hands and feet, ankles, face, wrists, upper chest and neck (Sivaranjani et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and the skin around the eyes and the eyelids (Thestrup <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Eczema is a form of chronic inflammatory skin disease (Wagener et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) with various hallmarks, such as chronic relapsing of skin inflammation, disturbance of the epidermal-barrier function which at its climax leads to dry skin and eruptions (Sivaranjani et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In an attempt to achieve an increased therapeutic rate of treatments of skin diseases, a combination of topical and oral anti-inflammatory drugs have been used (Soares et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). A decrease in inflammation and an improved rate of recovery could be achieved in the treatment of inflammatory skin conditions by targeting oxidative stress (Wagener et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Atopic dermatitis is associated with an impaired oxidative status, and systemic alterations in antioxidant patterns of the skin have been found in skin of AD patients as well as in non-lesioned skin as an adaptive response to chronic inflammation of the epidermis (Briganti &#x00026; Picardo <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Filament aggregating protein (filaggrin, FLG) is a key protein that plays a major role in the formation of the cornified cell envelope, which is crucial for an effective skin barrier (Candi et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Studies have shown that loss-of-function (null) mutations in the gene-encoding FLG leads to skin barrier impairment in AD patients (Marenholz et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Palmer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Weidinger et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Many AD patients acquire a deficiency of filaggrin with subsequent barrier disruption as a result of the local inflammatory immune response (Howell et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>A combination of events such as transepidermal water loss, disruption of the skin epidermal barrier system, oxidative stress, inflammation and ultimately, invasion by microbial pathogens are responsible for the manifestation of skin diseases. In view of this, an effective antifungal should encompass all the activities needed to restore skin health. As a result of the principal role of ROS in inflammatory pathologies, the restoration of redox balance forms a ground-breaking therapeutic target in the development of new approaches for the treatment of inflammatory skin conditions (Wagener et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Nuclear factor E2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) links antioxidant defence mechanisms in the epidermis with the control of skin permeability barrier and antimicrobial defence (Schafer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The production of ROS and ROS-induced oxidation results in the disruption of the skin barrier (Thiele <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). This implicates that restoration of redox balance through the use of effective antioxidant formulations in combination with an effective antifungal could ameliorate skin inflammation, reduce transepidermal water loss and thus restore the skin barrier function and prevent further invasion by microbial pathogens.</p></sec><sec id="s0011"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Methanol extracts of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaves contain bioactive compounds capable of inhibiting the growth of <italic>T. rubrum</italic>, <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic> and <italic>M. gypseum</italic>. Hence, the extracts can provide a novel source of antifungal for the treatment of skin diseases. The EO of both species is rich in terpenes which have been reported in literature to exhibit antifungal activity. However, the season of harvest of the leaves will determine the level of antifungal activity displayed by the EO as bioactive compounds present in EO varies with environmental and physiological (age) factors during harvest of leaves or plant part(s). The EO of both plant species can be combined to formulate an effective antifungal ointment that can combat skin diseases associated with <italic>T. rubrum</italic>. The result of this study revealed the therapeutic value of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic>, which is not as popular as its sister species, <italic>C. album</italic>. Extracts and EO of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> should be considered in the production of skin and hair care products just as its sister species (<italic>C. album</italic>). A combination of the antifungal and antioxidant activities of <italic>C. album</italic> and <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> leaf extracts and the antifungal activity of their EO volatiles against <italic>T. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. mentagrophytes in vitro</italic> as reported in this study gives hope for the development of an effective and cheap skin antifungal of natural origin. The results of this study give credence to the incorporation of <italic>C. album</italic> extracts and EO into skincare products. As a result of the remarkable antifungal and antioxidant activities of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic>, as revealed in this study, the plant can be incorporated into skincare products just like <italic>C. album</italic>. However, toxicity studies of <italic>C. pulchellum</italic> extracts and EO need to be carried out in order to ensure it is safe for topical application on the skin.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank our Czech Republic collaborator (Prof Karel Dole&#x0017e;al) for his support. Fajinmi OO gratefully acknowledges Dr Tibor Beres (Centre of the Region Han&#x000e1; for Biotechnological and Agricultural Research, Faculty of Science, Palack&#x000fd; University, Czech Republic); Anthony Hitchcock and Roger Oliver (South African National Biodiversity Institute, Kirstenbosch, Republic of South Africa); Dr Bhekumthetho Ncube (Research Centre for Plant Growth and Development, University of KwaZulu-Natal); Mrs Alison Young (University of KwaZulu-Natal Botanical Garden); and the South African National Biodiversity Institute (Kirstenbosch).</p></sec><sec id="s0012"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>The authors do not have any conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Burtamani</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fatope</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marwah</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Onifade</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaidi</surname><given-names>SH.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year>
<article-title>Chemical composition, antibacterial and antifungal activities of the essential oil of <italic>Haplophyllum tuberculatum</italic> from Oman</article-title>. <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>. <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15588657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>Aromatherapy &#x00026; immunity: how the use of essential oil aids immune potentiality: part 3 immune responses to inflammation and essential oils useful in inhibiting them</article-title>. <source>Int J Aromather</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ba&#x0015f;er</surname><given-names>KHC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demirci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x000d6;zek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Viljoen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>JE.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<article-title>Composition of the essential oils of five <italic>Coleonema s</italic>pecies from South Africa</article-title>. <source>J Essent Oil Res</source>. <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baskaran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moyo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> plant regeneration, phenolic compound production and pharmacological activities of <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic></article-title>. <source>S Afr J Bot</source>. <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylac</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Racine</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of 5-lipoxygenase by essential oils and other natural fragrant extracts</article-title>. <source>Int J Aromather</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhagra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganju</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guleria</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanga</surname><given-names>AK.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title><italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> dermatophytosis in a patient of acquired immunodeficiency syndrome: a rare case report</article-title>. <source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source>. <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23883721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braconi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernardini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santucci</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>
<article-title>Post-genomics and skin inflammation (review article)</article-title>. <source>Mediat Inflamm</source>. <volume>2010</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brader</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year>
<article-title>Prenylated phenylpropenes from <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> with antimicrobial activity</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9272968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Briganti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Picardo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>
<article-title>Antioxidant activity, lipid peroxidation and skin diseases. What's new</article-title>. <source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14761133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lassak</surname><given-names>EV.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year>
<article-title>Volatile leaf oil of <italic>Coleonema pulchellum</italic> I. Williams (Rutaceae)</article-title>. <source>Flavour Frag J</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Candi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Melino</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year>
<article-title>The cornified envelope: a model of cell death in the skin</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15803139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catal&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Lipid peroxidation of membrane phospholipids generates hydroxy-alkenals and oxidized phospholipids active in physiological and/or pathological conditions</article-title>. <source>Chem Phys Lipids</source>. <volume>157</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18977338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chisolm</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year>
<article-title>The oxidative modification hypothesis of atherogenesis: an overview</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <volume>8</volume><fpage>:1815</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1826</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical Laboratory Standards</collab></person-group>
<year>2002</year>. Reference method for broth dilution antifungal susceptibility testing of filamentous fungi. Approved standard M38-A. National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards, Wayne, Pennysylvia.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deigner</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hermetter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>
<article-title>Oxidized phospholipids: emerging lipid mediators in pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source>. <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18460921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demmig-Adams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WW.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title>Antioxidants in photosynthesis and human nutrition</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <volume>298</volume>:<fpage>2149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year>
<article-title>Distribution of limnoids in the Rutaceae</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>713</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eldeen</surname><given-names>IMS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory and mycobacterial activity of leaf extracts of <italic>Coleonema album</italic></article-title>. <source>S Afr J Bot</source>. <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esterhuizen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006b</year>
<article-title>Antioxidant activity of metabolites from <italic>Coleonema album</italic> (Rutaceae)</article-title>. <source>Nat Prod Commun</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>375</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Esterhuizen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006a</year>
<article-title>Antimicrobial compounds from <italic>Coleonema album</italic> (Rutaceae)</article-title>. <source>Z Naturforsch C</source>. <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16989307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fajinmi</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amoo</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finnie</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title>Optimization of <italic>in vitro</italic> propagation of <italic>Coleonema album</italic>, a highly utilized medicinal and ornamental plant</article-title>. <source>S Afr J Bot</source>. <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fajinmi</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finnie</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staden</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Factors influencing seed germination of <italic>Coleonema album</italic> &#x02013; an aromatic and medicinal plant</article-title>. <source>Seed Sci Technol</source>. <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akiti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barreiros</surname><given-names>MG.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>
<article-title><italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic> infection in AIDS patient: a case report</article-title>. <source>J An Bras Dermatol</source>. <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Telplitz</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilshner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hershenbaum</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year>
<article-title>Prevalence of cutaneous disease in patients with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) or AIDS related complex</article-title>. <source>J Amer Acad Dermatol</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2957397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>PG.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year>
<article-title>Coumarins in the Rutaceae</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>864</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>AI.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year>
<article-title>New coumarins from <italic>Coleonema album</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1713</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutteridge</surname><given-names>JMC.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year>
<chapter-title>Lipid peroxidation: some problems and concepts</chapter-title>, In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Oxygen radicals and tissue injury</source>. <publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FASEB</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aruoma</surname><given-names>OI.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year>
<article-title>DNA damage by oxygen-derived species. Its mechanism and measurement in mammalian systems</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett</source>. <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1849843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Havlickova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Czaika</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>
<article-title>Epidemiological trends in skin mycoses worldwide</article-title>. <source>Mycoses</source>. <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18783559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tagliaferro</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bobilya</surname><given-names>DJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title>Flavonoid antioxidants: chemistry, metabolism and structure-activity relationships</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12550068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinecke</surname><given-names>JW.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year>
<article-title>Oxidants and antioxidants in the pathogenesis of atherosclerosis: implications for the oxidized low density lipoprotein hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Atherosclerosis</source>. <volume>141</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9863534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KH.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<chapter-title>Dermatologic manifestations in HIV disease</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KCW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>HIV Manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Integrated Treatment Centre, Special Preventive Programmes, Department of Health</publisher-name> p. <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoult</surname><given-names>JRS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year>
<article-title>Pharmacological and biochemical actions of simple coumarins: natural products with therapeutic potential</article-title>. <source>Gen Pharmacol</source>. <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8853310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boguniewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Debenedetto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>DY.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Cytokine modulation of atopic dermatitis filaggrin skin expression</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>. <volume>124</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamanos</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sotiropoulou</surname><given-names>DEK.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Field studies of nitrogen application on Greek oregano (<italic>Origanum vulgare</italic>) essential oil during two cultivation seasons</article-title>. <source>Ind Crop Prod</source>. <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kolodziej</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year>
<article-title>Antibacterial activity of simple coumarins: structural requirements for biological activity</article-title>. <source>Z Naturforsch C</source>. <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10349736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<article-title>Synthetic and natural coumarins as antioxidants</article-title>. <source>Mini Rev Med Chem</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16613573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duchnik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title>Oxidative stress and skin diseases: possible role of physical activity</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source>. <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>568</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24568458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferroud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupuis-Hamelin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mauvais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lassaigne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnefoy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musicki</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year>
<article-title>Synthesis and <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of novel highly potent coumarin inhibitors of gyrase B</article-title>. <source>Bioorg Med Chem Lett</source>. <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2084</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liebenberg</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year>
<article-title>Evaluation of biologically active compounds in <italic>Coleonema album</italic>.</article-title> [Masters Degree Dissertation]. South Africa: University of Johanessburg.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lis-Balchin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title><italic>Coleonema album</italic>: studies of the pharmacological action on smooth muscle <italic>in vitro</italic> and antimicrobial action of its essential oil</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res</source>. <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12164282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>DNA microarray analyses and interactomic predictions for atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Dermatol Sci</source>. <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19443183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marenholz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nickel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x000fc;schendorf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esparza-Gordillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerscher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#x000fc;ber</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Filaggrin loss-of-function mutations predispose to phenotypes involved in the atopic march</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>. <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>871</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Cayuela</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year>
<article-title>Oxygen free radicals and human disease</article-title>. <source>Biochimica</source>. <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moure</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dominquez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sineiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dominquez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parajo</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>Natural antioxidants from residual sources</article-title>. <source>Food Chem</source>. <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Aids and STI Control Program</collab></person-group>
<year>2008</year> Dermatological manifestations of the HIV disease. In: National manual for the management of HIV-related opportunistic infections and conditions. Baltech Equipments Limited., Kenya, pp. <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crespi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penman</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wishnok</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>SR.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year>
<article-title>DNA damage and mutation in human cells exposed to nitric oxide <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>3030</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3034</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1557408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Lipid peroxidation: physiological levels and dual biological effects</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19500666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okunade</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elvin-Lewis</surname><given-names>MPF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>WH.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year>
<article-title>Natural antimycobacterial metabolites: current status</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1017</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1032</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hampsch-Woodill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>RL.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>Development and validation of an improved oxygen radical absorbance capacity assay using fluorescein as the fluorescent probe</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>4619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4626</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11599998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CNA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terron-Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goudie</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandilands</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Common loss-of-function variants of the epidermal barrier protein filaggrin are a major predisposing factor for atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>446</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16550169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Isolation and characterization of dermatophytes with <italic>Tinea</italic> infections at Gwalior (MP), India</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharm Sci Invent</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Preedy</surname><given-names>VR.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year>
<source>Essential oil in food preservation, flavour and safety</source>. <edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhind</surname><given-names>JP.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<source>Aromatherapeutic blending: Essential oils in synergy</source>. <edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Singing Dragon</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burdon</surname><given-names>RH.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year>
<source>Free radical damage and its control</source>. <edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Amsterdam, Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudikoff</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title>The relationship between HIV infection and atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Curr Allergy Asthma Rep</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12044260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Farwanah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willrodt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huebner</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandhoff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roop</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title>Nrf2 links epidermal barrier function with antioxidant defense</article-title>. <source>EMBO Mol Med</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>379</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<article-title>Fungitoxicity of the essential oil of <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> on post-harvest pathogens</article-title>. <source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>. <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>593</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivaranjani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajeev</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Role of reactive oxygen species and antioxidants in atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Diagn Res</source>. <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2685</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24551611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De C&#x000e1;ssia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gullo</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scorzoni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giannini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>AMF.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Anti dermatophytic therapy-prospects for the discovery of new drugs from natural products</article-title>. <source>Braz J Microbiol</source>. <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1041</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24688490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadtman</surname><given-names>ER.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year>
<chapter-title>Protein modification in oxidative stress</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samuelsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catapano</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rinetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Oxidative processes and antioxidants</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Raven Press</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thestrup</surname><given-names>PK.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year>
<article-title>Clinical aspects of atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source>. <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11122225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>JJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>
<article-title>Oxidative targets in the stratum corneum. A new basis for antioxidative strategies</article-title>. <source>Skin Pharmacol Appl Skin Physiol</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trouba</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamadeh</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Germolec</surname><given-names>DR.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title>Oxidative stress and its role in skin disease</article-title>. <source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12230879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ICT.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year>
<chapter-title>Dermatologic manifestations in HIV disease</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JCY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, editors, <source>HIV Manual 2007</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong Special Administrative Region Government</publisher-name>; p. <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Wyk</surname><given-names>B-E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gericke</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year>
<source>People's plants. A guide to useful plants of Southern Africa</source>. <edition>1st ed.</edition><publisher-loc>Briza, Pretoria, South Africa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Briza Publications</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>FADTG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carels</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundvig</surname><given-names>DMS.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Targeting the redox balance in inflammatory skin conditions: review.</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>9126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23624605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weidinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Illig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baurecht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz-Lacava</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klopp</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagenpfeil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Loss-of-function variations within the filaggrin gene predispose for atopic dermatitis with allergic sensitizations</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>. <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16815158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasprzak</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maragos</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elespuru</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunams</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cebula</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al</etal></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>DNA deaminating ability and genotoxicity of nitric oxide and its progenitors</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <volume>254</volume>:<fpage>1001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1003</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1948068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weldon</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year>
<article-title>The scent of the reticulate giraffe (<italic>Giraffa camelopardalis reticulata</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Biochem Syst Ecol</source>. <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>917</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasser</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nabil</surname><given-names>HO.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title>Anti-inflammatory new coumarin from the <italic>Ammi majus</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Org Med Chem Lett</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22373472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>